1 Introduction

When we started this book, our major motivator was to understand the role of the system of multilateral development banks (MDBs) in promoting both debt and development. Despite the 2007–8 Global Financial Crisis (GFC), it was clear that debt was again rapidly building in many countries and that the development paradigm was shifting, partly thanks to Chinese influence. While scholars had written about the impact of some of the MDBs, it seemed odd to us that there was no comprehensive picture or analysis of the MDB system; and in this work, we identify 30 of them. Since commencing the book, COVID-19 emerged, which added a whole new level of urgency to our task because multilateral development finance (MDF) is a major source of finance for many Global South countries in their response to the health, social, and economic consequences of the pandemic. Debt build-up was a global concern prior to COVID-19, with the World Bank calling the build-up in emerging markets and developing economies (EMDEs) between 2010 and 2018, the ‘largest, fastest and most broad-based increase’ in the past half century (Kose et al. 2020, 111). Yet, states around the world, especially the poorest, need additional resources to limit the scale of the pandemic’s human tragedy.

As the saying goes, we have seen this film before, and we know how it ends – with another debt crisis. In just the past four decades, the major crises have been the 1982 Developing World Debt Crisis, 1997 Asian Financial Crisis, and 2007–8 GFC. Of course, history does not repeat itself and each crisis had specific drivers, features, and triggers but all involved a significant debt build-up, unregulated financial ‘innovations,’ and a trigger – often a banking or financial crisis, though this time it may be a virus.

The MDBs were key building blocks of the post-Second World War financial order and they have multiple ways they operate in that system (Culpeper 1997). They:

Provide states with increased access to finance;

Signal a state’s creditworthiness to private financiers and thus promote the expansion of private sector lending across the globe;

‘De-risk’ projects to bring in private finance;

Advocate financial liberalisation by persuasively ‘educating’ policymakers and, when that fails by attaching coercive policy conditionalities to loans;

Develop ‘innovative’ (i.e., risky) financial instruments to underpin their loans and encourage EMDEs to utilise them; and

Expand debt relations within countries via policy diffusion, loans to governments and financial intermediaries, and projects supporting the financialisation of households.

The MDBs have been players in the handling of each new debt crisis. Yet, the building blocks analogy is problematic because the international financial system does not have a solid foundation. The regulatory regime relies, on the one hand, on inter-state cooperation, which is increasingly hard to achieve, and, on the other hand, on rules for private finance that they have themselves established to suit their own interests. There is no orderly default mechanism for states.

The development banks have shaped thinking about what development means and how to go about it. The World Bank is a leader in this field. Over 25 years ago, George and Sabelli (1994, 5) compared the Bank’s role in development discourse to the medieval Christian church, arguing that it ‘has a doctrine, a rigidly structured hierarchy preaching and imposing this doctrine and a quasi-religious model of self-justification.’ There is still truth in that comparison; core elements of the neoliberal banking doctrine remain, though the Bank has evolved its thinking in a range of areas and understanding the detail is vital. What is less understood is how the 29 other MDBs operate: what are their similarities and differences? It is our hope to shed some light on these questions by exploring the system of MDBs.

MDF is a mechanism through which regional and international organisations arrange loans, credits, and guarantees for investments in countries, generally with the aim of fostering economic growth. The MDBs are a key source of MDF. All MDBs follow the mould of the World Bank, which commenced operations in 1946. Since then, their number and type have flourished. Regional, sub-regional, and specialised MDBs have emerged across the globe. While the flow of MDB creation turned to a trickle in the late 1970s, it did not stop, even in the neoliberal age of the 1980s on, which was seemingly hostile to the public facilitation of capital. Some banks have faced near-catastrophic challenges, but we have found only one MDB not currently operating, though it still exists on paper. So, here are further important questions: why do new MDBs keep getting created and why have they persisted? The two most recent MDBs established in the mid-2010s – the BRICS-led New Development Bank (NDB) and China-led Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank (AIIB) – reignited debate on the MDBs and their role in the global order. And yet there is still no book-length study of the MDB system.

To understand what the MDBs do, one need look no further than their name (Babb 2009, 6): their ownership is multilateral, in contrast to national development finance institutions (DFIs); they focus on development, taking a predominantly economic approach; and, they are banks, mainly providing loans and not grants like some other aid agencies. Most of the MDBs have charters – or Articles of Agreement, as they tend to be called – modelled upon the World Bank. They are organised as shareholding corporations, with the size of their capital bases determining their lending capacity. They originally prioritised lending for infrastructure but have come to work in a range of sectors. Our approach covers all MDBs. We do not make artificial distinctions between those working in the Global North and South as some research has done.

The staff of the World Bank and five regional development banks (RDBs) number over 24,000. If we add in the 24 sub-regional and specialised development banks, that number would be closer to 30,000, which compares to the United Nation’s 44,000 employees but with a narrower field of operations. The MDBs also contract thousands of consultants and indirectly influence tens of thousands of recruits on the projects they fund. In 2018, the 30 MDBs in our study had a total capitalisation of over $1.3 trillion and some $222.7 billion in new lending commitments.^1 Many commentators like to point out that the scale of MDB loans relative to private markets is low (see Ahluwalia et al. 2016). There is some truth in that. According to the International Monetary Fund (IMF), total global public and private debt reached $188 trillion in 2018. Still, the MDBs and other public DFIs ‘are the pin on which the upside down pyramid of investment is crowded in from the rest of the private sector and bilaterals, who are reassured that their risk is controllable because of the presence of IFI capital in a country, sector, project, company or bank. It is the underwriting function’ of MDBs that is vital to bilateral and private finance (Bracking 2009, 54).

Investments can often be beneficial to a state’s development, but debt-based operations are more complicated. Debt is a ‘matter of morality’ (Graeber 2014, 8). Debt predated money but as bullion money became the basis for daily human relations, debt became something else, something unlike any other obligation thanks to the fact that it ‘can be precisely quantified. This allows debts to become simple, cold, and impersonal – which, in turn, allows them to be transferable’ (Graeber 2014, 13). Yet, despite often horrific and violent consequences, debt relations have expanded at an incredible pace since the Second World War and particularly since the financial liberalisation of the 1970s that went along with the rise of neoliberalism. The rapidity with which debt was again pushed on states and people and hailed as the solution to poverty, low growth rates, and even climate adaptation after the GFC was astonishing. Financial innovation and financialisation are again on the rise, with the latter being ‘where the financial sector grows faster, or appropriates a larger share of profits than, manufacturing or trading in goods and services’ (Gabor 2018, 1).

The rest of this chapter is occupied, first, with outlining our somewhat eclectic theoretical framework, which is influenced by both Critical Theory and Constructivism. Our book is deeply informed by our theoretical engagement, but as a text on the entire MDB system we have a lot of material to cover, thus we keep our theoretical musings short. The second part of this chapter defines what we mean by MDF and the MDBs and explains how we have categorised the MDB system. In this process, we outline the structure of the book and the key questions driving it.

1.1 Theorising the MDBs: Critical Theory and Constructivism

The MDBs embody a set of theoretical ideas and their work is framed by sets of beliefs and ideas too. As John Maynard Keynes (1973, 383), the lead theoretical architect of the MDB system, famously put it, even ‘[p]ractical men [and women] who believe themselves to be quite exempt from any intellectual influence, are usually the slaves of some defunct economist.’ This book is a collaboration of two scholars of International Relations (IR), or more precisely from the field of International Political Economy (IPE), meaning we have a strong focus on the international level and the intersection of politics and economics. The MDBs are important case studies in this regard. Indeed, there are only a handful of other formal international organisations (IOs) that are as important to this intersection as the MDBs.

While the authors of this book share an overarching IPE framework, we diverge in theoretical approach. Susan Engel adopts a neo-Gramscian/Critical Theory lens and Adrian Robert Bazbauers draws on Constructivism and Organisational Sociology. Both of us have seriously engaged with each other’s approach and we consider there is overlap between the two approaches but equally that theoretical eclecticism is a strength.

The three core tenets broadly uniting Constructivist IR (see Copeland 2006, Park 2018, Wendt 1995) can be explored to reveal commonalities and differences with neo-Gramscian scholarship. First, Constructivism seeks to understand global social relations. While mainstream IR/IPE theories Neo-realism and Neo-liberalism attempt to predict causal outcomes, Constructivism seeks to understand social interactions. The Italian neo-Marxist Antonio Gramsci (1971) does have moments in his writing where he tends to determinism (Anderson 1976), but, as with contemporary neo-Gramscian scholarship, Susan focusses on Gramsci’s historicist mode (Engel 2010). Thus both approaches share a focus on social relations, but a neo-Gramscian account interrogates how elites construct hegemonic power and how working classes might progress positive social change and human well-being (Engel 2010, Rupert 1998).

The second core tenet uniting Constructivism is the view that the world is socially constructed through the social relations of actors sharing intersubjective meanings; ideas, rules, and norms are constitutive and shape actor behaviour appropriate for their fields, a point explored by Adrian in analyses of the World Bank (Bazbauers 2016, 2018, 2019a, 2019b). Gramsci had similar concerns in his analysis of hegemony, focussing on leadership, alliances, and networks as well as ideas and ideology, which not only organise human action and thought but frequently produce a reductionist ‘common sense’ (Gramsci 1971, Simon 1991). Norms, which Constructivists label standards ‘of appropriate behavior for actors with a given identity’ (Finnemore and Sikkink 1998, 891), certainly have much overlap with Gramscian scholarship, although neo-Gramscians contend that this literature lacks sufficient engagement with power and does not give enough attention to the social relations of production (Wills 2017).

Constructivism’s third common tenet is that non-material factors are positioned above material ones in understanding global social relations. Constructivist IR does not dismiss material factors entirely, however. Wendt (1999, 96) argued that ‘brute material facts’ exist, constraining but not determining ideational factors; it is ‘not ideas all the way down.’ The contrast with the material-focussed Neo-realism and Neo-liberalism is clear. For Constructivists, material features exist, but their meaning is shaped through social action producing intersubjective understandings. Gramsci’s approach to the material and non-material is best understood through his concept of the ‘historic bloc,’ which is Gramsci’s term to explain how dominant groups predominate for long periods (Simon 1991). Historic blocs emerge from the production and the distribution of goods and services but are also based in culture, religion, theory, and ideology (Lears 1985), in other words there is a dialectical relationship between the material and non-material. Gramsci took a dynamic approach to studying historic blocs and encouraged attention to both short-term non-structural changes and long-term structural changes. Overall, while both approaches share an interest in the material and non-material, material interests are more prominent in neo-Gramscian analysis.

Applied to the MDBs, our approaches view the IOs as embedded in broader social orders, in our case a focus on their role in debt dynamics as a way they reproduce contemporary social relations. The reader will see that Susan’s neo-Gramscian view of debt relations as capitalist and often exploitative frames much of the analysis on this issue. The shared concern with ideas means that the book engages extensively with the development paradigms at play in the MDBs at the macro, meso, and micro levels, trying to both deconstruct them and understand their relationship to practices that might best progress human well-being. Adrian’s Constructivist analysis emphasises the role of internal organisational traits – like bureaucratic and normative structures – and external institutional characteristics – such as social networks and intersubjective meanings shared within MDF – and is visible in the study of the individual MDBs and how they constitute a system.

1.1.1 The MDBs from a Critical Theory perspective

Key ontological and epistemological priorities of a neo-Gramscian approach are outlined above. One concept, however, needs further explanation: hegemony. Hegemony occurs when a dominant class builds an effective historic bloc that controls the social system predominantly through consent rather than coercion and force (Cox 1983, Gill and Law 1993). A hegemonic system sees subservient classes acceding to the dominant one because of their consent to practices and ideologies established by the dominant class, which restrict alternatives, frame thought, and instil legitimacy, thus establishing a ‘common sense’ for all members of a community (Cox 1992). Hegemonic common sense can be resisted, however, and an historic bloc can breakdown through (i) an ‘organic crisis’ that destroys the social, economic, and political relations of a hegemonic system, (ii) a ‘passive revolution’ by the dominant group from above to resist potentially transformative change, and (iii) the actions of a counter-hegemonic movement, whereby subaltern classes undermine the historic bloc (Morton 2007, Murphy 2005, Rupert 1998).

Robert Cox (1986, 1996, 1992, 1983) was one of the first scholars to apply Gramsci’s concepts to the global arena, constructing a schema to analyse hegemonic and non-hegemonic forces globally by considering the levels of social forces, states, and world orders. At the level of world orders, the historic bloc concept is deployed as a transnational entity. These are organic, involve more than one class, and include ‘government institutions and civil societies of a number of countries including weak states’ (Gill 1986, 211). IOs play a significant role in world orders, legitimising hegemonic norms, co-opting the elites of developing countries, and absorbing counter-hegemonic narratives (Cox 1986). Given that ‘world hegemony is thus in its beginnings an outward expansion of the internal (national) hegemony established by a dominant social class’ (Cox 1996, 137), neo-Gramscian analyses of IOs have tended to emphasise the role played by the US and pax Americana in establishing global governance actors like the World Bank and IMF and the role such IOs play in securing a transnational historic bloc designed to reinforce US intellectual and cultural hegemony, notably on economic policy. Susan’s earlier work on the World Bank took this approach (Engel 2010); however, she has shifted views somewhat, influenced by work challenging the state-centric conception of hegemony, which argues it is increasingly incompatible with a globalised world. It is vital to move towards a transnational framing that recognises horizontal connections between social forces across and between national and transnational institutions (Robinson 2005, 2015).

This approach helps to explain the emergence of the two new MDBs: the AIIB and NDB. While the BRICS do reflect shifting structural power at the level of world orders (see Bond 2016 for a summary of analyses), a transnational capitalist approach highlights that the MDBs do not challenge the ideational base of the world order. Indeed, they support it. At best, as Stephen (2014, 914) argues, the BRICS ‘pose a within-system challenge to global governance: they challenge its most liberal content, while becoming dependent on, and engaging with, its existing institutional structures.’ Such a within-system challenge may produce a more multipolar, diverse international system, but it is unlikely to displace the inegalitarian order itself (Robinson 2014); variability in the system does not mean the historic bloc is being substantively challenged. This is not to say that states are irrelevant. Significantly, the US retains quite a degree of power over the World Bank and several other MDBs and has not been willing to relinquish that control and ‘BRICS capitalism exhibits a greater role for state regulation and public sectors… What this simply tells us is that “varieties of capitalism” produce “varieties of integration” into global capitalism’ (Robinson 2015, 17–18).

This brings us to one final point: the global system has been managing structural crisis resulting from capitalism’s tendency to overaccumulation and the resultant inequality for some time, but the crisis is becoming more acute. One of the World Bank’s key roles was to ensure that capital was provided where it was most needed, initially in the context of capital shortages. However, as the Keynesian, modernisation, welfare model was overturned, inequalities increased (Piketty 2014) and the propensity for capital to accumulate more rapidly than could be productively reinvested in the production or exchange of goods and services grew (Harvey 2005, 2010, Soederberg 2006). The MDB system is supportive of the ways capitalism has tended to deal with crisis. Harvey (2010) identified three key avenues. One is a spatial fix, meaning geographical expansion and spatial reorganisation. Here the growth and expansion of the MDBs has allowed the greater penetration of economies that would not normally be regarded as ‘bankable.’ A second fix is temporal – excess capital is invested into long-term activities, which take many years before returning capital to circulation. Infrastructural investments by the MDBs are classic examples of this and the current focus of the MDBs on de-risking projects for the private sector rather than investing themselves facilitates greater reach. The third fix is where the preceding two intertwine: ‘spatio-temporal’ fixes. Again, MDB projects do this, including signalling investment feasibility to private capital; the capacity to influence capital markets and shape government policy is of greater consequence than the money the MDBs lend.

1.1.2 The MDBs from a Constructivist perspective

Constructivism is not a substantive theory of international politics but rather an attempt to understand social relations and the fluid intersections between the global, regional, and national. Drawing from sociology, Constructivism sees social reality as built on collective understandings produced and reproduced by people; ‘people always construct, or constitute, social reality, even as their being, which can only be social, is constructed for them’ (Onuf 1989, 1) – hence the term ‘Constructivism.’

In understanding the behaviour of IOs, Constructivist IR/IPE is often positioned in contrast to the rationalist principal-agent model. The model proposes that principals, such as states, delegate authority to agents, such as IOs, to perform tasks for the principal thereby maximising benefits and reducing costs for the principal (Snidal and Tamm 2018). Beyond ontological and epistemological distinctions, a central difference between the two relates to the autonomy of IOs from their principals. Whereas the principal-agent model argues that ‘member governments sometimes empower their IO agents with real decision-making authority’ (Nielson and Tierney 2003, 242 emphasis added), Constructivists tend to regard IOs as far more autonomous.

Barnett and Finnemore (1999) argued that IOs have their own bureaucracies and authority and are thus empowered to act autonomously of their principals. IO autonomy is significant in recognising that the MDBs are not simply artefacts controlled by shareholders but are capable of exercising their own authority (Snidal and Tamm 2018). While the US is influential in the World Bank, even there its power varies over time and by issue. In the MDB system, the distribution of internal shareholder power varies greatly too, as does the relative power of shareholders to influence their MDBs. This creates an opportunity to explore in detail the autonomy of the MDBs relative to their principals (Humphrey and Michaelowa 2013), especially when analysing the institutionalisation of behavioural norms in the MDF architecture (Hanlon 2017, 546).

The focus of Constructivism on institutional fields derives from Organisational Sociology and seeks to understand IOs not just in terms of inter-state relations but in reference to organisational dynamics and their broader social relations in producing and reproducing intersubjective meanings (Koch and Stetter 2013). This has led to a central focus on institutions, which Scott (2008, 48) defines as ‘comprised of regulative, normative, and cultural-cognitive elements that… provide stability and meaning to social life.’ An institutional field is the architecture of procedures, routines, norms, and conventions that surround organisations within their field. For the MDBs, this means the institutional field of MDF, which they, in turn, shape. A key insight coming out of the literature that is very relevant to the MDB system is the process of institutional isomorphism – this work highlights how IO operations become normalised and their organisational behaviour and culture similar over time due to social influence, coercive and persuasive forces, and socialisation (Acharya 2009, Finnemore and Sikkink 1998, 2001, Park 2006, 2014).

Constructivist IPE aligns with new institutionalism, which is comprised of numerous theoretical strands (see Lowndes and Roberts 2010), of which the sociological variant is the most relevant here. New institutionalism posits that organisational behaviour is not reducible to rational or functional pursuits (Bell 2011, DiMaggio 1998). Organisations of course need to ensure their own effectiveness, but the drive to demonstrate legitimacy is, in fact, more important (Frandsen and Johansen 2013). Organisational convergence derives from the pursuit of legitimacy, an end-state facilitated by the production and reproduction of social facts through institutional isomorphism. Three forces drive institutionalisation (DiMaggio and Powell 1983, 150–2): (i) coercive isomorphism derives from formal pressures, such as legal regulations, exerted on actors to conform to prescribed behaviour; (ii) mimetic isomorphism arises in places of industry ambiguity leading new organisations to model themselves on more established organisations; and, (iii) normative isomorphism relates to professional and occupational standards that produce conformity in an industry. These forces are all visible in MDF and help the MDBs demonstrate their legitimacy and thus survival.

Institutional processes are not passive. Power relations pervade institutional structures and not only are such structures powerful in conditioning behaviour, but organisations exercise power in shaping their institutional fields (Lawrence and Buchanan 2017); Constructivists regard this as the production and reproduction of social facts. The World Bank, for example, has exercised considerable influence in shaping MDF. Further, isomorphic processes are not neat and tidy. Organisations adapt and change in often difficult and confusing ways, contingent upon internal organisational exigencies and rational bureaucratic factors.

IOs are thus defined by their formal bureaucratic structures and juridical personalities as well as their social embeddedness in global institutional fields (Abdenur and Folly 2015). Further, the staff employed by them are socialised and normalised into the formal and informal practices of their organisations while also being sought by IOs for their expertise, experience, and socialised skills necessary to align with organisational and institutional priorities (Malkin and Momani 2016). IO staff members emerge from and are socialised within communities of practice (Haas 1992), or are sought out as they already possess beliefs derived from their training and experience in related organisations. Demonstrating linkages to neo-Gramscian thought, we can say that those employed by MDBs are part of a transnational technocratic elite institutionalised within particular normative frameworks (Robinson 2015).

1.2 Structure of the book

MDF involves regional and international organisations arranging loans, credits, and guarantees for investment in economic development. The focus on multilateral finance means we exclude bilateral finance provided by states to other states and to the private sector for development purposes. This, unfortunately, means excluding some quite important areas of development finance, including:

Government-sponsored or quasi-governmental export credit agencies (ECAs, sometimes called export-import banks): these provide credit, insurance, and guarantees to facilitate a country’s exports. ECAs preceded the MDBs – as outlined in Chapter 2 – and they operate in around 85 countries today. They are significant creditors to EMDEs, they work with the MDBs, and they are a key part of the broader DFI network that few scholars have explored, one exception being Bracking (2009).

Bilateral aid agencies that include loan programmes in their development assistance. The US initially developed loan schemes in a de facto form through the 1954 Agricultural Trade and Development Assistance Act, which allowed local currency repayment for US agricultural products. In 1957, the US established the Development Loan Fund, which has been through several titles and seemed in danger of being defunded, but competition from China saw the US establish the International Development Finance Corporation in 2019. A range of other bilateral aid agencies also provide loans, including established donors – such as Japan and Germany – and some new ones, like Thailand.

Domestic development banks: these generally commenced with a domestic mandate but have expanded to provide development finance to other states as well. The BRICS have become important players in this area. The China Development Bank, for example, is twice the size of the World Bank and has increasingly engaged in cross-border projects, as has the large Brazilian Development Bank (BNDES). The MDBs sometimes lend to domestic development banks as financial intermediaries.

The function of the MDBs as lenders and guarantors evolved out of the long history of debt, money, inter-state lending, and inter-state cooperation. This is the focus of Chapter 2, which offers a brief longue durée record of these topics. The direct ancestors of the MDBs are the ECAs, set up in the Global North just after the turn of the 20th century, to assist exporters but their focus on geostrategic allies and former colonies led them to have a developmental element. Further, US financial cooperation with Latin America included discussions on forming an inter-American bank from the late 1880s and in 1939 a Mexican delegation proposed that this bank should channel investment to promote economic development in the Americas (Villaseñor 1941). Thus, Chapter 2 demonstrates that, rather than being an American idea, the MDBs may well be a Mexican one. Still, the first MDB did not come into being until the US was behind the idea at the 1944 Bretton Woods Conference, where the establishing agreement of the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD) – alongside its ‘sibling,’ the IMF – was signed.

Chapters 3 and 4 tell the story of the evolution of the 31 MDBs, 30 of which are functional (see Table 1.1). Chapter 3 starts in 1946, when the IBRD – today known as the World Bank, alongside its concessional arm, the International Development Association (IDA) – became operational and outlines the key issues and debates that shaped its creation. It explores the expansion of the MDB system from 1956 to 1979, when a further 21 MDBs were founded. The early growth of the MDB system is linked to the post-war Keynesian, welfare, modernisation model (Fine 2001) and the mandates of most MDBs from this period reflect this. The chapter concludes with the first major post-war debt crisis, the 1982 Debt Crisis, demonstrating on the MDBs relationship with, and response to, debt.

Table 1.1 Development banks by type

Decade | Specialised | Regional | Sub-regional
2010s | Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank (2015) New Development Bank (2014)
2000s | Eurasian Development Bank (2006) ECO Trade and Development Bank (2005)
1990s | European Bank for Reconstruction and Development(1991) | Black Sea Trade and Development Bank (1997)
1980s | Pacific Islands Development Bank (1989) Eastern and Southern African Trade and Development Bank (1985) Development Bank of the States of Great Lakes (1980)a
1970s | International Fund for Agricultural Development (1977) OPEC Fund for International Development (1976) Nordic Investment Bank (1976) Islamic Development Bank (1974) Arab Bank for Economic Development in Africa (1974) Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development (1971) | ECOWAS Bank for Investment and Development (1975) Development Bank of Central African States (1975) FONPLATA Development Bank (1974) West African Development Bank (1973) International Investment Bank (1970) Development Bank of Latin America (1970) Caribbean Development Bank (1970)
1960s | Asian Development Bank (1966) African Development Bank (1963) | East African Development Bank (1967) International Bank for Economic Cooperation (1963) Central American Bank for Economic Integration (1960)
1950s | Council of Europe Development Bank (1956) | Inter-American Development Bank (1959) European Investment Bank (1958)
1945 | World Bank (global)

a No longer functional.

Chapter 4 analyses the period from 1980 to 2020, an era when a further eight still-functional MDBs were established. The focus is again on the inter-relationships between the MDBs, geopolitics, debt, and development discourse. The chapter thus explores the evolution of neoliberalism, which came to dominate thinking in the World Bank and many other MDBs, particularly in the policy prescriptions they suggested to developing countries between 1980 and 1997, a period known as the Washington Consensus era. With the 1997 Asian Financial Crisis, hardline Washington Consensus prescriptions were discredited and, in the attempt to revitalise neoliberal development discourse, the post-Washington Consensus era began. It combined some core neoliberal ideas with the Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) and a global interest in poverty alleviation to produce a small window of time where the global development agenda was somewhat more progressive and human centred. However, this period closed with the 2008 GFC and was replaced with the retroliberal development agenda (Murray and Overton 2016) and the re-emergence of a more state-centric, nationalist discourse promoting debt-not-grants and an excessive focus on infrastructural investment.

Chapter 5 examines the formal structure of the MDBs, using the World Bank as a model. It delves into how their structures have shaped them as organisations, exploring voting rights and capital subscriptions. We highlight how the MDBs need to issue bonds on international capital markets to raise funds, which has given capital markets and credit rating agencies considerable influence over them. The banking and development agendas of the MDBs frequently conflict, with banking norms often taking precedence. The chapter also explores governance structures and loan types, terms, and conditions. Despite the rapid growth in private finance since the 1980s, many private financiers will not lend to low-income countries and there are many projects that they will not fund in middle- and high-income countries because of perceived financial risk, thus the MDBs persist and new ones have been created.

Chapters 6 through 8 analyse the key features, priorities, and frameworks of the 29 MDBs established after the World Bank. Loosely adapting Wihtol’s (2014) typology, we divide the MDBs into regional, sub-regional, and specialised development banks. The RDBs are ‘regional’ in that their mandates support African, Asian, Latin American, and European development, collaboration, and integration. The sub-regional development banks (SRDBs) resemble the RDBs, except that they are typically much smaller and serve sub-regions, such as East Africa or the Caribbean. The specialised banks are more disparate but are unified as niche development financiers; for example, they finance agricultural interventions or provide Islamic development finance.

Chapter 6 focusses on the RDBs, the first of which was the European Investment Bank (EIB) in 1958, a product of the fast-evolving post-war European integration project. EIB was quickly followed by the Inter-American Development Bank (IADB) in 1959 from Latin America. The African Development Bank (AfDB) was established in 1964, emerging remarkably quickly after post-war African decolonisation; between the 1940s and 1960s, the number of independent African states increased from a handful to over 30. The Asian Development Bank (AsDB), founded in 1966, was more a case of a regional power – Japan – pushing the creation of an MDB. Chapter 6 also examines the outlier in RDB creation – the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD), established in 1991 at the height of the Washington Consensus era with the aim of assisting the post-Cold War transition of Soviet states from communism to capitalism.

Chapter 7 turns to the 15 SRDBs, which Culpeper (1997, 54) described as a ‘stratum’ of MDBs ‘that lies below the regional banks; they generally serve a group of borrowers that share borders or geographical or other characteristics and that stand apart from their neighbours in other ways.’ We would add that they were frequently the product of a concern that capital needs were not being met by the World Bank and RDBs and, notably in sub-Saharan Africa, were often the financial arms of formal sub-regional groups. There are some success stories among them, such as the Development Bank of Latin America (CAF) today rivalling the IADB in Latin America, but also stories of failure – the Development Bank of the States of Great Lakes (BDEGL) collapsed in 1993 due to conflict between its members.

Chapter 8 covers the nine specialised banks. These MDBs either have memberships that do not fall along regional lines or have a specialised focus on an area of development, like agriculture or infrastructure. The largest group of these banks is one that we broadly call the ‘Arab-led MDBs’: the Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development (AFESD), Arab Bank for Economic Development in Africa (BADEA), Islamic Development Bank (IsDB), and OPEC Fund for International Development (IsDB). With Arab countries as their largest shareholders, they emerged from pressure imposed on oil exporters after the 1973 oil price shock to expand their international contributions and they did this partly through MDBs. The specialised banks also include the two most recent entrants to the MDB system: first, the NDB, which was established in 2014 and whose membership is currently limited to the five BRICS countries, and, second, the China-led AIIB established in 2015 that prioritises infrastructural investments.

Chapters 9 through 11 explore three of the main areas of MDB operations: infrastructure, climate finance, and human development. As Chapter 9 outlines, infrastructure has always been central to the MDBs. It was a key concern after the destruction of the Second World War and underpinned the Keynesian, welfare, modernisation model. While declining in importance as human needs entered development discourse, it regained its top spot during the current retroliberal era. Infrastructure is vitally important for development but at the same time it is a complicated field. Large projects mean complexity and the likelihood of technical errors, mismanagement, and corruption goes up, as do environmental and social consequences. Problematic infrastructure projects were the key drivers of the MDBs establishing safeguard policies and inspection panels. The retroliberal push for increased infrastructure funding could be very useful for some countries, but is equally likely to provide many failures, leaving a debt legacy that will last many years.

Chapter 10 analyses the development of MDB environmental policies and lending programmes. Despite their culpability in a range of what can only be described as environmental disasters up to the 1980s, the MDBs are now prominent financial agencies in a range of environmental initiatives, including the Global Environment Facility (GEF). Certainly, on paper at least, their environmental policies and safeguards are among the best in the world, but as mainstream development financiers they have taken a long time to reduce their portfolios of carbon projects. Further, the MDBs have promoted the use of innovative financial instruments to expand the climate finance regime. While these instruments may be built on strong financial structures, questions emerge whether they are well suited to assist countries adapt, mitigate, and build resilience to climate change.

Chapter 11 discusses human development, focussing on education, health, and gender. Prior to the 1970s, most MDBs had not funded social projects as they preferred investments with easily quantifiable economic returns. With the introduction of basic needs, absolute and relative poverty, and human development to development discourse, the MDBs slowly began to broaden their understanding of development. Yet, the small percentage that the MDBs allocated to fund such projects prioritised investing in people to improve their productive capacity not improving their quality of life. Further, the MDBs only belatedly – and somewhat reluctantly – came to acknowledge the role of women in development starting in the 1980s, which evolved into gender policies, programmes, and safeguards. While considerable strides have been made over the past few decades, the MDBs continue to approach gendered inequalities as problems that can be ‘fixed’ through the application of the right resources, focussing on creating economic opportunities for women and not addressing structural gendered imbalances.

Note

1 In this study, $ = US dollars, € = Euros, £ = British pounds, and any other currencies are as specified.

Bibliography

Abdenur, Adriana Erthal, and Maiara Folly. 2015. “The New Development Bank and the Institutionalization of the BRICS.” R/evolutions 3:66–92.

Acharya, Amitav. 2009. Whose Ideas Matter? Agency and Power in Asian Regionalism. New York: Cornell University Press.

Ahluwalia, Montek Singh, Lawrence Summers, Andrés Velasco, Nancy Birdsall, and Scott Morris. 2016. Multilateral Development Banking for This Century’s Development Challenges: Five Recommendations to Shareholders of the Old and New Multilateral Development Banks. Washington, DC: Centre for Global Development.

Anderson, Perry. 1976. “The Antinomies of Antonio Gramsci.” New Left Review 100:5–78.

Babb, Sarah. 2009. Behind the Development Banks: Washington Politics, World Poverty, and the Wealth of Nations. Chicago, IL and London: The University of Chicago Press.

Barnett, Michael, and Martha Finnemore. 1999. “The Politics, Power, and Pathologies of International Organizations.” International Organization 53 (4):699–732.

Bazbauers, Adrian Robert. 2016. “The World Bank as a Development Teacher.” Global Governance 22 (3):409–26.

Bazbauers, Adrian Robert. 2018. The World Bank and Transferring Development: Policy Movement through Technical Assistance, International Political Economy Series. Cham: Palgrave Macmillan.

Bazbauers, Adrian Robert. 2019a. “The Relational Dynamics of World Bank Survey Missions.” International Journal of Public Administration 42 (1):28–40. doi: 10.1080/01900692.2017.1390763.

Bazbauers, Adrian Robert. 2019b. “World Bank Technical Assistance: Participation, Policy Movement, and Sympathetic Interlocutors.” Policy Studies:1–19. doi: 10.1080/01442872.2019.1581156.

Bell, Stephen. 2011. “Do We Really Need a New ‘Constructivist Institutionalism’ to Explain Institutional Change?” British Journal of Political Science 41 (4):883–906. doi: 10.1017/S0007123411000147.

Bond, Patrick. 2016. “BRICS Banking and the Debate over Sub-imperialism.” Third World Quarterly 37 (4):611–29.

Bracking, Sarah. 2009. Money and Power: Great Predators in the Political Economy of Development. London: Pluto Press.

Copeland, Dale C. 2006. “The Constructivist Challenge to Structural Realism.” In Constructivism and International Relations: Alexander Wendt and His Critics, edited by Stefano Guzzini, Anna Leander and Barry Buzan, 1–2. Abingdon, Oxon: Routledge.

Cox, Robert W. 1983. “Gramsci, Hegemony and International Relations: An Essay in Method.” Millennium: Journal of International Studies 12 (2):162–75.

Cox, Robert W. 1986. “Social Forces, States and World Orders: Beyond International Relations Theory.” In Neorealism and Its Critics, edited by Robert Keohane, 204–54. New York: Columbia University Press.

Cox, Robert W. 1992. “Multilateralism and World Order.” Review of International Studies 18 (2):161–80.

Cox, Robert W. 1996. “Gramsci, Hegemony, and International Relations: An Essay in Method.” In Approaches to World Order, edited by Robert W. Cox and J. Sinclair, 124–143. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Culpeper, Roy. 1997. Titans or Behemoths? London: Lynne Rienner.

DiMaggio, Paul. 1998. “The New Institutionalisms: Avenues of Collaboration.” Journal of Institutional and Theoretical Economics (JITE) / Zeitschrift für die gesamte Staatswissenschaft 154 (4):696–705.

DiMaggio, Paul, and Walter Powell. 1983. “The Iron Cage Revisited: Institutional Isomorphism and Collective Rationality in Organizational Fields.” American Sociological Review 48 (2):147–60. doi: 10.2307/2095101.

Engel, Susan. 2010. The World Bank and the Post-Washington Consensus in Vietnam and Indonesia: Inheritance of Loss. London: Routledge.

Fine, Ben. 2001. Social Capital versus Social Theory: Political Economy and Social Science at the Turn of the Millennium. London: Routledge.

Finnemore, Martha, and Kathryn Sikkink. 1998. “International Norm Dynamics and Political Change.” International Organization 52 (4):887–917.

Finnemore, Martha, and Kathryn Sikkink. 2001. “TAKING STOCK: The Constructivist Research Program in International Relations and Comparative Politics.” Annual Review of Political Science 4 (1):391–416. doi: 10.1146/annurev.polisci.4.1.391.

Frandsen, Finn, and Winni Johansen. 2013. “Public Relations and the New Institutionalism: In Search of a Theoretical Framework.” Public Relations Inquiry 2 (2):205–21. doi: 10.1177/2046147x13485353.

Gabor, Daniela. 2018. Understanding the Financialisation of International Development through 11 FAQs. Washington, DC: Heinrich Böll Stiftung North America.

George, Susan, and Fabrizio Sabelli. 1994. Faith and Credit: The World Bank’s Secular Empire. London: Penguin Books.

Gill, Stephen. 1986. “Hegemony, Consensus and Trilateralism.” Review of International Studies 12 (3):205–22.

Gill, Stephen, and David Law. 1993. “Global Hegemony and the Structural Power of Capital.” In Gramsci, Historical Materialism and International Relations, edited by Stephen Gill, 93–124. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Graeber, David. 2014. Debt: The First 5,000 Years. Brooklyn, NY: Melville House.

Gramsci, Antonio. 1971. Selections from the Prison Notebooks of Antonio Gramsci. Translated by Quintin Hoare and Geoffrey Nowell Smith. London: Lawrence and Wishart.

Haas, Peter. 1992. “Epistemic Communities and International Policy Coordination.” International Organization 46 (1):1–35.

Hanlon, Robert J. 2017. “Thinking about the Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank: Can a China-Led Development Bank Improve Sustainability in Asia?” Asia & the Pacific Policy Studies 4 (3):541–54. doi: 10.1002/app5.186.

Harvey, David. 2005. The New Imperialism. Oxford: Oxford Unviersity Press.

Harvey, David. 2010. The Enigma of Capital: And the Crises of Capitalism. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

Humphrey, Chris, and Katharina Michaelowa. 2013. “Shopping for Development: Multilateral Lending, Shareholder Composition and Borrower Preferences.” World Development 44:142–55. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2012.12.007.

Keynes, John Maynard. 1973. The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money. London: Macmillan for the Royal Economic Society.

Koch, Martin, and Stephan Stetter. 2013. “Sociological Perspectives on International Organisations and the Construction of Global Political Order: An Introduction.” Journal of International Organizations Studies 4 (Special Issue):5–13.

Kose, M. Ayhan, Peter Nagle, Franziska Ohnsorge, and Naotaka Sugawara. 2020. Global Waves of Debt: Causes and Consequences. Washington DC: World Bank.

Lawrence, Thomas B., and Sean Buchanan. 2017. “Power, Institutions, and Organisations.” In The SAGE Handbook of Organizational Institutionalism, edited by Royston Greenwood, Christine Oliver, Thomas B. Lawrence and Renate E. Meyer, 477–506. London: SAGE Publications.

Lears, T.J. Jackson. 1985. “The Concept of Cultural Hegemony: Problems and Possibilities.” The American Historical Review 90 (3):567–93.

Lowndes, Vivien, and Mark Roberts. 2010. Why Institutions Matter: The New Institutionalism in Political Science. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan.

Malkin, Anton, and Bessma Momani. 2016. “An Effective Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank: A Bottom Up Approach.” Global Policy 7 (4):521–30. doi: 10.1111/1758-5899.12357.

Morton, Adam David. 2007. Unravelling Gramsci: Hegemony and Passive Revolution in the Global Political Economy. London: Pluto Press.

Murphy, Craig N. 2005. Global Institutions, Marginalisation, and Development. London: Routledge.

Murray, Warwick E., and John Overton. 2016. “Retroliberalism and the New Aid Regime of the 2010s.” Progress in Development Studies 16 (3):244–60. doi: 10.1177/1464993416641576.

Nielson, Daniel L., and Michael J. Tierney. 2003. “Delegation to International Organizations: Agency Theory and World Bank Environmental Reform.” International Organization 57 (2):241–76.

Onuf, Nicholas. 1989. World of Our Making: Rules and Rule in Social Theory and International Relations. Columbia: South Carolina University Press.

Park, Susan. 2006. “Theorizing Norm Diffusion within International Organizations.” International Politics 43 (3):342–61. doi: 10.1057/palgrave.ip.8800149.

Park, Susan. 2014. “Institutional Isomorphism and the Asian Development Bank’s Accountability Mechanism: Something Old, Something New; Something Borrowed, Something Blue?” The Pacific Review 27 (2):217–39. doi: 10.1080/09512748.2014.882394.

Park, Susan. 2018. “Constructivism.” In International Organization and Global Governance, edited by Thomas G. Weiss and Rorden Wilkinson, 146–56. Milton: Routledge.

Piketty, Thomas. 2014. Capital in the Twenty-First Century. Cambridge, MA: Belknap Press.

Robinson, William. 2005. “Gramsci and Globalisation: From Nation-State to Transnational Hegemony.” Critical Review of International Social and Political Philosophy 8 (4):559–74.

Robinson, William. 2014. Global Capitalism and the Crisis of Humanity. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Robinson, William. 2015. “The Transnational State and the BRICS: A Global Capitalism Perspective.” Third World Quarterly 36 (1):1–21.

Rupert, Mark. 1998. “(Re-)Engaging Gramsci: A response to Germain and Kenny.” Review of International Studies 24:427–34.

Scott, W. Richard. 2008. Institutions and Organizations: Ideas and Interests. Los Angeles, CA: Sage.

Simon, Roger. 1991. Gramsci’s Political Thought: An Introduction. London: Lawrence & Wishart Ltd. Original edition, 1982.

Snidal, Duncan, and Henning Tamm. 2018. “Rational Choice: From Principal-Agent to Orchestration Theory.” In International Organization and Global Governance, edited by Thomas G. Weiss and Rorden Wilkinson, 135–45. Milton: Routledge.

Soederberg, Susan. 2006. Global Governance in Question: Empire, Class and the New Common Sense in Managing North-South Relations. London: Pluto Press.

Stephen, Matthew. 2014. “Rising Powers, Global Capitalism, and Liberal Global Governance: A Historical Materialist Account of the BRICs Challenge.” European Journal of International Relations 20 (4):912–38.

Villaseñor, Eduardo. 1941. “The Inter-American Bank: Prospects and Dangers.” Foreign Affairs 20 (1):165–74.

Wendt, Alexander. 1995. “Constructing International Politics.” International Security 20 (1):71–81. doi: 10.2307/2539217.

Wendt, Alexander. 1999. Social Theory of International Politics. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Wihtol, Robert. 2014. Whither Multilateral Development Finance? Tokyo: Asian Development Bank Institute.

Wills, Joe J. 2017. Contesting World Order?: Socioeconomic Rights and Global Justice Movements. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

2 Debt, development, and the emergence of multilateral development finance

Some of the most intricate and momentous problems of foreign investment are connected with loans to alien Governments. It has been said that the possession of a national debt is one of the first signs of civilisation. Borrowers are always eager to lend where there is a chance of big profits, and the Governments of weak and backward countries [sic] often fall an easy prey to the wiles of financiers, when they are faced with difficulties, internal or external.

(Hobson 1914, xx–xxi emphasis added).

This chapter start with a brief longue durée examination of the emergence of money and debt. It examines state debt as the precursor to the creation of various kinds of state and multilateral development finance (MDF). It analyses the factors that led to the establishment of the first multilateral development bank (MDB) – the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD), commonly known as the World Bank – in 1944, following earlier proposals for an Inter-American development bank. Positioning MDF within a longer tradition of finance and debt demonstrates its place in the web of globalised finance that slowly emerged since the creation of money. Early state debt mostly financed warfare and empire building, while modern MDF has evolved to focus primarily on development, though war and the arms trade have not been absent. Financial innovation took off from the 1800s and the creation of MDF was part of this. As we shall see in later chapters, the MDBs now play a significant role in spreading financial innovation.

Debt is not, and never has been, an innocent instrument. Regardless of whether it was utilised for warfare, business, or development, money-debt’s logic turns moral questions about debt and credit ‘into a matter of impersonal arithmetic’ (Graeber 2014, 14). Debts must be repaid regardless of the legitimacy of those that took them out or the purposes for which they were taken. Positioning MDBs within a broader expansion of credit relations is vital to the purposes of this book. The MDBs have enhanced the legitimacy of debts – because as banks, they need to ensure they themselves are repaid – and expanded its reach across the world in the context of a post-war financial system that has no orderly mechanism for nation-states to default on debt. The poor, as taxpayers, have borne disproportionate responsibility for debt repayment.

The chapter also examines the more immediate inspirations for the creation of the IBRD. This is important because, in much of the literature, the origins of MDF are either a bit of a mystery or the outcome of Anglo-American negotiations at the 1944 Bretton Woods Conference, which produced the Articles of Agreement of the IMF and IBRD. However, recent historical research has helped correct this and, piecing together the different histories, we posit five key precedents for MDBs, taking analysis well beyond Anglo-American negotiations into US-Latin American cooperation, broader international cooperation, and also to the role of new ideas and hegemonic change.^1

The first precedent is the growth in international cooperation from the mid-1800s and the related belief in human capacity to organise. These helped set the enabling environment for change. The second factor, a contextual one, is the change in international hegemony produced by the First World War, the inter-war chaos, and the Second World War. Even with a transnational theoretical focus, it is clear that the Bretton Woods twins – the IMF and IBRD – were the product of US global hegemony, which was firmly in place by the end of the Second World War. Keynesianism and New Deal politics are the third precedent to MDBs explored in the chapter. Keynes’ academic analysis provided a theoretical backbone for increased economic cooperation between states, explaining why markets left on their own would not necessarily produce good economic or social outcomes.

The fourth precedent to the IBRD is less well known but very important, namely, US economic cooperation with Latin America. This produced a 1940 proposal for an Inter-American development bank, well before the proposal for the IBRD (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010, Helleiner 2014, 2017, Scott-Smith and Rofe 2017). This was a grander proposal than the IBRD and the later iteration of the IADB that emerged in the 1960s. What is equally interesting is that this proposal emerged out of loans that were already being provided to the region through the US Export-Import (Exim) Bank. This link to Exim banks is less well-known and scholars working on development rarely consider the MDBs as part of a larger MDF system (Bracking 2009). The final factor considered in this chapter is US economic planning during the Second World War, which drove thinking about the post-war system.

Taken together, this chapter paints a new picture of MDF’s emergence, one that highlights the tension between MDF’s progressive origins in internationalist ideals of producing a fairer, more inclusive global system and its state-centric origins in promoting a Western world order based on markets and debt. This is significant because this new analysis demonstrates how many of the strengths and limitations of the IBRD were inherent in its development and subsequent MDBs have reproduced this dynamic.

2.1 The growth of inter-state private and public debt

State debt is vital background to the emergence of the MDF system. It is a largely capitalist phenomenon, although the state system predates capitalism and hence understanding MDF’s origins demands a dialectical understanding of capitalism and the state system (Bieler and Morton 2018). As Graeber (2014) argued, money (or bullion) debt owed by empires and states was historically closely linked to war and violence making, whereas credit money systems have generally gone hand-in-hand with more peaceful human epochs. MDF emerged late in the most recent bullion debt era, which started around 1450. It was designed to address war debt and reconstruction problems but became increasingly part of a credit money system promoting development not warfare. At face value, this suggests that MDBs could be part of a more human-friendly future. However, at least two challenges stand in this path. First, so long as debt remains capitalism’s tribute mechanism and there is no mechanism to manage default by states, a shift to credit debt will not reduce the violence traditionally associated with debt collection. Second, development itself is a complex and contested term and MDBs have generally promoted a rather emaciated vision of development as growth plus a minimalist vision of poverty reduction as getting people above the international poverty line of $1.90 a day (Cammack 2004).

Debt and credit have, in fact, been around for a lot longer than money. People in different parts of the world long had informal systems of credit. Money in its bullion form began to appear around 800–500 BCE in Europe, India, and China. Graeber (2014, 213) argued that the single key reason for the rise of money was the increase in warfare because ‘[b]ullion predominates, above all, in periods of generalized violence’; money can be stolen and used to pay soldiers and empires need taxation to fund warfare. Graeber’s first period of bullion money, 800 BCE to 600 CE, saw extensive warfare and the concomitant creation of great empires. As Graeber argued, cash and barter are usually limited to contexts of low trust involving strangers or people who are not credit-worthy, but money provided a problematic mathematical precision to debt that was enforceable, though only with the help of sovereign or state violence. You might lose your home or need to sell your wife or children to pay your debts but that’s ‘incidental to the creditor’ (Graeber 2014, 14). The debt peonage that came from this system resulted in large-scale social unrest and sometimes revolt, so that rulers regularly instituted general debt amnesties to resolve tensions. In contrast, the Middle Ages saw the return to credit money (not a reversion to barter), the fall of empires, bans on slavery across most parts of Eurasia, and an increase in living standards for many ordinary people. The age of capitalist empires, which Graeber (2014, 214) dates from around 1450, saw a return to bullion, slavery (in particular the North Atlantic slave trade), and generalised violence through both inter-state violence and the colonial project. While the core of Graeber’s argument is important, 1450 was a marker in the emergence of the state system, and capitalism appeared much later, from the late 18th century.

Bullion money and conflict were central to the emergent states system. Historically, monarchs and rulers of various kinds borrowed predominately to fund their wars and conflicts (Kindleberger 1984). Indeed, it seems likely that inter-state lending started with loans to allies or nations at war, though private lending was mostly driven by trade (Hobson 1914). Moving into more modern times, borrowing by states was mostly wars-driven too. States and their predecessors borrowed through a range of mechanisms: early on it was common for monarchs to take mostly short-term loans directly from wealthy individuals and later from banks and, as borrowing from banks developed, loan terms lengthened. States also started issuing annuities and later bonds that guaranteed the purchasers a long-term income stream. These were initially to finance wars, but later they backed state infrastructure and development projects. In either case, creditors have been willing to inflict violence directly or economically on those who cannot pay back such debts.

Public or sovereign debt in Europe is generally said to have begun around 1200 CE in both city-states and the growing large centralised monarchical states, though it began earlier in China. The large European states generally borrowed domestically, but they began to borrow internationally too. English King Edward I borrowed extensively from the Ricciardi of Lucca from 1272 to 1310 and defaulted on the debts. In the mid-16th century, the Fuggers from southern Germany are credited with developing ‘financial intermediation, borrowing from wealth-owners and lending to a king’ (Kindleberger 1984, 45). Money lending was, of course, risky and Geisst (2013, 47) expresses the common view that ‘lending to sovereigns in general was riskier than lending to established merchants.’ However, according to Stasavage (2016, 3), the primary lenders to European states were merchants who had gained wealth from long-distance trading and wanted to diversify their risk. This highlights the important point that lending always involves two sets of interests – the lenders and the borrowers – and both sets pursue interests and systems that suit their needs. There have always been winners and losers in the relationship, which has changed over time, often reflecting the relative political weight of the parties (Stasavage 2016). The MDBs were established to reduce risk thus enabling expanded lending to (less credit-worth) countries, but they have always promoted the political interests of lenders.

The city-states began long-term borrowing or fund-raising through annuities and securities from the early 13th century, with the large monarchical states only following a few centuries later. This aligns with Arrighi’s (1994) argument that Italian city-states were the economic hegemons of the 13th and 14th centuries, with the Dutch taking over in the 16th and 17th centuries, the British in the mid-18th century, and the US from the Second World War. Great Britain was slow to issue long-term sovereign debt; it sold its first Treasury order, or what we would now call government bond, in the late 1660s and its first annuity to the public in 1692, the latter to finance a war with France (Geisst 2013, 101–3). MDBs’ primary source of funds today is from issuing bonds. Britain expanded the system with the creation of the Bank of England in 1694 amid the Nine Years’ War, as a corporation of London merchants that could sell government tradeable securities. The Dutch had also already established a national bank in 1609 and these banks became lenders to the crown often to finance wars (Geisst 2013, 106–9). Expansion in the scale of European conflict generated scale and innovation in finance.

After the Reformation in the 16th century, religiously based strictures against usury started to fade and the modern state system began to emerge. International Relations scholars tend to regard the 1648 Peace of Westphalia, which ended the Thirty Years’ War in Europe, as a key marker, though the transition started earlier. This was a time of exploration and commerce, and national and commercial debt was central to expansion (Geisst 2013, 97). Colonialism was largely an extractive venture, whether through plunder, extraction of natural resources, or cash crop production for European markets. Still, extraction and plantations often required investment. The British and Dutch East India Companies – established in 1600 and 1602 – played a key role in international investments. They were initially private companies, yet their existence was bound up with their respective states and the Dutch East India Company was a pioneer of foreign direct investment (FDI). Both public and private investments were central to the formation of colonies (Mikesell 1966), and plantations became a key driver of private investment (Hobson 1914). The colonial states’ investments in their colonies sometimes lasted past their colonial role. For example, the British crown had investments in the US after independence (Geisst 2013, 131). These investments were a way of returning capital to the colonial powers.

Colonial era sovereign borrowing was mostly from private banks rather than other states, though during wars allies lent to each other. Britain utilised debt across the 18th century to build canals, towns, factories, and to fund industrial agriculture facilitated by the enclosure of the commons (Hobson 1914). The British made government loans to its ally Austria during the Napoleonic Wars and the French raised funds through borrowing and annuities to support the US in the American War of Independence (Kindleberger 1984), while both the British and US sought loans in Holland (Hobson 1914). The French state sold assets to fund Napoleon’s wars and such wartime borrowing often produced very complex transactions. Common causes of state-to-state debt were indemnities and war reparations (see Kindleberger 1984, ch 13) and the repayments frequently produced problems similar to those in the first era of bullion debt, namely, direct financial hardship leading to poverty and instability. The state system and emergent capitalism had granted autonomy to money and built up a political and military system to ensure repayment regardless of the cost to people (Graeber 2014).

By the 19th century, complex financialisation of loans was compounding problems created by bullion war debt. The century saw two large waves of sovereign defaults that influenced later thinking. Both hit Latin America and also several other states and were preceded by speculative waves and economic crises. Indeed, as Toussaint (2019) argued, before each of the debt crises from the 19th to the 21st centuries, there was a boom in central states resulting in surplus capital being recycled into peripheral states. And the subsequent crises in peripheral states have, for the most part, been caused by external factors like a financial crash or a recession in the core states. This contrasts to the mainstream narrative that blames over-indebtedness in the periphery for the crisis. In the case of the 1820s crisis starting in Latin America, Toussaint (2019) pointed to the London Stock Exchange crash as the precipitator but the terms of the speculative loans made to states as the underlying driver. Perhaps the most problematic case was a bond issue by Mexico in 1824. Bonds to the value of £3.2 million were issued by Mexico’s broker B.A. Goldschmidt & Co at 5% interest. But investors rarely pay the full or par price for bonds and, in this case, they paid just £58 for a £100 bond. This changes the effective interest rate from 5% to 8.6%. In addition, B.A. Goldschmidt & Co took a further £750,000 in commission and fees, so Mexico ended up with £1.1 million from £3.2 million in debt issued (Toussaint 2019, Wynne 1951). The resulting defaults in 1825 included all independent Latin American countries, four US states, Greece, and later Portugal. The loan mania leading to defaults in the early 1870s again in Latin America was even more extreme and its effects longer lasting. One of its more notorious impacts was the 1902–3 naval blockade of Venezuela by the UK, Germany, and Italy. This resulted in the Second Hague Conference of 1907 creating a convention to limit the use of force in debt recovery where debt is owed by one government to another (Hobson 1914).

Financialisation continued after the First World War, feeding into the Great Depression from 1929 and another debt crisis, discussed later. The idea for the IBRD came from concerns about the ugly loans made during this mania as well as the problem of war debts creating instability. Yet, by the late 2010s, MDBs were focussed on leveraging billions of dollars of lending into trillions, despite the evidence that such debts will become a weight around the neck of borrowing countries as soon as the next crisis hits. Writing in 2020, an economic crisis seems to have been triggered by a virus rather than a banking crisis, but the underlying causes are financial innovation and debt build-up and the consequences will almost certainly be long-lasting and severe. It will involve repayments to MDBs being made from recycled bilateral grant aid or from each other’s loans as has occurred in the past (Bracking 2009).

Banks started to develop various mechanisms for settling accounts between them and lending to each other during crises, which provided the logic for the creation of an international settlement bank that was one of the building blocks in the emergence of MDF. Similarly, states and national banks, after their creation, lent to each other during financial crises. This led governments to discuss creating a lender of last resort, like the IMF, for a couple of decades before its actual establishment, discussed below.

After this brief detour into the long-term growth of states, money, and debt, the chapter takes a more in-depth look at the factors that led up to the establishment of the first MDB. We pick up the story in the 1800s, when Britain was still at the centre of global finance, before the US took over this mantle between the two world wars. The picture of boom and bust financial markets was well established. By the 1880s, international capital flows were on a large scale and there were significant flows to foreign governments at the national, state, and municipal level mostly through securities. But, from this time until the eve of the First World War, the level of finance flowing to governments declined significantly, though flows to private ventures continued (Mikesell 1966, 4). Lending was tending to occur in bursts of about 20 years, followed by busts and defaults (Eichengreen 1991). Some of these loans, especially those to Latin and Central America, produced not just defaults but also concerns about exploitative lending practices and conditions. The forerunners of MDF were wider than just the boom and bust debt cycle though and include thinking about the possibilities for international cooperation.

2.2 Five key factors behind the emergence of MDBs

2.2.1 The growth of international cooperation

Nascent international cooperation was a key factor in the emergence of the MDBs. One of the first attempts at a mechanism for promoting international peace and stability was the Concert of Europe, established in 1815. It failed but set the precedent for cooperation and international organisations dedicated to pragmatic economic and technical cooperation did ultimately prove successful. Interestingly,

in earlier international organizations, voting power was determined purely by financial contributions, ensuring that the most economically powerful members would prevail. This was the case in the International Telegraphic Union established in 1865 and, subsequently, in the Universal Postal Union, the International Wine Office, and the International Institute of Agriculture, all of which were created by 1914.

(Woods 1999, 42)

The voting proposed for, and adopted by, the IMF and World Bank and most subsequent MDBs seems to derive from this precedent. The distribution of power in the IBRD initially reflected the economic hierarchy at the end of the Second World War and this legacy has been hard to overcome with the US determined to maintain its control. As Pieterse (2011, 26) said, ‘even if hegemonic capacity isn’t what it used to be, the habits of hegemony and of following hegemony linger.’

Still, the key point, as Mazower (2012) argued, is that between the late 1700s and the 1830s Europeans started to conceive not just of inter-state politics but also of an international political system acknowledging diverse peoples and forms of government. Systems of international organisation took a leap forward after the First World War, though most proposals and organisations were not able to overcome state rivalries and the forces of isolationism – especially in the US, the emerging hegemon.

2.2.2 The First World War, inter-war chaos, and changing international hegemony

The First World War was a nodal point in the decline of British hegemony and the rise of the US. War debts were one significant factor in this shift. The inter-war period (1918–39) saw a range of proposals for international cooperation, including in the financial terrain, though few successes. Still these provided the inspiration for later efforts. The ideas, and failures, of earlier cooperation attempts and the Great Depression were key motivators driving renewed cooperation efforts during and after the Second World War.

During the First World War, there were large government-to-government war and relief loans in particular from the US, Britain, and France to their allies and, subsequently, to support reconstruction (Mikesell 1966). However, there was no formal cooperation to assist countries recover from the war individually or collectively. Interestingly, Imperial China’s leader Sun Yat-sen unsuccessfully proposed ‘to the Paris Peace Conference of 1919 the creation of an “International Development Organization” that could mobilize international long-term lending to support China’s development’ (Helleiner 2017, 29). After the war, many countries faced political and economic chaos and for some this was exacerbated by the terms of the Treaty of Versailles, which concluded the war. The Great Powers established the League of Nations, though it was largely a failure. They attempted to organise financial cooperation through the League, starting with a conference in Brussels in 1920. Discussions on the monetary system and exchange rates at the conference were not successful but those for lending did continue. The proposals at these conferences provide a lineage for the Bretton Woods twins.

One proposal for the Brussels conference sent to delegates by Léon Delacroix, Prime Minister and Finance Minister of Belgium, was to set up an International Bank of Issue, which has a range of similarities to the IBRD (Oliver 1975). Its purpose was to issue interest-bearing gold bonds in exchange for securities like rights over customs duties, minerals, harvests, and so on. The bonds were to be issued to importers to pay for countries’ imports of productive goods. Shares in the Bank were to be purchased in gold and voting power determined by the number of shares held, as in the IBRD. But the proposal lacked a guarantee that the bonds would be redeemed and sufficient incentive for nations that would not borrow to join (Oliver 1975).

M.C.E ter Meulen, the Dutch delegate, working off Delacroix’s ideas, developed a plan for a Central Commission, which would allow individual states to issue interest-bearing bonds. It proposed using government revenues as securities and to give those securities to importers to use as collateral with exporters. The Central Commission was to be appointed by the League of Nations, which suggested that creditors’ interests would be protected, and the bonds were to be 5–10 years, longer than Delacroix’s, aiming to give borrowers more chance of recovering. The ter Meulen Plan was accepted and a Commission was established but, in 1922, the scheme was abandoned without making any loans. One of the reasons for this was the development of alternative sources of finance, in particular the 1919 US Edge Act provided long-term credits to support exports and, in the same year, the UK established an Exports-Credit Scheme (Oliver 1975). Export-import banks are, in fact, a key predecessor to the MDBs and they remain as siblings in the contemporary MDF system.

There were several other plans for economic cooperation in the 1920s and 1930s of lesser and greater ambition, the most important being John Maynard Keynes’ 1930 plan for a Supranational Bank. This was the predecessor to his International Clearing Union Plan that was the alternative to US Treasury official’s, Harry Dexter White’s, plan for the post-war economic and financial order. Keynes’ proposal was focussed on short-term adjustment finance, but other plans had long-term development aspects. What is notable is that there was significant debate on the topic in the inter-war years.

By the mid-1920s, the post-war chaos seemed to settle, and private international finance began to flow again. In contrast to the 19th century when flows to emerging regions mostly financed wars, these flows financed many productive investments (Mikesell 1966). Equally, however, many loans were reckless and excessive and there were mass defaults in the 1930s, resulting in private long-term lending slowing to almost a stand-still; it was even slower to recover after the Second World War. The defaults were caused, or aggravated, by the Great Depression, which started in 1929 with a financial crisis in the US. It spread internationally initially because Germany relied on US loans to pay its war reparations to Great Britain and France, and they, in turn, relied on these funds to pay their war debts to the US and other countries. Global lending collapsed and countries resorted to trade protectionism and currency devaluations which only exacerbated the crisis by contributing to a collapse in global trade. Mikesell (1966, 3–4) argued that the collapse of private lending in the inter-war years was in large part responsible for the establishment of the ‘complex of national and international public lending agencies’ that grew in the post-war era as there was clear evidence that free markets were not providing the necessary credit. The defaults of the 1930s produced the idea that loans for reconstruction and productive investments should be based on the recipients’ ability to repay. In other words, creditors should set conditions that were conducive to repayment and growth (Mikesell 1966, 19–20). Here is a key logic for MDF – coordination of creditors and debtors needs. The focus on fair terms between creditors and debtors is no longer as prominent in many MDBs but the broader idea of the need for economic cooperation between nations has remained.

In 1931, US President Herbert Hoover put in place a one-year moratorium on war debt repayments from all nations and this became permanent (Mikesell 1966, Rohrer 2006). The chaos of the inter-war years and unregulated debt informed the US approach in the Second World War – from March 1941, under the Lend-Lease programme, the US supplied whatever goods were declared by President Roosevelt as ‘in the interest of national defense’ to more than 38 nations and repayment was as ‘the President deems satisfactory’ (Kimball 2003). Between $42 and $50 billion of aid was given and repayment frequently came in the form of post-war agreements rather than cash or bullion. Before and during Lend-Lease, many nations had taken on debt, and Britain only paid back the last of this debt in 2006 (Rohrer 2006).

Despite the failure of the League of Nations’ attempts at economic cooperation, international monetary cooperation expanded during the inter-war period (Mikesell 1966). Cooperation between the emerging system of Federal Reserve Banks began in the 1920s (Ahamed 2009) and the Bank for International Settlements (BIS) was established in 1930 to manage the flow of German reparations and to formalise cooperation between central banks. German reparations were suspended shortly after the BIS was established but it continued to operate as a clearing house. It was set up as a corporation with shares owned by central banks, except for the US where private banks purchased the shares (Mikesell 1966, 14–15). This is like the IMF and IBRD, which are structured as state-owned shareholder-based institutions. The US Exchange Stabilization Fund was established in 1934 to promote exchange rate cooperation, which means it is a direct predecessor of the IMF. However, before the Second World War, the US was not willing to underpin an international system and the UK no longer had the capacity to do so (Arrighi 1994, 271, Ikenberry 1992, 306), thus cooperation was still largely piecemeal.

2.2.3 Keynesianism and the New Deal

Along with the shift in hegemonic power from the UK to the US, a vital part of the emergence of MDF was the arrival of a new theoretical and ideological framework, a new ‘common sense’ around economics (Engel 2010). The Great Depression, the rise of communism, and the increasing organisation of labour saw academics and politicians alike agreeing that high rates of unemployment were not just sub-optimal, but also dangerous in that they could lead to chaos or revolution. The Great Depression was tangible evidence that free markets do not always produce ideal economic and social outcomes. The new faith in human capacity to organise and the practical example of socialist states, which had grown industrially during the Great Depression, opened the door to the idea of state planning, which became a buzz-word in politics (Hobsbawm 1999).

These experiences and ideas were given a theoretical baptism by Keynes who homed in on the importance of the demand-side of the economic equation and the negative impact of deflationary policies. He started this focus in A Tract on Monetary Reform (1923) and bought together his ideas in his magnum opus, The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money (1936). He argued that there was not necessarily a direct relationship between savings and investment and that confidence affects investment. The level of both aggregate demand and investment might not be enough to create full employment and that investors were too interested in short-term profits not long-term societal gains. This provided a case for government investment to increase demand and direct investment to its most productive uses. The ‘Keynesian revolution’ was in fact a two-headed animal – ‘first, the theoretical revolution in economic analysis; and, second, the practical revolution in governmental policies’ (Meade 1975, 82). The revolution in government policies did not always strictly follow Keynes’ ideas, for example, in the growth of the welfare state, but the governmental revolution was more important than the economic one (Meade 1975), and it greatly improved the life experience of most people in Western countries. Overall, ‘there was a profound change in the approach of liberal capitalist states to the role of government intervention in the economy – there was a new openness to the idea of economic planning and of state participation in the economy’ (Engel 2010, 19). These changes further opened the door to expanded economic cooperation at the international level too.

The Second World War deepened US economic dominance as its economic productivity expanded and control over the financial system shifted to New York (Arrighi 1994, Kennedy 1989). US political isolationism was put to rest for many decades and the US became the global hegemon able to lead international organisation building. Indeed, the US government began planning for the post-war economic and political order from the autumn of 1939 (Gardner 1980), prior to becoming directly involved in the war! Its first focus was the post-war monetary and economic system, not the organisation of peace and security (Ikenberry 1992). US economic planning is discussed a little more below but first we turn to its economic cooperation with Latin America.

2.2.4 US economic cooperation with Latin America: from export-import banks to development banks

Discussion of regional economic and financial cooperation started in earnest with the First Pan-American Conference of 1889–90, in other words prior to the European discussions of the inter-war years. This conference proposed the idea of a private International American Bank to facilitate trade and investment in the region (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010). The then US President supported the idea, but it did not pass the Congress. Still it was reaffirmed at the Second Pan-American Conference in 1898, before disappearing. The 1913 Federal Reserve Act, in addition to setting up a decentralised reserve system, dealt with many of the issues that had concerned the first conference by allowing US banks to finance overseas trade, to operate accounts in other countries, and to establish agencies and branches abroad (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010). The issue of improving trade and investment relations, specifically exchange rates and adequate credit flows to Latin America, was again discussed during the First World War but little came of it. In the 1920s another credit binge took hold.

By the 1930s, the US was concerned about countering the appeal of Nazism and statist and nationalist economic policies in Latin America, which had grown during the Great Depression. The Depression had hit Latin America hard with the prices of its main primary commodities exports dropping from 1928. In fact, the ‘Pan-American Agricultural Conference of 1930 contemplated the creation of an Inter-American Agricultural Bank’ extending rural credits and finance for trade, but dropped the idea fearing subjugation to Wall Street (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010, 26).

Franklin D. Roosevelt’s election in 1932 changed relations with Latin America with the ‘Good Neighbor’ policy renouncing US military intervention in the region. The policy was expanded over time to include a financial partnership promoting development (Helleiner 2014). The Seventh Inter-American Conference in 1933 proposed greater economic and financial cooperation through an agency comprising a Board, Consultative Committee, and an Inter-American Bank, which was to be like a central bank for the continent. Yet again, the US did not pursue implementation due to Congressional opposition. The US did though formally established an Export-Import (Exim) Bank in 1934 and, towards the end of the 1930s, it started providing the equivalent of development loans to some Latin American countries (Mikesell 1966, 13).

The language in Executive Order 6581 that established the Exim Bank has clear parallels to the IBRD’s Articles of Agreement (AoA). It states that, in creating the Exim Bank, Congress aimed:

to remove obstacles to the free flow of interstate and foreign commerce which tend to diminish the amount thereof, to provide for the general welfare, by promoting the fullest possible utilization of the present productive capacities of industries, to reduce and relieve unemployment, to improve standards of labor, and otherwise to rehabilitate industry…

(Roosevelt 1934)

The IBRD’s AoA (World Bank 2012) promote ‘private foreign investment,’ the ‘development of productive facilities,’ and the ‘development of the productive resources of members, thereby assisting in raising productivity, the standard of living and conditions of labor in their territories.’ New Deal, Keynesian principles permeate both documents. Like the IBRD, the Exim Bank was set up with capital stock divided into shares, though all were held by the Secretary of State and Commerce. Further, the IBRD followed the US Exim Bank’s procedure of providing funds on receipt of invoices rather than establishing a deposit in the name of the borrower and of investigating the usefulness of projects, although as an MDB it abandoned the Exim’s tied aid (Oliver 1975, 90).

A memorandum to the President in October 1938 by White under guidance from Treasury Secretary Henry Morgenthau urged large-scale economic aid to Latin America and China to secure peace and make the Good Neighbor policy effective (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010). White was the US Treasury Department official who drafted the first plans for what became the IMF and World Bank, and he had New Deal views and supported statist development models in line with US Treasury views.

A 1939 consultation meeting with Latin America’s foreign ministers ‘asked again for the creation of a new financial institution’ with a multilateral focus and not a bilateral one like the US Exim Bank (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010, 32). The Mexican delegation presented a draft for the institution which included a range of clearing house and exchange stabilisation functions, many of which had been discussed earlier. However, ‘on this occasion the Mexican Delegation expressly added the following: (f) To act as a channel for the investment of capital which will promote sound economic development in the American Republics’ (Villaseñor 1941, 166). Indeed Kirsty Thornton (2017) attributed this addition to Eduardo Villaseñor, then Mexico’s Undersecretary of the Ministry of Finance and Public Credit, and noted that Mexican officials had been discussing long-term development finance for at least 15 years prior to Bretton Woods. The US tried to deflect this request through expansion of the Exim Bank in 1940 and an agreement that it could lend to governments not just the private sector. Still, US views about a regional state-backed investment mechanism started to change; they became more open to the idea. In this context, the Inter-American Financial and Economic Advisory Committee began work on a draft charter for an Inter-American Bank (IAB), which is the chief direct progenitor of the MDBs.

The plan combined a clearing house, a stabilisation fund (like the IMF), and a development bank promoting the growth of industry and infrastructure. It was also to promote research, provide technical advice, and promote and publish data (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010). Like the IBRD, its first purpose was promoting the productive use of capital (Federal Reserve Bulletin 1940). Its structure was a bank with a capital base of $100 million, made up of 1,000 shares of $100,000. This follows the inter-war plans for an institution by Delacroix and became the model for the Bretton Woods twins. Voting was linked to shareholding and important decisions required a four-fifths majority, though the US was not going to have veto power as it did with the IMF and IBRD. Administration was to be vested in a Board of Directors meeting at least four times a year, rather than a permanent presence as the IMF and IBRD have. The proposal flagged the idea of an executive committee to make decisions between Board meetings, like the IBRD’s Executive Directors who are responsible for day-to-day decision-making. The draft charter also outlined that any medium- or long-term loans needed a report from experts before approval.

From the US side, drafting was led by the State Department and White worked on it along with Emilio G. Collado who also worked on the IBRD. Oliver (1971, 4) argued the White’s stabilisation fund and bank plan were ‘an outgrowth of the Inter-American Bank proposal, though it embodied his own thoughts and the thoughts which had been expressed during earlier discussions within the Treasury Department.’ Reading the proposed charter for the IAB that seems clear, although, in terms of the IMF, the US Exchange Stabilization Fund and other developments influenced White’s thinking too (see Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010, Helleiner 2017). In a footnote, Oliver (1971, 24) argues that Collado, Assistant State Department Chief, Division of American Republics was a major author of the Convention for the Establishment of an Inter-American Bank and ‘may really have been the individual most responsible for the conception’ of the IBRD. He was later the IBRD’s first US Executive Director. In an oral history, Collado (1974) stated:

In that committee we had a proposal for an inter-American bank. We actually wrote a treaty for an inter-American bank which was signed by half the American Republics, including the United States, but it was never ratified. It’s a long story as to why it was never ratified. Harry White was one of the principal authors of this with Adolf Berle, who was the Assistant Secretary of State at the time. I got to do a great deal of the work and this was usually the rule. Actually a great deal of thought was put into an inter-American bank proposal at that time and it had some rather innovative aspects which never survived into the World Bank. It had access to the credit of the Federal Reserve System in a way that was never further put into some of the later proposals and maybe that’s why it never got adopted.

The focus on White, Collado, and Berle, it seems to us, obscures the leading role of the Latin American delegations, in particular Mexico; indeed, The Washington Times critically labelled the IAB ‘a Mexican-inspired institution’ (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010, 39). The proposed operational powers of the IAB exceeded those of the IMF and World Bank and the ‘sheer ambition of the bank project proved intimidating’ (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010, 39). The US never ratified the charter after stiff opposition from sections of Congress and private banks. The latter is not surprising given the IAB had a broad mandate including making loans to private individuals and business. Indeed, Villaseñor (1941) argued that this should be its primary function.

2.2.5 US economic planning and the Bretton Woods Conference

Economic planning by the US and its allies has been outlined and debated in depth (see inter alia Block 1977, Gardner 1980, Helleiner 2014, Van Dormael 1978) and Chapter 3 explores the outcomes of that planning. This section simply outlines some of the key topics of debate and what was not agreed upon and not debated. The US State Department began economic and political planning in 1939, prior to becoming directly involved in the Second World War (Gardner 1980). The State Department had a laissez-faire approach and adopted, at times, aggressive tactics to push its trade agenda. The Treasury had been more influenced by the chaos of the inter-war years and was committed to planning. They became the key US negotiators and found common ground with the British and others on the need for a post-war monetary system (Ikenberry 1992). Still, the Bretton Woods institutions were shaped by the trade-offs needed to get approval from Congress, which was dominated by laissez-faire views (Gardner 1980, Scammell 1983). The planning negotiations aimed to create a stable trading order with reduced tariffs and limited non-tariff barriers to trade, cooperation in exchange rates and settlements to avoid the competitive devaluations of the inter-war years, building on the nascent central bank cooperation of that period, and to promote economic expansion after the war.

Negotiations between the US and its allies were based on the Suggested Plan for a United and Associated National Stabilization Fund and a Bank for Reconstruction and Development of the United and Associated Nations, drafted by White first in 1941. The plan was circulated for comment in mid-1943 and did not include a plan for the Bank. When the Bank plan was published it was no longer a central international bank as the IAB proposal was for the Americas, it had become an international lending agency (Block 1977). The British, led by Keynes, produced their own proposal for the Stabilization Fund – the International Clearing Union. Negotiations before and at Bretton Woods, though, were based on the White plan. There were 44 nations present, including strong representation from Latin America and the USSR. Still, it is often presented as an Anglo-American affair. There is some truth in this, but recent historical research has reclaimed the role played by other states, in particular in the developmental focus of the World Bank (Scott-Smith and Rofe 2017).

The IMF that emerged out of Bretton Woods was designed to manage a fixed exchange rate system with gold and US dollars the core units of account, act as a multilateral clearing house of funds between nations, supplement international liquidity for states, and impose conditions on states in regular deficit if they wished to access further liquidity from the Fund. Keynes had wanted both countries in surplus and deficit to be pressured to adjust but this did not suit US interests at the time; US interests did not consider that they would ever face regular deficit, as is the case now. Conditionality was also built into the IBRD’s AoA, and, as sibling organisations, the World Bank has often acted as an enforcer of IMF conditionality, especially from the 1980s with the emergence of the Washington Consensus (more on this in Chapters 4 and 5).

Trade negotiations did not get far at Bretton Woods, dominated as it was by representatives from ministries of finance, though for the US orderly exchange mechanisms and convertibility were core to trade. The IMF dealt with short-term balance of payments deficits, while the World Bank was to provide long-term loans for reconstruction and development. This sounds comprehensive but there were key topics for the financial order not addressed. First, the movement of private capital – the system encouraged immediate liberalisation of countries’ capital account. In fact, most of the world did not achieve this for some decades and attempts at premature liberalisation were the cause of a number of crises for developed countries (Scammell 1983). Capital movement’s capacity to cause instability for developing and emerging economies dramatically expanded after the liberalisation of finance markets from 1973 with the end of fixed exchange rates. In the 1980s, many developing countries were pushed to open their capital accounts through IMF and World Bank conditionality often resulting in financial crises. The scale of international financial movements and lending is a significant cause of instability for developing countries and something that MDBs promote (Bracking 2009). Second, there are many weaknesses in the regime for supervising and regulating banking and finance, domestically and internationally, as was all too clear in the 2007–8 GFC. These weaknesses are a problem for the Global South, where debt can easily build up for a host of reasons. Virtually no matter how a state came to power, they can put a country into debt and this debt must be repaid by citizens. Third, there was no mechanism to deal with long-term default by states established at Bretton Woods. White’s first draft of the IMF and IBRD did include a role in debt restructuring but this disappeared in later drafts (Helleiner 2017), presumably because it was too politically contentious for the world’s largest creditor, the US, where powerful Wall Street interests wanted to ensure debtor paid up. The IMF and World Bank have taken up some of this role, though they have no legal power in managing relations with private creditors. Further, because of the tendency to bail-out failed governments and banks, the finance system has created an enormous moral hazard that favours the interests of elites (Bracking 2009). The MDBs face virtually no risk of non-repayment.

2.3 Conclusion

This chapter demonstrated that MDF was a logical step in the evolution of state borrowing initially for war and later for development. Debt from complex but largely unregulated private finance produced instability that Western democratic states could not tolerate and, at the same time, an overall dearth of financial flows to newly independent states. The dire impacts of the boom and bust cycles of international finance produced domestic and international forces promoting control and regulation but it was incomplete. Indeed, the very mechanisms created to facilitate flows to developing countries have created instabilities as there are few or no mechanisms to ensure public and particularly private debt is created for useful purposes by representative, effective regimes.

Some of the tensions embodied in MDF derive from its origins. State lending to other states has always been fraught and war credits often fed into post-war instability. The debates about economic cooperation by the League of Nations after the First World War led to the first proposals for institution building in this area and the creation of the BIS. However, the first formal development finance institutions were export-import banks, dating back to 1919 and they were designed with the developmental interests of the already industrialised world in play. The US Treasury was aware in the 1930s that Exim banks created political tensions (Oliver 1971). Nevertheless, the US Exim Bank came to provide something like concessional development finance to Latin America during the 1930s, assisted by concerns in the US Congress about the rising popularity and influence of Nazi Germany in the region. The US Treasury was also acutely aware of the failures of private institutions to provide adequate credit to developing regions, let alone ones at reasonable interest rates and for well-researched projects, which were likely to promote development and progress.

It seems clear that the first proposal for a regional body to provide MDF came from Mexico and not the US. Mexico, at the time, was pursuing a fairly radical economic nationalist developmental policy and actively sought to represent and promote the interest of poorer states (Thornton 2017). Given the relative progressiveness of the Roosevelt Administration and the concerns about the rise of Nazism, they supported the idea and helped develop a proposal for the IAB. The IAB ‘combined the functions of (a) an investment bank; (b) an international stabilization fund with some Central Bank powers; (c) an ordinary commercial bank, and (d) a centre of technical and economic research to promote economic development’ (Diaz-Bonilla and del Campo 2010, 39). In other words, it had broader functions than the subsequent proposals for the IMF and IBRD at Bretton Woods. These origins support Helleiner’s (2014, 2017) recent accounts of Bretton Woods as having a greater developmental focus than has been presented in the histories of the World Bank to date. What Helleiner perhaps misses are that in structuring these organisations as banks – bound up with, and indeed reliant on, the international banking sector and money markets – the institutional structures created would prioritise banking needs not developmental ones. White thought that the institution’s disinterested analysis of projects would be enough to differentiate it from older forms of finance capital. He said:

In the past movement of capital have been regarded as, frankly, imperialist. They usually led later to difficulties of one sort or another. The other country did not like to pay; the interests built up were frequently supposed to be tyrannous. We are still liquidating many of the nineteenth-century messes which were occasioned by the somewhat violent and not too enlightened motives of capital.

(White cited in Oliver 1975, 97, emphasis added)

Yet MDBs have not overcome the violence of capital, rather, as Graeber (2014) argued, debt as violence continued and has only been partially hidden by the impersonal structures of the modern state system and capitalism. Structural features were more influential in shaping the IBRD and MDF than the, at times, progressive aspirations of its founders to a ‘New Deal in international economics’ whose goals included supplying ‘the huge volume of capital that will be needed abroad for… the attainment of world prosperity and higher standards of living’ (Memo to Roosevelt quoted in Helleiner 2017, 28). State-backed MDF still remains subject to cycles of credit expansion followed by crisis. The repayment imperative sees basic services cut to the poor to pay back debt. Across the world, austerity policies result in increased disease and death, but such cuts disproportionately impact the poor in the Global South.

The MDF system was designed to ensure that debts were used productively but it did not include any mechanism for dealing ‘expediently and humanely with a bankrupt government’ (Soederberg 2006, 96–7). The IMF was focussed on currency stability and convertibility and short-term loans to countries facing balance of payments crises. This latter topic, along with increased surveillance of states, became its main focus after the end of the Bretton Wood mark I system, as the period from their establishment to the demise of the gold standard in 1971 and fixed exchange rates in 1973 is sometimes called. Neoliberal conditionality grew too with lending. The Bretton Woods twins have guaranteed repayment and both organisations are arbiters of country creditworthiness. Both also act as de facto global debt collectors and not always, or indeed often, in humane ways (Soederberg 2006). For example, in the case of the Argentine default in 2001, even after the country reached a deal with its creditors, a small number of private investors defied the agreement buying up defaulted debt at cheap prices and suing the Argentine government through US courts to get a better deal on the debt. An agreement was only reached in late 2016 and the precedent set by the holdouts was a major setback for effective restructurings (Stiglitz 2013).

It is fascinating that today’s emerging powers, in particular China, are largely following the patterns of credit creation established from the 1930s. China’s development finance started through its export-import bank and national policy banks and, as the political costs of this system of tied aid started to become too high, they established their own MDB, the AIIB. It is not entirely surprising that a state-led economy like China would find comfort in the Keynesian ideas that dominated when the first MDBs were proposed and created, namely, that ‘[p]rivate investors cannot be counted on to finance world-wide economic development in the absence of government guarantees to reduce the risk of overseas lending’ (Oliver 1975, 62). But the fact is that the record of MDBs in creating economic development has not been overwhelming yet the system of MDBs continues to expand.

Note

1 This analysis draws quite a bit on Mikesell (1966). He outlined four direct precedents for the emergence of the IBRD: first, the growth of private finance and lending; second, war loans, third, international monetary cooperation; and, finally, the establishment of export-import banks. However, he does not discuss the proposal for an Inter-American Bank, which is the key precedent for the IBRD.

Bibliography

Ahamed, Liaquat. 2009. Lords of Finance: The Bankers Who Broke the World. New York: Penguin Press.

Arrighi, Giovanni. 1994. The Long Twentieth Century: Money, Power, and the Origins of Our Times. London: Verso.

Bieler, Andreas, and Adam David Morton. 2018. Global Capitalism, Global War, Global Crisis. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Block, Fred L. 1977. The Origins of International Economic Disorder: A Study of United States International Monetary Policy from World War II to the Present. Berkeley: University of California Press.

Bracking, Sarah. 2009. Money and Power: Great Predators in the Political Economy of Development. London: Pluto Press.

Cammack, Paul. 2004. “What the World Bank Means by Poverty Reduction and Why it Matters.” New Political Economy 9 (2):189–211.

Collado, Emilio. 1974. Oral History Interview with Emilio Collado, edited by Richard D. McKinzie. Truman Library. Accessed 8 November 2018. https://trumanlibrary.org/oralhist/collado2.htm

Kimball, Warren. 2003. “Lend-Lease.” In The Oxford Companion to World War II, edited by I.C.B. Dear and M.R.D. Foot. Oxford: Oxford University Press, online.

Diaz-Bonilla, Eugenio, and Maria Victoria del Campo. 2010. A Long and Winding Road: The Creation of the Inter American Development Bank. Australia: Lulu.

Eichengreen, Barry. 1991. “Historical Research on International Lending and Debt.” Journal of Economic Perspectives 5 (2):149–69.

Engel, Susan. 2010. The World Bank and the Post-Washington Consensus in Vietnam and Indonesia: Inheritance of Loss. London: Routledge.

Federal Reserve Bulletin. 1940. Inter-American Bank, edited by Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve. Washington, DC.

Gardner, Richard N. 1980. Sterling-dollar Diplomacy in Current Perspective: The Origins and the Prospects of our International Economic Order, 3rd ed. New York: Columbia University Press.

Geisst, Charles R. 2013. Beggar Thy Neighbor: A History of Usury and Debt. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press.

Graeber, David. 2014. Debt: The First 5,000 Years. Brooklyn, NY: Melville House.

Helleiner, Eric. 2014. Forgotten Foundations of Bretton Woods: International Development and the Making of the Postwar Order. Ithaca, NY and London: Cornell University Press.

Helleiner, Eric. 2017. “What’s Been Missing from Conventional Histories of Bretton Woods?” In Global Perspectives on the Bretton Woods Conference and the Post-War World Order, edited by Giles Scott-Smith and J. Simon Rofe, 17–34. Cham: Palgrave Macmillan.

Hobsbawm, Eric. 1999. Age of Extremes: The Short Twentieth Century 1914–1991. London: Abacus. Original edition, 1994.

Hobson, C. K. 1914. The Export of Capital. London: Constable and Company Ltd.

Ikenberry, G. John. 1992. “A World Economy Restored: Expert Consensus and the Anglo-American Postwar Settlement.” International Organization 46 (1):289–321.

Kennedy, Paul. 1989. The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers: Economic Change and Military Conflict from 1500 to 2000. New York: Vintage Books.

Kindleberger, Charles P. 1984. A Financial History of Western Europe. London: George Allen & Unwin.

Mazower, Mark. 2012. Governing the World: The History of an Idea, 1815 to the Present. New York: Penguin Books.

Meade, James. 1975. “The Keynesian Revolution.” In Essays on John Maynard Keynes, edited by Milo Keynes, 82–88. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Mikesell, Raymond F. 1966. Public International Lending for Development. New York: Random House.

Oliver, Robert W. 1971. Early Plans for a World Bank, Princeton Studies in International Finance No. 29. Princeton, NJ: Department of Economics, Princeton University.

Oliver, Robert W. 1975. International Economic Co-operation and the World Bank. London and Basingstoke: Macmillan Press.

Pieterse, Jan Nederveen. 2011. “Global Rebalancing: Crisis and the East-South Turn.” Development and Change 42 (1):61–79.

Rohrer, Finlo. 2006. “What’s a Little Debt between Friends?” BBC News Magazine. Accessed 28 February 2018. http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/4757181.stm.

Roosevelt, Franklin D. 1934. Executive Order 6581 Creating the Export-Import Bank of Washington. The American Presidency Project.

Scammell, W. M. 1983. The International Economy Since 1945, 2nd ed. London: Macmillan Education Ltd.

Scott-Smith, Giles, and J. Simon Rofe, eds. 2017. Global Perspectives on the Bretton Woods Conference and the Post-War World Order. Cham: Palgrave Macmillan.

Soederberg, Susan. 2006. Global Governance in Question: Empire, Class and the New Common Sense in Managing North-South Relations. London: Pluto Press.

Stasavage, David. 2016. “What We Can Learn from the Early History of Sovereign Debt.” Explorations in Economic History 59:1–16. doi: 10.1016/j.eeh.2015.09.005.

Stiglitz, Joesph. 2013. “The Vultures’ Victory.” Project Syndicate, September 4.

Thornton, Christy. 2017. “Voice and Vote for the Weaker Nations: Mexico’s Bretton Woods.” In Global Perspectives on the Bretton Woods Conference and the Post-War World Order, edited by Giles Scott-Smith and J. Simon Rofe, 149–65. Cham: Palgrave Macmillan.

Toussaint, Eric. 2019. The Debt System: A History of Sovereign Debts and Their Repudiation. Chicago, IL: Haymarket Books.

Van Dormael, Armand. 1978. Bretton Woods: Birth of a Monetary System. London: Macmillan Press Ltd.

Villaseñor, Eduardo. 1941. “The Inter-American Bank: Prospects and Dangers.” Foreign Affairs 20 (1):165–74.

Woods, Ngaire. 1999. “Good Governance in International Organizations.” Global Governance 5 (1):39–61.

World Bank. 2012. International Bank of Reconstruction and Development Articles of Agreement. Washington, DC: World Bank. Accessed 24 November 2020. https://www.worldbank.org/en/about/articles-of-agreement/ibrd-articles-of-agreement

Wynne, William Harris. 1951. State Insolvency and Foreign Bondholders Vol II: Selected Case Histories of Governmental Foreign Bond Defaults and Debt Readjustments. Washington, DC: Beard Books.

3 Development thinking, debt, and the multilateral development bank system: 1946–79

This chapter is the first of two chapters exploring the emergence of development ideas and how they link to (i) the advent of the MDB system and (ii) development in practice. Chapter 3 explores the period from the start of the Bretton Woods system at the end of the Second World War until the late 1970s, three decades through which the post-war Keynesian consensus melded with welfare state and modernisation model to dominate economic thinking (Fine 2001). It was also the largest period of MDB creation with 22 organisations established. The chapter pays special attention to the founding of the first MDB – the World Bank – as it provided the model for future development banks. Thus, this chapter begins with a brief outline of the Bank set within the context of the emergence of development thought. The second section of the chapter explores the impact of regionalism and the United Nations (UN) on the expansion of the MDB system, outlining how the marginalisation of the UN in favour of the MDBs profoundly shaped development practice and more. The third section explores the sub-regional expansion of the MDB system, while the final section returns to the issue of debt, which rapidly expanded in the 1970s laying the foundations for the so-called 1982 Third World Debt Crisis.

As Chapter 2 outlined, the theoretical tradition that most influenced the Bretton Woods institutions was Keynesianism. Keynes’ (1973) work was aimed at saving capitalism from its tendency to crisis as well as ensuring high levels of employment and reasonable standards of living for all; he aimed to make capitalism work more effectively. Keynes argued that capitalism tended to boom and bust cycles and that contra neoclassical economics, there was no automatic system for adjustment rather government intervention was needed (Galbraith 1975, Roll 1973). Keynes also saw the need for international economic cooperation as these same forces were at work globally and coordination was vital, especially during crises. Indeed, he was a key participant at the July 1944 Bretton Woods Conference that created the World Bank. Keynesianism fed into the establishment of development economics in the 1940s and 1950s and helped consolidate the idea that the state was a key means to organise society and promote development (Berger 2004). Keynes’ work also reflected changes that had already been taking place in many industrialised states, where the role and reach of the state was expanding. This has been called a revolution in practical governmental policy, and Meade (1975, 87) argues this was ‘of much greater importance and significance for the welfare of mankind’ than the revolution in macroeconomics produced by Keynesianism.

After the Second World War, influenced by Keynesianism, development thought was not particularly ideological, it was not ‘left’ or ‘right,’ rather there was general consensus that more government intervention was needed than previously (Rapley 2002). Other key influences on development thinking were Modernisation Theory, with its focus on emulating the political and social systems of the West, and Growth Theory, which focussed on expanding capital formation from savings and investments as crucial to accelerating economic growth. Fine (2001) usefully labelled the post-war consensus as the Keynesian, welfare, modernisation model. This was the general milieu as the World Bank was established – development studies and development economics were in their infancy and thinking focussed on a greater role for the state through planning. Statism, Modernisation Theory, and Growth Theory all saw debt as a useful way the state could obtain the capital necessary for investment and ‘take-off,’ though Structuralism and Dependency Theory would challenge many of these ideas.

3.1 The World Bank: a brief introduction

The World Bank commenced operations in 1946 as the IBRD but later grew into the World Bank Group, which today has five institutions: IBRD, International Finance Corporation (IFC) added in 1956, IDA in 1960, International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID) in 1966, and Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency (MIGA) in 1988. Given that this book studies MDF, we focus on the Bank’s MDF arms: the IBRD, IDA, and IFC. As per World Bank Group usage, the term ‘World Bank’ refers to the IBRD and the concessional lending arm, the IDA, which have different Articles of Agreement but share the same staff and headquarters. In contrast, the IFC invests purely in private enterprises via loans and guarantees and provides risk management and advisory services. The Bank is the largest development agency in the world with over 12,000 staff and 5,000 contractors in 2019. After a large capital increase agreed to in 2018, its total capital base is $312.9 billion, meaning that surpassed even the European Investment Bank (EIB) which has $275 billion in capital.

Most historical accounts of the World Bank largely present it as the product of Anglo-American negotiations. As outlined in Chapter 2, however, its origins are more complex than that, with proposals for international economic cooperation dating to the 1800s. The story of the Bretton Woods Conference, where the final details of the IMF and Bank were negotiated, has been told often and very well (see inter alia Block 1977, Gardner 1980, Oliver 1971) and hence is not retold here. Overall, Bretton Woods gave the IMF responsibility for promoting an orderly exchange rates system, providing short-term assistance to nations facing balance of payment crises and undertaking surveillance of global economic conditions. Of course, its role in the exchange rate system changed dramatically in the early 1970s with the end of the gold standard and the shift to floating exchange rates. The Bank was to provide long-term loans to promote reconstruction and development. As Chapter 2 outlines, both institutions reflected the growing belief in the importance of international organisation, and they had Keynesian social democratic aims. The Bank’s primary architect, Harry Dexter White, intended the IBRD as an alternative to private banks, which had been too exploitative and crisis prone (Oliver 1975). But, like most things, the devil is in the detail and in setting up the IBRD as a bank, White created an institution that would institutionalise banking norms more than human development goals. Other MDBs largely followed the model framed by the Bank, with their structures outlined in Chapter 5. Still, the Keynesian ideals that imbued the Bank’s creation remain an important influence on the institution and subsequent MDBs, often most visible in their purposes, one focus of this chapter.

Analyses of Bretton Woods have tended to argue that reconstruction was at the forefront of White’s mind in establishing the IBRD (e.g., Oliver 1971). In fact, White also had a strong focus on development and the Latin American delegations – and Mexico’s representatives in particular – ensured that development was higher on the Bank’s agenda than would have otherwise been the case (Helleiner 2017, 2014, Urquidi 1996). US bureaucrats did use the funding of reconstruction as a way of selling the Bank to Congress (Gardner 1980) and most of the other large shareholders were engrossed by concerns with reconstruction and the Bank’s early loans reflected this (Mason and Asher 1973).

The IBRD’s main aim is facilitating investment ‘for productive purposes,’ promoting private foreign investment, and promoting ‘long-range balanced growth,’ productivity, and standards of living (World Bank 2012, 3). The MDB was designed to help capitalism function more effectively and in a socially acceptable manner. In line with the Keynesian project, growth was important not just for its own sake but for its impact on employment (Engel 2010). The Great Depression had demonstrated that the international economy would not, under its own momentum, provide investment at a level that would achieve near full employment. Once operational though, the Bank understood development as the expansion of capitalism. But as Amin (2014, 14) has argued, ‘[c]apitalism is not “a system of development”,’ rather it is about the expansion of capital and private property. The Bank demonstrates this point in the way that it has sidelined some of its purposes, including balanced trade and national accounts, standards of living, and employment. To illustrate, the Bank for years claimed that its prohibition on political activity prevented it from promoting the International Labour Organisation’s Core Labour Standards (Murphy 2014) despite the fact that among its purposes is the promote of the ‘conditions of labour’.

The focus on private investment, private markets for capital, and guaranteeing private loans was a key contribution of the European delegations at Bretton Woods. As the Bank’s first official history noted, it ‘was all but the universal expectation of the founders of the Bank that its primary function would be to guarantee private investments’ (Mason and Asher 1973, 26). In practice, it focussed on direct lending to states. The clause on private investment also highlights how economic logic dominated Bretton Woods thinking which has ‘colored the Bank’s development efforts’ ever since, as the Bank’s second official history pointed out (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997, 70). The purposes demonstrate belief in planning and management by experts, noting the need for prioritising ‘useful and urgent projects’ (World Bank 2012, 3). Finally, the clause highlighting ‘the effect of international investment on business conditions’ (World Bank 2012, 3) offered a limited promise of counter-cyclical investment on both a country and a world scale, a Keynesian view. This is an area where it rarely engaged up until the 2007–8 GFC.

In terms of what investments should be prioritised, the World Bank sets the agenda and continues to play a leading, indeed often hegemonic, role in shaping the development practices of other MDBs. Founding senior IBRD staff held that manufacturing and export industries should be funded by private investors, so they were excluded as was investment in state-run enterprises, other than utilities. The consensus that dominated IBRD lending for more than a decade was that public utilities – in particular electricity, dams, transport, and communications – provided the preconditions to economic growth and the expansion of private investment (Mason and Asher 1973). As Toussaint (2008) points out, in its first 17 years the Bank did not lend at all for education, health, drinking water, or wastewater treatment and certainly not for welfare. Bank staffers felt their contribution to economic growth was ‘less measurable and direct than that of power plants’ (Mason and Asher 1973, 151) though it is now clear that this is the most direct way to improve human well-being.

In its early years, the Bank made several loans to colonial powers to finance projects in colonies in direct contravention of the UN’s commitment to self-determination (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). Once independent, former colonies were required to take over Bank debts contracted by former colonial entities regardless of how odious they were (Toussaint 2008). Further, a key loan condition from its earliest operations has been settlement of outstanding debts, making the Bank a debt collector enforcing a capitalist hegemonic principle. Table 3.1 outlines the main contributions of Bank Presidents until 1981.

Table 3.1 World Bank Presidents 1946–81

Name and Term | Background | Legacy
Eugene Meyer June–Dec 1946 | Born in US, attended Yale University, wealthy banker, served in several government offices, owned Washington Post. | Recruited senior staff, mostly bankers. Laid some of the groundwork for the Bank, especially loan analysis backed by a research department. Adopted a conservative approach to gain Wall Street’s confidence. Clashed with Executive Directors over authority.
John McCloy 1947–9 | Born in US, attended Harvard University, trained as lawyer, served Assistant Secretary of War during World War II. | Accepted presidency on the basis that he would have strong executive authority relative to the Board of Executive Directors. Obtained funds from capital markets and to do so demonstrated ‘sound’ (read conservative) lending and staffing policies. Established the interest rate policy and negative pledge – that no other creditor would take precedence over the IBRD – and policy of not lending to countries that had not tried hard to settle on any defaults to other creditors. Started the shift from reconstruction to development financing.
Name and Term | Background | Legacy
Eugene Robert Black 1949–62 | Born in US, attended University of Georgia, served in US Navy, worked as investment firm banker, saw himself as a development diplomat. | Built up the foundations of the Bank started by McCloy in terms of loan development, staffing, management, and access to US credit markets to raise capital. Emphasised conservative banking principles. Focused on projects that align with strong national development plans and launched the Bank’s technical assistance program. Promoted a vision of development as modernisation and advocated the role of private sector finance, leading to the creation of the IFC in 1956. The concessional loan affiliate, the IDA, was established in the Bank in 1961, although he originally rejected the idea. Popular with Bank staff.
George David Woods 1963–8 | Born in US, office worker at bond firm, investment banker. | Viewed the Bank as a development institution rather than just a bank. He expanded lending and introduced program loans and established the Bank’s role in aid coordination and strengthened the IFC. Woods expanded research from country creditworthiness to a more comprehensive assessment and expanded economic staff. He shifted focus from large-scale investment to agriculture productivity, education, and population growth. To allay investor fears about private investments, he established ICSID in 1966. Decolonisation saw membership increase by one third.
Robert Strange McNamara 1968–81 | Born in US, attended University of California and Harvard Business School, introduced quantitative management to US car industry, served as US Secretary of Defence, responsible for the Vietnam War strategy that analysed success by the number of enemy dead. | One of the most influential and transformative Bank Presidents and a spokesperson for developing countries. He applied his quantitative managerial program to achieving Bank expansion in lending volume, geographical reach and staffing, and diversifying sources of finance. Lending expansion came at the expense of quality. McNamara focused the Bank on inequality and poverty, basic needs, education, and rural development especially for smallholders. Strengthened aid coordination and research capacity. Successful in substantially increasing IDA replenishments through political lobbying. Responded to the OPEC oil crisis by expanding lending and introducing structural adjustment late in his term.

Source: Compiled by authors from a range of sources, basic details from World Bank website (2019).

3.2 The expansion of the MDB system: the role of the UN and regional politics

The World Bank’s shift to lending to developing countries occurred in the context of early Cold War hysteria. Despite the Cold War, many newly independent countries were assertive about their developmental needs and they were motivated by the success of the Marshall Plan. They focussed on the need for external capital for the development and were concerned that continued reliance on primary products exports would lead to under-development. This latter concern was empirically demonstrated by the work of Raúl Prebisch (1950) and Hans Singer (1950), whose separately published work on First-Third World trade, titled the Prebisch-Singer thesis, showed that the price of primary commodities, the main exports of developing countries, was declining relative to the price of manufactured exports from the First World. The declining terms of trade meant Third World countries would either need to export more and more primary commodities, change the structure of production in their economies, or live with increasing under-development. Faced with this dilemma, developing countries made a revolutionary push for soft finance to be provided through the UN and not the IBRD (Shaw 2005). The call was originally made by the Indian economist Dr. V.K.R.V. Rao in 1949 and was championed in developing countries and by Singer over the next decade. In 1952, the proposal was labelled the Special United Nations Fund for Economic Development (SUNFED) and it provided the core ideas for what became the IDA. SUNFED was to provide highly concessional loans and grants and be replenished regularly (Shaw 2005). The World Bank originally opposed the idea, in particular low-interest, long-term loans, as it perceived such loans would reduce the creditworthiness of borrowers (Mason and Asher 1973, 389–90).

The US was also opposed to SUNFED and little happened in IOs in these years without their imprimatur. US initial aid efforts focussed on technical assistance and Congress was very hostile to proposals for grant aid, indeed isolationist elements opposed any expansion of aid (Engerman 2018). The growth of MDF was an attractive alternative to grant aid and US President Truman’s famous Four Points Speech in 1949 opened the door for its further expansion (Peet 2003). Still, it took some time to convince Congress of this and an idea from a State Department official for an Asian Development Fund went by the wayside in 1955 (Engerman 2018). This was despite the famous Asian-African Conference taking place in Bandung in April 1955, where 29 Afro-Asian states met to promote economic and cultural cooperation and to oppose colonialism and neocolonialism; the Bandung Conference was a key step in the creation of the Non-Aligned Movement (NAM) in 1961.

The World Bank was focussed on expanding support for the private sector. President Eugene Black proposed the establishment of the IFC as a sibling to the IBRD, to fill a supposed void in private sector lending. The US originally opposed its establishment too, but reversed this as a way of being seen to respond to the SUNFED calls (Mason and Asher 1973, Shaw 2005). Thus, the IFC was established in 1956 ‘to further economic development by encouraging the growth of productive private enterprise in member countries, particularly in the less developed areas, supplementing’ IBRD activities (IFC 2012). The US shift was influenced by Cold War concerns too, which is clear from the fact that it created its own Development Loan Fund in 1957 under the Mutual Security Act aimed at strengthening ‘friendly foreign countries’ through ‘competitive free enterprise’ (United States Committee on Government Operations 1960, 6).

Other MDBs started to appear at this time. The Council of Europe Development Bank (CEB) (1956) and EIB (1958) were established without US involvement and are both borrower-led banks in contrast to the IBRD. They were early attempts to create a regional European bloc, as well as rebuild and strengthen Western Europe following the Second World War and during the early Cold War years (Bussière and Willaert 2006, Griffith-Jones and Tyson 2013). The CEB is a specialised development bank and it initially focussed on the welfare element of the Keynesian, welfare, modernisation model. Its social mandate aimed to help solve Europe’s problems focussing on the impact of refugees and displaced peoples. It established the idea of both a regional and specialised focus for the MDBs, demonstrating that MDBs could engage with social issues, something the IBRD had avoided. The EIB followed in 1958, established by the Treaty of Rome as part of the European integration project. It aimed to build a common market, facilitate European integration, and promote balanced growth, which set the region-building tone of the RDBs and returned to a modernisation, economic focus. Still, Keynesian social elements continued with its focus on ‘balanced and steady development’ (European Union 2002, 139). It claims not to be an MDB, but its structure and functions are so similar that we think that it doth protest too much (see Chapter 6). The EIB’s focus on region-building – it prioritises funding to ‘projects of common interest to several Member States’ (European Union 2002, 140) – was explicitly replicated in later regional and sub-regional banks (see Chapters 6 and 7). It was also the first MDB to specify that it is not-for-profit, in contrast to the IBRD being formally a profit-making institution and other MDBs being a mix.

Next came the US-backed IADB, established in 1959. As noted in Chapter 2, the early ideas for an inter-American bank pre-date the IBRD, although formal negotiations fell through. It was resurrected in the post-war era by the 1957 Economic Conference of the Organisation of American States. By 1958, the US supported the proposal, first and foremost because the US was concerned that the Cold War was impacting its zone of influence (Tussie 1995). Further, as discussed in more depth in Chapter 6, the IADB was seen as a counterweight to the IBRD’s rather monopolistic position (Phillips 2009) and as a response to the Bank’s perceived inadequate attention to Latin America and regional interests in integration (Barria and Roper 2004, Krasner 1981, Tussie 1995).

The IADB started a new approach to the purposes of the MDBs, moving away from the IBRD’s mandate of facilitating investment for productive purposes and promoting private investment to the broader goal of contributing ‘to the acceleration of the process of economic and social development of the regional developing country members, individually and collectively’ (IaDB 1996, 5). While this could be seen as broadly Keynesian, it also reflects the impact of structuralist and statist development ideas that came out of the UN’s Economic Commission for Latin America (UN-ECLA), which were popular in the region (Tussie 1995). Indeed, it had more flexibility to direct loans to the private sector than the World Bank (Humphrey 2016). This follows the strategy of import substitution industrialisation (ISI), which was the main way structuralism was operationalised to change the structure of production and avoid under-development (Rapley 2002). ISI was a key strategy in Latin America from the 1930s and was adopted by many newly independent states after the Second World War as well.

Although conforming to the IBRD’s banking model, the IADB was established with a concessional lending arm, the Fund for Special Operations (FSO). This indicated that it was possible to combine hard-nose banking functions with a social agenda. While Latin American states had a majority of votes in the main body, the US demanded a veto over FSO operations and insisted that the IADB be headquartered in Washington, DC (Humphrey 2016), demonstrating again the impact of geopolitics on MDBs. Technical assistance is included in the IADB’s functions, which was not the case in the earlier MDBs. This likely derived from the experience of the IBRD, which found it could not develop a project pipeline without the provision of extensive advisory services (IBRD 1948). This is further demonstration that the network between the MDBs started early. The establishing agreements of the subsequent RDBs – the AfDB, AsDB, and EBRD – all include technical assistance in their functions.

The IADB supported the creation of other RDBs (Culpeper 1997). Still, the supporters of SUNFED at the UN continued their efforts and even started drafting statutes in 1957. US views had been shifting, which was clear by 1958, but they wanted a soft lending facility under their control rather than the UN, hence tied it to the World Bank. The US had other motivations for supporting the IDA too, they had been accumulating non-convertible foreign exchange through the US food aid programme sale of surplus agricultural commodities and saw the IDA as an outlet for these holdings (Shaw 2005). Further, it was clear that the outlook for developing countries was not great and that the IBRD could not provide the needed support. Indeed, a report on the US Development Loan Fund had noted the IBRD was more like ‘the international equivalent of the Export-Import Bank rather than’ a loan fund (United States Committee on Government Operations 1960, 33). In other words, the IBRD had a hard-nosed business focus. Once the US supported the IDA idea, the US Treasury Secretary took an outline for it to the IBRD, and they then filled out the details and the IDA was launched in 1960.

The consequences of this decision were profound. The UN ‘became a residual organization in economic and social development programs’ (Shaw 2005, 58). The World Bank, in contrast, with the IDA add-on increased its resources and client base and was able to move into whole new areas of work that were not self-liquidating like most IBRD lending, including poverty and the social sector. The IDA may have slightly reduced Bank reliance on Wall Street, but it increased the power of major donor states because of the need for regular resource replenishments (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). The desirability of IDA resources helped facilitate structural adjustment lending in the 1980s at the same time as donors, especially the US, intervened more in policymaking. Overall, the IDA add-on put the Bank in a tremendous position of power in relation to borrowers, meaning that it is not a servant of sovereign states – as the UN system was designed to be (Shaw 2005, 59). The Bank was meant to liaise with the UN system but in practice even liaison has been weak and there is a chasm between the two organisations. In another weakening of the UN system, a group of Northern states set up a coordination mechanism for donors in 1960 through the grouping of rich states, the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), which came to be called the Development Assistance Committee (DAC). It gets to decide what counts as aid and has become an influential voice in development debates.

Despite the focus on poverty and social lending in the debate that produced the IDA, its purposes – like that of the IBRD – make no mention of poverty. The IDA aims to ‘promote economic development, increase productivity and thus raise standards of living…,’ which will trickle down to raise standards of living (World Bank 1960, 2). This is not surprising as the IBRD played a key role in drafting the Articles and President Black promised that the ‘IDA will not be a “soft lender”’ (cited in Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997, 155). To protect the IBRD’s creditworthiness, the IDA was created under its own establishing agreement, which duplicates the IBRD’s with three changes: first, the Articles identify developed and developing countries and link countries’ access to the IDA to their status to ration its concessional resources, second, the IDA’s voting structure is slightly more favourable to developing countries, and, third, the IDA can fund social projects. Even though they have separate Articles and finances, the IBRD and IDA function as one institution.

By the late 1960s, the World Bank was largely focussed on assisting poorer countries, having reduced lending to rich states, and diversified sectoral loan allocations (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997, 140). This did not happen just through the Bank’s own vision of course, but in the context of rapid decolonisation, demands from the Global South, and challenges to the Keynesian, welfare, modernisation development model. The IDA and retained IBRD earnings also facilitated expansion, though the big push took place under President McNamara (see Table 3.1), who turned his zeal for prosecuting the Vietnam War to combatting poverty or, to be precise, promoting redistribution with growth and later basic human needs. The Bank expanded into soft sectors including health, education, water supply, and agriculture. In a way, McNamara was re-inserting welfare into the Keynesian, welfare, modernisation model, but in a minimalist form with the focus on absolute poverty reduction rather than on equality and rights, which has continued to be the Bank’s focus. The basic needs approach increased the level of intervention in developing countries at the same time as bolstering the legitimacy of the Bank as a development agency (Rist 1997). It was, in Gramscian terms, part of the hegemonic struggle to shore up capitalist development combining coercive and consensual elements (Engel 2010).

From 1969, the Nixon Administration supported McNamara’s growth plans for the Bank, because they wanted to increase private US bank lending globally to centralise the role of the US dollar in international finance and hence shore up US hegemony (Gowan 1999, 22). The Bank was useful because of its role as a recycler of funds and signaller to private finance. In practice, basic needs lending expanded after 1974 when McNamara discovered the integrated rural development approach. By the later years of McNamara’s Presidency, the Keynesian consensus was under attack and neoliberalism and structural adjustment came to dominate the Bank, which is discussed in Chapter 4.

3.3 Sub-regional and general expansion of multilateral development banking

From 1960 to 1977, a further 18 MDBs were added to the system, ten of these in the 1970s. Only two were from Europe, the rest from the rapidly growing number of newly independent states. MDBs continued to grow too following the collapse of the Bretton Woods monetary order and the first oil shock in the early 1970s. Eight new MDBs were established between 1974 and 1979, indicating that they may even have been a response to the chaos generated by this time. This section explores the logic of this expansion linking it to geopolitics and development ideas, though given the number of actors, the section paints a broad picture, with the details of each MDB explored in later chapters.

After the IDA, the next MDB was from the Latin American region, which had fought for and won independence earlier than most of Africa and Asia. It was a sub-regional development bank (SRDB) and, like all the subsequent early SRDBs, it aimed to promote the integration and development of a sub-region. And growth of both regions and sub-regions were seen by structuralism as an instrument for promoting economic transformation (Bruszt and Palestini 2016). The Central American Bank for Economic Integration (CABEI) was established in 1960 by five Central American states, which were all members of the IADB. This makes it the first MDB established without the backing of a First World state. As part of their treaty on economic integration they established a SRDB to support sub-regionalisation, possibly taking inspiration from the European integration project and the EIB, but examining its purposes reveals clear influences from UN-ECLA and structuralism. As Chapter 7 outlines, CABEI’s objectives start with the aims visible in earlier MDBs of regional development and balanced economic and social development but go on to specify that it will support projects and programmes in infrastructure, industry, and agriculture that benefit and modernise the region. Thus, it incorporated ISI in its objectives more directly than the IADB. Further, CABEI’s subscriptions were not weighted, so founding states had equal shareholdings (Cochrane 1965), though this changed with the introduction of non-regional and non-founding member states, which quite a number of the smaller MDBs did in the 1980s, as discussed in the next chapter.

Several Soviet states created the International Bank for Economic Cooperation (IBEC) in 1964. It started as something closer to the IMF, but post-Cold War reforms saw it become an MDB. Next from what was then Communist Eastern Europe and Russia was the International Investment Bank (IIB) in 1970, a Soviet competitor to the World Bank. Its original aims are worth quoting as they are at one level so different from all the other SRDBs yet, at another level, they share the view of development as industrialisation and growth. It aims to provide:

long-term and medium-term credits primarily for the implementation of measures relating to the international socialist division of labour, specialization and co-operation in production, expenditure for the broadening of the raw materials and fuels base in the common interest and the building of projects in other branches of the economy…

(IIB 1970, 344)

The IIB’s aims have since been changed quite radically, which is discussed in more detail in Chapter 7.

The 1955 Bandung Conference helped stimulate the idea of pan-Africanism, and five African MDBs were created between 1964 and 1975, the first an RDB – the AfDB in 1964 – and then four SRDBs. The AfDB followed the IADB’s purposes in promoting accelerated economic and social development, and it also specified that development must be sustainable. Like CABEI, and inspired by NAM and Group of 77 (G77) agenda of seeking independent development, it was formed without any superpower or First World engagement (Culpeper 1997, English and Mule 1996, Mingst 1990). The four African SRDBs originally had only regional developing country membership as well and all arose from sub-regional integration efforts, which the UN Economic Commission for Africa (UN-ECA) played a key role in (Humphrey 2019). Many of the regional integration and trade agreements are no longer operational yet the MDBs remain. The SRDBs are the:

East African Development Bank (EADB), formed in 1967 to support the East African Community (EAC);

West African Development Bank (known by its French acronym, BOAD), established in 1973 as part of the West African Monetary Union (WAMU);

Development Bank of Central African States (known by its French acronym, BDEAC), set up in 1975 to support the Central African Economic and Monetary Community (CEMAC); and

Fund for Cooperation, Compensation, and Development formed as part of a second West African initiative – the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) – in 1975; in 1999, it was renamed the ECOWAS Bank for Investment and Development (EBID).

All four African MDBs have standard SRDB purposes, although the EADB includes a role for regional promotion and BOAD has a strong focus on mobilising domestic resources. These SRDBs demonstrate the conflicting forces at play in post-colonial Africa of fragmentation and cooperation – as in Latin America, economic cooperation was seen as vital to post-colonial development. Mostly the African SRDBs financed infrastructure and small and medium enterprises to support industrialisation (Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli 2018).

Following the AfDB, the next RDB was the AsDB established in 1966. It did not have anti-colonial credentials being proposed by Japan, then an emerging regional and global power. The US originally opposed the MDB’s formation but later changed mind, seeing it as a way to contain perceived Soviet and Chinese influence by fostering regional growth and cooperation (Dent 2008, Kappagoda 1995). With Japan and the US as its major shareholders, it adopted much more pragmatic and capitalist language in its Charter with the aim of fostering ‘economic growth and co-operation’ in the region (AsDB 1967, 2). Like the World Bank, the AsDB now articulates a poverty-free region as its mission. The AsDB mirrored earlier MDBs closely from its inception, with the first President Takeshi Watanabe attending IBRD and IADB meetings to see how they were run before the Asian MDB began operations (McCawley 2012). Notably, there are no SRDBs in South or Southeast Asia, though a couple emerged that cover Central Asia later.

The next two MDBs established were again in the Latin America and Caribbean region circa 1970 with a further one added in 1974, bringing the regional total to five MDBs. The Caribbean Development Bank (CDB) was established in 1969 to support regional and local financial institutions and the development of regional capital markets as well as the usual SRDB goals. The innovation of building local financial markets harks back to the failed attempts at creating an Inter-American Bank and is a reminder of the recent development of public and private financial markets in some parts of the Global South. The CDB originally had 16 regional members along with Canada and the UK as non-regional members. While additional stakeholders have been added including China in 1998, the US is still not a member. The famous development economist Sir W. Arthur Lewis was the CDB’s first president. Lewis was a key founder of classical Growth Theory which posited that states need to focus on growth, not redistribution, and that poverty was an employment problem, making it a suitable topic for economists (Engel 2019, Todaro 1985). His work on the need to transfer labour from the supposedly inefficient rural subsistence sector to the industrial high productivity sector was quite influential at the World Bank. The logic of most MDBs today is still to fund the enabling environment for this growth model, but the model has gaps and investments in industrialisation often came at a high human and environmental cost.

The Development Bank of Latin America (known by the Spanish acronym CAF) was established in 1970 and like the CDB it was tasked with ‘providing multiple financial services to clients in the public and private sectors’ in order to achieve regional integration and sustainable development (CAF 2015, 9). It started operations without member states from the Global North. USAID, Canada, the IADB, and a few European states provided resources early on but stopped, leading it to struggle to gain enough financial resources to operate until later restructuring (Humphrey 2016). The Financial Fund for the Development of the River Plate Basin (known since 2018 as FONPLATA Development Bank), followed in 1974 to support the River Plate Basin. It still has just five regional members: Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Paraguay, and Uruguay. It has a strong focus on studies and technical assistance, though they are also empowered to act as a financial agent or broker for loans for members (FONPLATA 2018).

Next in the MDB chronology is the Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development (AFESD). Its founding documents were prepared in 1968 but entered into force in 1972 and it was the first of a group of four diverse MDBs whose common feature is their Arab country-led shareholding. The Arab Fund is an SRDB with the rather pragmatic aim of ‘[f]inancing economic projects of an investment character… to public or private organizations and institutions, giving preference to economic projects that are vital to the Arab entity and to joint Arab projects’ (AFESD 2016). While it is best understood as an SRDB, we have included it in Chapter 8 as a specialised MDB alongside the other Arab-led MDBs as they are an interrelated group that emerged after oil prices started to increase in 1971 (Corm 2006). The Arab Bank for Economic Development in Africa (BADEA) was established in 1973. It was a response to the increasing anger in the Third World about rising oil prices but also reflected the Arab desire to replace Israeli influence in Africa and promote Arab access to raw materials (Shushan and Marcoux 2011). It was the first development bank whose aim was to promote linkages between two regions, by providing financing and technical assistance. It was quickly followed by the Islamic Development Bank (IsDB) in 1974, which is a specialised bank operated in accordance with Shari’ah financial principles that ban the practice of interest. Its capital was subscribed in a new accounting currency, the Islamic Dinar (Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli 2018). Its purposes are economic development and social progress, with the level of focus on human well-being standing out among the MDBs. It has stuck to its original, albeit broad, sectoral focus on transportation, infrastructure, energy, agriculture, and social infrastructure and not shifted with trends like policy-based loans, conditionality, or safeguards (Kellerman 2019). Its membership is not limited to Arab states but to those with a majority Islamic citizenry, making it a unique MDB.

Next came the Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) Fund for International Development (OFID) in 1976, which has the very pragmatic aim of promoting cooperation between OPEC member states and developing countries by providing financial support to the latter, making it a bit like BADEA. Its membership is again not limited to Arab states; indeed, Venezuela is the third largest shareholder. Looking at shareholdings in these Arab-led MDBs, Saudi Arabia is the largest shareholder in all except the Arab Fund where Kuwait has a slightly larger stake (Shushan and Marcoux 2011). Libya has large stakes in the BADEA and IsDB and is the third largest shareholder in the AFESD and sixth in the OFID, which is a left over from Muammar Gaddafi’s activist Islamic socialist agenda of the 1970s.

It is useful to follow the Arab-led MDBs with the International Fund for Agricultural Development (IFAD), established in 1977, because Arab states also played a key part in its formation. Intellectually informed by calls for a New International Economic Order (NIEO) in 1974, it is based on an amalgam of Keynesian and structuralist ideas. IFAD’s direct heritage is that of a challenge between OECD DAC donors and OPEC states in 1974 to each put up around $600 million for agricultural development in developing countries (Szasz 1999). This was following the early 1970s sub-Sahelian food crisis (Wihtol 2014) and a general increase in food insecurity aggravated by the 1973 oil shock. The negotiations took place in 1974 and 1975, just after the NIEO. IFAD’s structure was coped from the World Bank, but its shareholder structure gave equal voting shares to three groups: DAC donors, OPEC, and G77 states. The G77 states argued very strongly that votes within each group should be equally distributed and not on the basis of contribution as DAC and OPEC states wanted (Szasz 1999). The compromise was that each group could decide how they distributed votes and elected board members. The DAC managed to constrain the organisation, however, by mandating that IFAD could not undertake project appraisals, instead having to rely on evaluations conducted by other financial institutions.

One final MDB was created before 1979, the Nordic Investment Bank (NIB), established in 1976. It had been discussed since the 1950s by the five Nordic states – Denmark, Finland, Iceland, Norway, and Sweden – but a more favourable political climate and the oil shocks provided the needed impetus (Dennis 2015). It was set up simply to supplement existing institutions and finance and notably did not have a mandate for sub-regional projects.

Overall, by 1979, there were 22 MDBs. MDB creation was very high in Latin America (five banks) and across much of Africa (five banks), excluding the southern states where apartheid South Africa still exerted hegemonic influence. There were three banks established in Europe including the very large EIB, four Arab-led banks, and just one Asian MDB. But by 1979, state debt in many developing countries had already started to build up to problematic levels, and this enabled the emerging neoliberal doctrine to be imposed on states through loan conditionality, which is discussed in the next chapter. But to conclude this one we explore the debt crisis.

3.4 MDBs, debt, and the developing world debt crisis

Using debt to finance investments was a key part of the post-war Keynesian, modernisation, welfare model, which the MDBs were a key part of. But they face a unique situation, having a limited clientele and, as detailed in Chapter 5, their non-concessional lending arms need credit-worthy borrowers to get good credit ratings, which allows them to borrow cheaply on financial markets and on-lend. Still, with a limited number of borrowers, MDBs often become debt-pushers. If they do not keep pushing new loans out the door, they run into the problem that borrowers are paying back more than is being lent in new loans. This is called the negative net transfer problem. For most countries, MDBs are not their largest creditors but as Chapter 1 outlined, they play a range of roles in the development finance system. Their role expanded over the decades, with the World Bank at the centre thanks to its repository of data and reports. After the first debt crisis, the World Bank also became a debt collector and lender of last resort.

Development banks walk a fine line between pushing debt and worrying that recipients have too much of it. Debt was a challenge in some countries as early as the 1950s; a number of Latin American states had existing debt portfolios and they had faced two large debt crises in the 19th century and one in the 1940s as we saw in Chapter 2. The World Bank rescheduled loans to Haiti in the 1950s on balance of payment grounds and in 1965 made two loans to Brazil to cover the maturities due on earlier loans (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). India’s debt problems were notable from the mid-1960s, but it was cushioned by its high level of access to the highly concessional IDA, becoming its largest borrower; the IDA was colloquially referred to as the Indian Development Association. The IDA add-on enabled the IBRD to reduce its exposure to India and undoubtedly India only met some IBRD and other obligations thanks to IDA credits. Nevertheless, India asked the World Bank to lead a rescheduling in 1966 (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997).

A large debt build-up occurred in the 1970s bolstered by low interest rates and financial innovations beginning with the Eurodollar market and syndicated loans, where a group of banks lends to a borrower. The oil price hikes of the 1970s had very negative impacts on oil importing developing countries by increasing their costs and reducing export prices, meaning they had to borrow to cover the immediate costs of the shock. The oil shock created large revenues for oil exporters called petrodollars and these, along with the end of the fixed exchange rates system, contributed to a large increase in liquidity in private banks. Like MDBs, private banks need to on-lend their funds to pay interest to depositors. Developing countries offered a seemingly lucrative market and there was profligate and very large scale lending (Bracking 2009, Scammell 1983). Debt accumulation was largest in Latin America with several sub-Saharan African countries following suit. On average, debt-to-GDP ratios for low-income countries increased from 13% in 1970 to 46% in 1982 (Kose et al. 2020, 62). Loans were also made to what can only be described as illegitimate, odious, or corrupt regimes (Toussaint 2019). And too many projects did not benefit local populations, or caused too much environmental, social, or human rights harm. Legal and illegal capital flight was a particular problem, as Caufield (1998, 132) noted, the ‘amount of money that left the Third World during the lending boom is staggering. The World Bank estimates that between 1976 and 1984, capital flight from Latin America equalled the increase in the continent’s external debt.’

The World Bank under McNamara had a liberal approach to debt and expanded Bank lending while encouraging developing countries to expand their access to private finance (Caufield 1998, George and Sabelli 1994, Toussaint 1999). The South was creating their own MDBs too, further expanding debt relations. While private sector lending accounted for most of the debt, MDBs signalled that countries were credit-worthy. It seemed for a time like the lending would be sustainable, though that was illusory. The immediate triggers for the debt crisis were the second oil shock in 1979 and the Volcker shock of 1981. The second oil shock led to a recession that hit the exports of developing countries very hard. Developed countries tightened their fiscal and monetary policy leading to increased interest rates globally and increased debt service payments. Paul Volcker, then Chair of the US Federal Reserve, almost doubled the US federal funds rate in 1981 to 20%, in what is often referred to as the Volcker shock. Given the power of the US dollar, it effectively sets global interest rates, still US banks also directly held 37% of the $600 billion developing country debt (Bracking 2009). In 1982, amid a global recession partly bought on by the Volcker Shock, Mexico defaulted on its loans. Quickly thereafter most private lending to developing states stopped and the debt crisis began. Some 40 states found themselves in arrears, 27 had to restructure debts and 16 of those were in Latin America and the Caribbean (Kose et al. 2020).

The IMF, World Bank, and larger MDBs thrive in financial crises. Borrowing increases and private finance looks to them as debt collectors and as a safe place to invest. In the 1982 crisis, the debt deals turned private debts into public ones; the private banks were largely paid and even received large fees for loan rescheduling. The Bank and other MDBs took on a larger share of developing country debt and became the global system’s main debt collectors. They had done this in part using what George and Sabelli (1994, 55) aptly called McNamara’s ‘parting gift’ to the World Bank: structural adjustment loans. These enabled the principles of the new Washington Consensus to be enforced upon developing countries with ferocity.

3.5 Conclusion

This chapter shows how MDBs were created during the modernisation or Bretton Woods era, which had a relatively non-financialised banking system in response to the excesses of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The Cold War political context was a key factor in many of the MDB creation – many larger MDBs were created by the Western block and the US as the political hegemon of the time had to be supportive or at least not obstructive. The Soviet Union played a similar role for states then in its sphere of influence, but it was not as interested in MDBs and only the IBEC and IIB were established in its sphere. Some of the MDBs in Africa and Latin America reflected more structuralist development ideas.

The MDBs were designed to meet one of the shortcomings of capitalist finance; private banks can be risk averse, particularly in developing country contexts, and so national and multilateral development banks were meant to provide an alternative way to boost investment. However, the MDBs played a role in the growing financialisation of the 1970s by encouraging lending to the Third World and setting standards for it as well as by promoting new financial instruments, so they were a contributor to the developing country debt crisis. Financialisation took off during the 1980s, which is where Chapter 4 takes up the story: MDB creation in the neoliberal era.

Bibliography

AFESD. 2016. Agreement Establishing the Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development. Kuwait. Accessed 14 May 2020. http://www.arabfund.org/Default.aspx?pageId=429.

Amin, Samir. 2014. Capitalism in the Age of Globalization: The Management of Contemporary Society. London and New York: Zed Books.

AsDB. 1967. Agreement Establishing the Asian Development Bank. Manila: Asian Development Bank. Accessed 24 November 2020. https://www.adb.org/documents/agreement-establishing-asian-development-bank-adb-charter

Barria, Lilian A., and Steven D. Roper. 2004. “Economic Transition in Latin American and Post-Communist Countries: A Comparison of Multilateral Development Banks.” International Journal of Politics, Culture, and Society 17 (4):619–38. doi: 10.1023/ B:IJPS.0000031235.74193.a4.

Berger, Mark T. 2004. The Battle for Asia: From Decolonization to Globalization. London and New York: Routledge Curzon.

Block, Fred L. 1977. The Origins of International Economic Disorder: A Study of United States International Monetary Policy from World War II to the Present. Berkeley: University of California Press.

Bracking, Sarah. 2009. Money and Power: Great Predators in the Political Economy of Development. London: Pluto Press.

Bruszt, Lazlo, and Stefano Palestini. 2016. “Regional Development Governance.” In The Oxford Handbook of Comparative Regionalism, edited by Tanja A. Börzel and Thomas Risse, 374–404. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

Bussière, Eric, and Emilie Willaert. 2006. Council of Europe Development Bank: The Social Development Bank in Europe. Paris: Council of Europe Development Bank.

CAF. 2015. Agreement Establishing Corporación Andina de Fomento. Caracas: Banco de Desarrollo de América Latina. Accessed 24 November 2020. https://www.caf.com/media/29934/caf-agreement-establishing-10032015.pdf

Caufield, Catherine. 1998. Masters of Illusion : The World Bank and the Poverty of Nations. London: Pan Books.

Cochrane, James D. 1965. “The Central American Bank for Economic Integration: A Descriptive Note.” Caribbean Studies 5 (2):64–73.

Corm, Georges. 2006. “The Arab Experience.” In Regional Financial Cooperation, edited by José Antonio Ocampa, 291–328. Washington, DC: UN ECLA and Brookings Insitution Press.

Culpeper, Roy. 1997. Titans or Behemoths? London: Lynne Rienner.

Delikanli, Ihsan Ugur, Todor Dimitrov, and Roena Agolli. 2018. Multilateral Development Banks: Governance and Finance. Cham: Palgrave Macmillan.

Dennis, Bengt. 2015. “Green Light at Third Attempt: How NIB Came to be Forty Years Ago.” Nordiic Investment Bank. Accessed 20 May. https://www.nib.int/who_we_are/news_and_media/articles/1761/green_light_at_third_attempt_how_nib_came_to_be_forty_years_ago.

Dent, Christopher M. 2008. “The Asian Development Bank and Developmental Regionalism in East Asia.” Third World Quarterly 29 (4):767–86. doi: 10.1080/01436590802052714.

Engel, Susan. 2010. The World Bank and the Post-Washington Consensus in Vietnam and Indonesia: Inheritance of Loss. London: Routledge.

Engel, Susan. 2019. “Development Economics: Classical, Neoclassical, Critical.” In Oxford Research Encyclopedia of International Studies, edited by Renée Marlin-Bennett, 1–24. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

Engerman, David C. 2018. The Price of Aid: The Economic Cold War in India. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.

English, E. Phillip, and Harris M. Mule. 1996. The African Development Bank. London: Lynne Rienner.

European Union. 2002. Consolidated Versions of the Treaty on European Union and the Treaty Establishing the European Community. Brussels: European Union. Accessed 24 November 2020. https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A12002E%2FTXT

Fine, Ben. 2001. Social Capital versus Social Theory: Political Economy and Social Science at the Turn of the Millennium. London: Routledge.

FONPLATA. 2018. Financial Fund for the Development of the River Plate Basin Articles of Agreement. Accessed 24 November 2020. https://www.fonplata.org/sites/default/files/paginas-fonplata/archivos/EN%20-%20Constitutive%20Agreement%20%28Update%202018%29.pdf

Galbraith, John Kenneth. 1975. “How Keynes Came to America.” In Essays on John Maynard Keynes, edited by Milo Keynes, 132–41. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Gardner, Richard N. 1980. Sterling-dollar Diplomacy in Current Perspective: The Origins and the Prospects of Our International Economic Order, 3rd ed. New York: Columbia University Press.

George, Susan, and Fabrizio Sabelli. 1994. Faith and Credit: The World Bank’s Secular Empire. London: Penguin Books.

Gowan, Peter. 1999. The Global Gamble: Washington’s Faustian Bid for World Dominance. London: Verso.

Griffith-Jones, Stephany, and Judith Tyson. 2013. The European Investment Bank: Lessons for Developing Countries. In WIDER Working Paper.

Helleiner, Eric. 2014. Forgotten Foundations of Bretton Woods: International Development and the Making of the Postwar Order. Ithaca, NY and London: Cornell University Press.

Helleiner, Eric. 2017. “What’s Been Missing from Conventional Histories of Bretton Woods?” In Global Perspectives on the Bretton Woods Conference and the Post-War World Order, edited by Giles Scott-Smith and J. Simon Rofe, 17–34. Cham: Palgrave Macmillan.

Humphrey, Chris. 2016. “The Invisible Hand: Financial Pressures and Organisational Convergence in Multilateral Development Banks.” The Journal of Development Studies 52 (1):92–112. doi: 10.1080/00220388.2015.1075978.

Humphrey, Chris. 2019. “‘Minilateral’ Development Banks: What the Rise of Africa’s Trade and Development Bank Says about Multilateral Governance.” Development and Change 50 (1):164–90. doi: 10.1111/dech.12467.

IaDB. 1996. Agreement Establishing the Inter-American Development Bank. Washington, DC: Inter-American Development Bank. Accessed 11 March 2020. https://www.iadb.org/en/legal-resource-center/historic-agreement-establishing-inter-american-development-bank

IBRD. 1948. Third Annual Report to the Board of Governors, 1947–1948. Washington, DC: International Bank for Reconstruction and Development.

IFC. 2012. Articles of Agreement. Washington, DC: International Finance Corporation. Accessed 24 November 2020. https://www.ifc.org/wps/wcm/connect/corp_ext_content/ifc_external_corporate_site/about+ifc_new/ifc+governance/articles/about+ifc+-+ifc+articles+of+agreement

IIB. 1970. Agreement Concerning the Establishment of an International Investment Bank. New York: United Nations – Treaty Series Volume 801, 1975. Accessed 11 March 2020. https://treaties.un.org/doc/Publication/UNTS/Volume%20801/v801.pdf

Kappagoda, Nihal. 1995. The Asian Development Bank. London: Lynne Rienner.

Kapur, Devesh, John P. Lewis, and Richard Webb. 1997. The World Bank Its First Half Century, Volume 1: History. 2 vols. Vol. 1: History. Washington, DC: Brookings Institution Press.

Kellerman, Miles. 2019. “The Proliferation of Multilateral Development Banks.” Review of International Organization 14 (1):107–45. doi: 10.1007/s11558-018-9302-y.

Keynes, John Maynard. 1973. The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money. London: Macmillan for the Royal Economic Society.

Kose, M. Ayhan, Peter Nagle, Franziska Ohnsorge, and Naotaka Sugawara. 2020. Global Waves of Debt: Causes and Consequences. Washington, DC: World Bank.

Krasner, Stephen D. 1981. “Power Structures and Regional Development Banks.” International Organization 35 (2):303–28.

Mason, Edward S., and Robert E. Asher. 1973. The World Bank Since Bretton Woods. Washington, DC: The Brookings Institution.

McCawley, Peter. 2012. Banking on the Future of Asia and the Pacific: 50 Years of the Asian Development Bank. Manila: Asian Development Bank.

Meade, James. 1975. “The Keynesian Revolution.” In Essays on John Maynard Keynes, edited by Milo Keynes. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Mingst, Karen. 1990. Politics & the African Development Bank. Lexington: The University of Kentucky Press.

Murphy, Hannah. 2014. “The World Bank and Core Labour Standards: Between Flexibility and Regulation.” Review of International Political Economy 21 (2):399–431. doi: 10.1080/09692290.2013.779591.

Oliver, Robert W. 1971. Early Plans for a World Bank, Princeton Studies in International Finance No. 29. Princeton, NJ: Department of Economics, Princeton University.

Oliver, Robert W. 1975. International Economic Co-operation and the World Bank. London and Basingstoke: Macmillan Press.

Peet, Richard. 2003. Unholy Trinity: The IMF, World Bank and WTO. London: Zed Books.

Phillips, David A. 2009. Reforming the World Bank: Twenty Years of Trial – and Error. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Prebisch, Raúl. 1950. The Economic Development of Latin America and Its Principle Problems. New York: United Nations.

Rapley, John. 2002. Understanding Development: Theory and Practice in the Third World. Boulder, CO: Lynne Reinner Publishers Inc.

Rist, Gilbert. 1997. The History of Development: From Western Origins to Global Faith. Translated by Patrick Camiller. London and New York: Zed Books.

Roll, Eric. 1973. A History of Economic Thought, 4th ed. London: Faber and Faber Ltd.

Scammell, W.M. 1983. The International Economy Since 1945, 2nd ed. London: Macmillan Education Ltd.

Shaw, D. John. 2005. “Turning Point in the Evolution of Soft Financing: The United Nations and the World Bank.” Canadian Journal of Development Studies XXVI (1):43–61.

Shushan, Debra, and Christopher Marcoux. 2011. “The Rise (and Decline?) or Arab Aid: Generosity and Allocation in the Oil Era.” World Development 39 (11):1969–80.

Singer, Hans W. 1950. “The Distribution of Gains between Investing and Borrowing Countries.” American Economic Review 40 (2):478.

Szasz, Paul C. 1999. “Establishment of the International Fund for Agricultural Development.” Studies in Transnational Legal Policy 31–32:32–43.

Todaro, Michael P. 1985. Economic Development in the Third World: An Introduction to Problems and Policies in a Global Perspective, 3rd ed. New York: Longman.

Toussaint, Eric. 1999. Your Money or Your Life! The Tyranny of Global Finance. Translated by Raghu Krishnan and Vicki Briault Manus. London: Pluto Press.

Toussaint, Eric. 2008. The World Bank: A Critical Primer. Translated by Elizabeth Anne, Vicki Briault, Bertrand Declercq, Sushovan Dhar, Judith Harris, Raghu Krishnan, Marie Lagatta, Christine Pagnoulle, Véronique Renard, Gillian Sloane-Seale and Diren Valayden. London, Anne Arbor: Pluto Press in associatin with CADTM, Committee for the Abolition of Third World Debt.

Toussaint, Eric. 2019. The Debt System: A History of Sovereign Debts and Their Repudiation. Chicago, IL: Haymarket Books.

Tussie, Dianne. 1995. The Inter-American Development Bank. London: Lynne Rienner.

United States Committee on Government Operations. 1960. Operations of the Development Loan Fund. Washington, DC: US Government Printing Office.

Urquidi, Victor L. 1996. “Reconstruction vs. Development: The IMF and the World Bank.” In The Bretton Woods – GATT System: Retrospect and Prospect After Fifty Years, edited by Orin Kirshner, 30–51. Armonk, NY: M.E. Sharp.

Wihtol, Robert. 2014. Whither Multilateral Development Finance? In AsDBI Working Paper Series. Tokyo: Asian Development Bank Institute.

World Bank. 1960. International Development Association Articles of Agreement. Washington, DC: World Bank. Accessed 10 March 2020. https://www.worldbank.org/en/about/articles-of-agreement

World Bank. 2012. International Bank of Reconstruction and Development Articles of Agreement. Washington, DC: World Bank. Accessed 24 November 2020. https://www.worldbank.org/en/about/articles-of-agreement/ibrd-articles-of-agreement.

4 Development thinking, debt, and the multilateral development bank system: 1980–2020

This second chapter on the evolution of the multilateral development bank (MDB) system starts in 1980 when neoliberalism captured the global political economy including the World Bank and other large MDBs. It journeys through a range of modifications to neoliberalism leading to the current era, which we call retroliberal following Murray and Overton (2016). There were nine MDBs established in this period, eight still functioning, thus by the end of 2020, there were 30 functioning MDBs, several with multiple financing arms. As with Chapter 3, the emergence of and shifts in the MDBs are linked to three factors: geopolitics, development discourse, and debt relations.

This chapter is divided into three periods, each linked to a major debt crisis that can be associated with calls capitalism’s need for spatial fixes (Harvey 2010). The first period was high neoliberalism or the Washington Consensus era; it lasted from 1980 to 1997 and began and ended with debt crises. At the start, the Third World debt crisis saw large MDBs become debt collectors and impose the new orthodoxy of free markets, free trade, small government, and individual responsibility on recipient states. Only a few MDBs were created during this period, including the only MDB with a pro-democracy, pro-market mandate: the EBRD. The Washington Consensus era ended with the 1997 Asian Financial Crisis, by which time the social costs of fundamentalist neoliberalism had become too great, including increasing poverty and social inequalities. The post-Washington Consensus era of 1998–2009 was the response to the problems of orthodox neoliberalism. Poverty reduction seemed to replace economic growth at the top of the development agenda, supported by the 2000 MDGs and, later, the 2015 SDGs. However, the term post-Washington Consensus highlights the continuities with neoliberalism – the focus on growth and private markets had not disappeared and the poverty-reduction agenda was ultimately rather minimalist; still, there was a sense that the development agenda had become more progressive. This period saw the rise of China and leftist movements in Latin America, which resulted in an increased focus on the role of the state and new development paradigms aimed at challenging the Washington Consensus. The era closed when debt expansion in the US and Western and Central Europe achieved critical mass in the 2007–8 GFC.

The GFC changed development discourse, but not as significantly as would be hoped. The moniker retroliberal for the period 2010–20 highlights that policy responses to the GFC mostly shored up the position of capital over labour by socialising private losses while maintaining the privatisation of gains. Financialisation was only reined in for a brief moment, before again being unleashed in another example of how the practices of neoliberalism adapt to circumstances (Cahill 2014). Still, a more state-centric, nationalist era has emerged. Aid and development finance are again viewed in terms of the benefits they provide to donor states’ firms rather than to poverty reduction. Further, in large part thanks to Chinese interests, infrastructure is again a key focus for development finance, which is a return to modernisation era thinking along with the revised fixation on economic growth. Hence the retro prefix makes sense; it hints at the retrospective and retrograde elements of development discourse in 2020, with the MDBs again at centre stage after having taken somewhat of a back seat during the early 2000s.

A major danger of this shift is its impact on debt. Already prior to the 2020 Coronavirus crisis, the IMF and World Bank were warning of growing debt, with the Bank calling the build-up of debt in EMDEs from 2010 to 2018 the ‘largest, fastest and most broad-based increase’ in the past 50 years (Kose et al. 2020, 111). COVID-19 is causing further debt build-up and may trigger a debt crisis, whereas the usual triggers of the past 50 years were financial or banking crises. It is an emerging context, yet it seems rather clear that the MDBs are again going to be key players in another debt crisis.

The three eras explored in the chapter each follows the same structure: first, changes in developing thinking are briefly analysed, second, changes in the World Bank are outlined, followed by a third section on changes in the other MDBs, and a fourth analysing the growth of new MDBs in each era.

4.1 The Washington Consensus era: 1980–97

The global shift from the Keynesian, welfare, modernisation model to neoliberal structural adjustment – or austerity politics – must be told in conjunction with that of the IMF and World Bank. This is because the policy prescriptions associated with this neoliberal approach were negotiated between the US and the Bretton Woods twins in Washington, DC, and hence are called the Washington Consensus (Williamson 1990). The policies reflected the resurgence of a strand of neoclassical economics propounded by scholars like Friedrich von Hayek and Milton Friedman, which rejected the post-war consensus and instead promoted the moral and economic priority of individuals and markets over society and the state. It was a broad project ushered in by a new politico-economic climate with the election of Margaret Thatcher in the UK, Ronald Reagan in the US, and Helmut Kohl in West Germany. There were neoliberal regimes elected or imposed through coups and other non-electoral mechanisms around the world, for example, the Augusto Pinochet regime in Chile. Multinational corporations promoted neoliberal approaches in ways that benefitted them. In Gramscian terms, neoliberalism’s spread was through both consent and coercion. In examining the practices of governments, it is important to remember that they have been happy to implement a range of policies that are not always immediately in keeping with neoliberalism or may not appear to be neoliberal, but this pragmatic approach reinforces the legitimacy of that state and often serves particular capitalist interests. In the wake of financial and banking crises, the GFC being a case in point, governments have often resorted to Keynesian-type policies, but generally only as a temporary measure in order to deepen neoliberalism in the long run (Cahill 2014).

The Washington Consensus clustered around three broad commitments: macroeconomic stability, outward orientation, and domestic liberalisation (Fine 2001). In the early years, it tended to be implemented in two phases: first, short-term macroeconomic stabilisation carried out quickly via ‘big bang’ reforms, which was the focus of IMF programmes; and, second, long-term exhaustive microeconomic reforms including trade liberalisation, privatisation of state-owned enterprises, and then later utilities, changes to taxation, land titling to make land more easily alienable, labour market reform, and deregulation of banking and capital movement (Chossudovsky 1997). This latter programme tended to be implemented jointly by the IMF, World Bank, and RDBs. The Washington Consensus was based on a ‘profoundly cynical view of the state in developing countries’ (Toye 1993, 135).

The Third World debt crisis provided the IMF and World Bank the opportunity to implement neoliberal policies as loan conditions, which often supported US hegemony and made the Global South structurally more open to US goods and finance (Gowan 1999). As time passed, there was variation in the Bank’s approach, mostly prompted by the failures of neoliberal austerity policies. The number of people living under the absurdly low $1 per day international poverty line increased in many regions. The 1980s were thus labelled the lost decade for developing countries, particularly those in Latin America and sub-Saharan Africa. For much of Africa, the debt crisis was not resolved until the late 1990s. In Latin America, where the 1980s debt relief schemes were targeted, growth remained low. The debt management processes also saw the Paris Club and multilaterals holding an increasing share of EMDE debt and the new loans they provided were often used to pay arrears on private sector debt.

There were two early additions to the Washington Consensus to try to improve performance. One was good governance, which initially meant multi-party elections but was expanded to include anti-corruption initiatives and the adoption of Western budgetary and auditing systems. The second was a focus on poverty and minimalist social safety; arguably without some focus on poverty, neoliberalism was in danger of collapsing. In 1990, the World Bank’s influential World Development Report was grandly titled Poverty and on 31 December 1991, poverty appeared in the Bank’s mission statement (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). Poverty reduction is the neoliberal alternative to redistribution and social democratic welfare systems because it is a minimalist idea that defines equity and equality as getting people above the international poverty line – now at $1.90 a day – and no more. It posits that getting out of poverty mostly involves individual pursuit of increased productivity (Cammack 2004) and re-awakens the distinction between the deserving and undeserving poor. In 1990, the UN Human Development Reports first appeared too, demonstrating a re-emergence of the UN system in development space, as a timid challenger to World Bank.

The literature on the empirical and theoretical failures of the Washington Consensus increased over the 1990s. GDP in Latin America only returned to its pre-debt crisis level in 1993 (Kose et al. 2020). The IFIs ‘big bang’ reform approach in the former Soviet Union was a failure as was their response to the 1997 Asian Financial Crisis. This 1990s debt wave was mostly in East Asia and some other emerging economies and was predominately caused by an upsurge in private sector debt following liberalisation and deregulation, while the Brady bonds created as part of the resolution of the Latin American debt crisis stimulated the development of sovereign bond markets in developing countries. In the case of the Asian Financial Crisis, former World Bank Chief Economist Joseph Stiglitz (2000, 60) concluded that the IMF’s response made the crisis ‘deeper, longer and harder.’ Sustained pressure on the Bank led it to claim by the late 1990s that it had moved beyond the Washington Consensus. What emerged, however, was merely a modified post-Washington Consensus.

While neoliberalism reigned at the World Bank, in academia in the 1980s and 1990s there was a flourishing of critical development approaches. These came from eclectic fields: concerns about the negative impact on women of the development project evolved into a sophisticated literature on gender and development; the environmentalist movement expanded, focussing attention on sustainability; scholars and activists highlighted the importance of grassroots concerns and indigenous knowledges; structuralism and Critical Theory continued to unpick the material interests at work behind development interventions; and, and the post-development school inspired by Foucault and post-structuralism explained the extent to which development was a neo-colonial and Eurocentric project that needed to be challenged from the grassroots (Willis 2005). The debate around gender, participation, and the environment were all taken up by the Bank, other MDBs, and the wider development community, though mostly in instrumentalist ways that ensured an expanded commitment to neoliberalism.

4.1.1 Key developments at the World Bank

At the World Bank, Reagan appointee Alden Winship Clausen ensured a neoliberal agenda was followed, though given that the organisation had been shaped by bankers, the shift was not always large (Engel and Bazbauers 2020). The initial debt crisis response plan – the 1985 Baker Plan – involved the IFIs and private banks providing additional resources to debtor states in return for structural adjustment. The 1989 Brady Plan also leveraged Bank resources and demanded further structural adjustment, so that the Bank became a key player in debt management (George and Sabelli 1994, Woods 2006). Developing country debt increased during the 1980s and more of it was owed to IFIs than to private sources (Bello 1994). Average annual Bank commitments grew from $5.36 billion in 1970–79 to $15.69 billion in 1980–89 and $22.03 in 1990–95 (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997, 6), increasing Bank leverage over borrowing countries.

The World Bank’s environmental failings started coming home to roost during Clausen’s presidency. The infamous Polonoroeste project paving 1,500 kilometres of highway through Brazil’s Amazon resulted in mass deforestation and immiseration of the local Amerindian tribes. The bad press for the Bank was a factor in the establishment of its first environment department in 1987 (Rich 1994). That did not stop them financing the Narmada Sardar Sarovar dam in India starting in 1988 that produced one of the world’s largest social movements up to that time. Despite its very poor environmental track record, the Bank became one of the chief operational arms of the Global Environmental Facility (GEF) established in 1992. The issues of the MDBs and the environment are discussed further in Chapter 10. The Bank introduced an Inspection Panel in 1993 for project affected persons to have their concerns heard, with the US playing a key role in its establishment (Park 2017). Over the next decade, the AfDB, AsDB, IADB, and EBRD all adopted similar accountability mechanisms due to a combination of US pressure, institutional isomorphism, and pressure from civil society organisations (Park 2014, Uhlin 2016). This is evidence of an interconnected MDB system.

The period from 1980 to 1997 saw three one-term World Bank Presidents – Clausen, Barber Conable, and Lewis Preston – and their key contributions and major events are outlined in Table 4.1.

Table 4.1 World Bank Presidents 1981–95

Name and term | Background | Legacy
Alden Winship Clausen 1981–6 | Born in US, attended Carthage College and University of Minnesota, lawyer, banker. | Led the Bank during the 1980s recession and developing world debt crisis. Strong focus on neoliberal free markets, structural adjustment, and coordination with the IMF. These policies damaged the Bank’s global reputation. Priority investment areas were agriculture, energy, and sub-Saharan Africa. Introduced innovations in guarantees and co-financing with commercial banks. The Bank’s poor environmental standards became a focus of NGOs and media.
Barber Conable 1986–91 | Born in US, attended Cornell University, short legal career, long-term Republican politician first in New York state then House of Representatives. | The US’ refusal to ratify Clausen’s last budget forced Conable into a major, disruptive reorganisation, vacating all positions. The cuts reinforced dominance of neoliberal ideas in the Bank. He established the Bank’s first environment department in 1987 and started negotiations on the GEF. Conable gained approval for a large IBRD capital increase in 1988 and IFC in 1991. Strengthened focus on poverty but in ways that promoted privatisation and proletarianisation. The Bank became increasingly involved in debt management.
Name and term | Background | Legacy
Lewis Thompson Preston 1991–5 | Born in US, served as a Marine during WWII, attended Harvard University, long banking career with JP Morgan. | Reaffirmed the Bank’s poverty focus and took a pragmatic, client-focused approach to management. Commissioned Wapenhans Report, which showed declining project quality inside the Bank. Established the Inspection Panel in 1993, and GEF had the Bank as a key administrator; Preston said development and environmental protection were complementary. Indigenous issues and resettlement gained attention after the disastrous Sardar Sarovar project in India; the Morse Commission report on it was prototype for the Inspection Panel. 24 new members joined IBRD and 20 IDA after collapse of USSR and many obtained loans.

Source: Compiled by authors from a range of sources, basic details from World Bank website (2019).

4.1.2 Key developments in other MDBs

Several MDBs were restructured in this era in response to either the debt crisis or the exigencies from the crises of the 1970s and the growth of globalised finance. Others, particularly the RDBs, became partners in pushing Washington Consensus policies on borrowing states (Babb 2009). Given the debt crisis centred on Latin America and the Caribbean, the IADB became a key player. In the Latin American RDB, there was a dramatic increase in their equivalent of adjustment programmes, indeed the US demanded that 25% of resources were devoted to such loans (Babb 2009, Kellerman 2019). There was also an increasing politicisation of lending policy, which regional member states protested with little success (Kellerman 2019). A large capital increase followed in 1988, so by 1994 it had become the region’s main source of development financing. The IADB added new private sector financing and insurance arms in this period too.

The SRDBs in the region struggled, with CABEI losing its ability to remain a regional member-only MDB (Cevallos 1996); the first non-regional members were Taiwan and Mexico in 1992 and Argentina and Colombia in 1995 and 1997. In 1990, CAF also started expanding its membership to include 12 additional countries from Latin America and the Caribbean as well as Spain and Portugal and then 13 private regional banks because its ‘finances were in a precarious state’ (Humphrey 2016, 104). In order to renew its effectiveness and relevance, CAF restructured its corporate model to resemble the World Bank and IADB and hired consultants ‘from Coopers and Lybrand and a former World Bank vice president to review the CAF’s operations and make recommendations for overhauling internal process’ (Humphrey 2016, 104).

Most of the African SRDBs were greatly affected by the economic downturn of the 1970s and this spilt over into the 1980s and even 1990s. Problems were compounded by failed member integration, lack of political commitment to regional actions, loan non-repayments worsening portfolio performance, reluctance to borrow from foreign donors, and deteriorating economic conditions in Southern Africa (Mistry and Kritzinger-van Niekerk 1998). The situation was so problematic for the EADB that it was almost dissolved during the late 1970s and early 1980s. The African SRDBs started admitting new members during the 1980s. Importantly, it was not just new non-regional member states but also MDBs, IFIs, national development banks, and even private banks, though the shareholdings tended to remain small.

The European-based MDBs were not particularly impacted by the debt crisis, and the Arab-led banks were setting up and expanding. The IsDB, in line with its distaste for conditionality, never offered structural adjustment programmes or policy-based lending (Kellerman 2019). Asia was also not hit particularly hard by the debt crisis and the AsDB slowly expanded, propelled by the addition of China as a borrower in 1986. The Asian RDB also started lending to the private sector in 1983, mirroring Washington Consensus trends. In regard to the specialised development banks, IFAD was restructured in 1995 making it more like the World Bank (Szasz 1999), and the NIB became a development group with the establishment of the Nordic Development Fund (NDF) in 1989, which is a regional financing mechanism linking Nordic countries to developing states.

4.1.3 New MDBs

MDB creation slowed but did not come to a standstill during the Washington Consensus era; five new banks were created between 1980 and 1997, though the Development Bank of the States of Great Lakes (BDEGL) established in 1980 was not operational long. It was another African SRDB founded to support a regional economic community, the Economic Community of the Great Lakes Countries. It was proposed in 1977 and became effective in 1980 and included two non-regional members: Belgium and the AfDB (The New Times 2009). Conflict between its regional member states of Rwanda, Burundi, and the Democratic Republic of the Congo led to its collapse in 1993. Discussions were held in 2009 about re-opening it but little seems to have happened.

The next MDB was the first of a sub-group of SRDBs focussed on trade and development, which combine the functions of an MDB with a multilateral version of national export-import banks. They are often focussed on regional infrastructure. The Eastern and Southern African Trade and Development Bank (TDB) was established in 1985. It came out of African regional integration efforts, and then called the Preferential Trade Agreement (PTA) of Eastern and Southern Africa – now called the Common Market for Eastern and Southern Africa – so it was initially called the PTA Bank. Southern Africa had remained outside earlier regional integration programmes but with Zimbabwe’s transition to majority rule in 1980, the door opened for expansion south.

The Pacific Islands Development Bank (PIDB) came next in 1989. It was established by a group of US-associated states in the Pacific, which worried that the US was going to end aid (Mak and Naya 1994). Despite its name, it only covers Micronesia and not any of the Polynesian or Melanesian Pacific Island states. Most of those states were already members of the AsDB, which has been the Pacific’s ‘principal multilateral development finance institution,’ even though most Polynesian and Melanesian states are also members of the World Bank (Mak and Naya 1994, 36).

Established in 1991, the EBRD came in the wake of the collapse of communism and at the height of neoliberal fervour. It has the most political and neoliberal aim of any MDB, which is ‘to foster the transition towards open market-oriented economies and to promote private and entrepreneurial initiative in the Central and Eastern European countries committed to and applying the principles of multiparty democracy, pluralism and market economics’ (EBRD 2013, 4). Indeed, the EBRD is the only MDB with an explicitly political mandate. Its region was extended to include Mongolia and the Southern and Eastern Mediterranean after 2006, which has expanded its lending. It has adopted a persona more alike a commercial bank than a traditional MDB (Babb 2009), but it still operates as an MDB. It is the smallest of the RDBs but may benefit from an InvestEU programme that was being legislated in 2020.

The second trade and development bank of the period was the Black Sea Trade and Development Bank (BSTDB), which was established in 1997 and became operational in 1999. Like all SRDBs, it was linked to a regional cooperation forum and has as its first goal assisting the transition of member states towards economic prosperity as well as promoting regional projects and banking services. It originally thought that trade finance would be its bread and butter; however, its portfolio is dominated by project loans either directly or through financial intermediaries (BSTDB 2019).

The continued growth of MDBs during this period demonstrates that they were not incompatible with neoliberalism, indeed the EBRD was a neoliberal-inspired creation. Still, most MDBs were bound up with postcolonial developmentalism and, as this slowed, so too did the creation of new banks.

4.2 The Post-Washington Consensus era: 1998–2009

The post-Washington Consensus era began following the Asian Financial Crisis and it saw a large shift in the global aid agenda with a big push for debt forgiveness and poverty reduction resulting in increasing the concessional resources available to developing countries and developing country ownership of development pathways through the Aid Effectiveness Agenda. Politically, the shift built on the rise of large progressive social movements and centre left parties like those of Bill Clinton in the US (1993–2001) and Tony Blair in the UK (1997–2007), whose minimally progressive agendas were friendly to globalisation (Mawdsley et al. 2018). Large social movements included the anti-globalisation movement peaking in the Battle for Seattle in 1999, the landmark protests in Cochabamba, Bolivia against privatised water price hikes in 2000, and the Make Poverty History coalition. Economically, the growth of China and relative stability globally meant many developing regions started to emerge from the austerity-induced recessions of the 1980s and early 1990s. It is a mistake, however, to think that there were no crashes: Brazil in 1999, the dotcom bubble burst of 2000, and Argentina in 2001 were three of the largest and the pre-conditions for the next regional debt crisis began with the build-up of private sector debt in the US and Europe, leading to the GFC.

Ideationally, the MDBs drew mostly on the New Institutional Economics (NIE) strand of mainstream economics. NIE was an attempt to build on neoclassical economics by incorporating a theory of institutions (North 1998). By significantly expanding neoclassical analysis of market failures to include information failures and transaction costs, NIE produced a picture of markets as subject to extensive imperfections, in contrast to the neoliberal idea of perfectly functioning markets (Fine 2001, 2005). As Greenwald and Stiglitz (1986) outlined, this means that government intervention could be efficient in many more cases than neoliberal doctrine allowed. Stiglitz was World Bank Chief Economist from 1997 to 2002 but was fired for his somewhat unorthodox views, though his influence lived on. His review of neoliberal ‘big bang’ capital market liberalisation concluded that if attention was not given to the order and timing of reform, programmes can cause more harm than good (Broad 2004, Stiglitz 2002).

Beyond NIE, the Developmental State and Neostructuralist literature were important parts of the broader context of development thinking, drawing a critical eye on the failings of the Washington Consensus. The Developmental State literature, analysing the rapid post-war development of Japan, South Korea, Taiwan, Singapore, and Hong Kong, emerged in the early 1980s and had some impact on the post-Washington Consensus. This literature highlights that active states utilising macroeconomic and industrial policies, run by a developmental elite shielded to a degree from political competition, had been able to achieve high levels of industrial transformation and economic growth (Amsden 1989, Thurbon 2016, Wade 2018). One of the most successful development states, Japan, sought to have the World Bank acknowledge the role of the state and industrial policy in development, funding a Bank report titled The East Asian Miracle (1993) to recognise this. In the editing of the report, however, the role of the state was watered down to the point that the neoliberal development paradigm emerged unscathed (Wade 1996). Developmental States certainly influenced the AsDB. Neostructuralism in Latin America similarly aimed to challenge neoliberal dogma but still cast market forces as the primary driver of development, adding that without attention to policy and institutional interventions focussed on equity, markets would not flourish (Leiva 2008). Like the Development State literature, Neostructuralism created space for thinking about the role of the state in development, an important contributor to the unfolding post-Washington Consensus.

Despite these new approaches, the practice of the post-Washington Consensus generally extended the neoliberal approach to constraining the state in both monetary and fiscal policy and through devolution of power to statutory bodies like central banks (Carroll 2010, Engel 2010, Wade 2001,). Regulation and other mechanisms were utilised to create more space for private markets, not states. Curbing state – but not private sector – corruption became a major focus, which was linked to the existing good governance agenda, thus many MDB projects targeted ‘reform’ of government financial and auditing systems. In later years, the focus was on deepening marketisation through tendering out of activities once performed by the state in everything from infrastructure to healthcare, education, and welfare.

Still, the post-Washington Consensus had a stronger focus on absolute poverty reduction than its predecessor and some focus on the social costs of adjustment. It offered a more progressive approach to health and education investments by state and markets, though in practice did little to support these. The World Bank and other MDBs claimed to have abandoned one-size-fits-all approaches to development and created tailored country programmes, found in country programming documents. These frameworks were meant to be based on recipient government ideas as local ownership was a key element of the post-Washington Consensus.

The focus on poverty and local ownership was formalised in two international agreements that became a key part of the 2000s aid consensus. The first was the MDGs and the second the Aid Effectiveness Agenda. Both came out of the OECD DAC and, despite some progressive overtones, they represented the Global North shaping the global justice agenda. The OECD DAC started work in the area in 1995, but the work was initially done by a group of all male, rich country development politicians and bureaucrats whose focus was on practical issues of projects and policies, hence the use of results-based management with target-setting (Hulme 2009). Through years of politicking, a series of international development goals, as the DAC called them, evolved into the eight MDGs comprised of numerous targets and indicators approved by the UN Millennium Assembly held in 2000. The MDGs became a unifying framework for the MDBs and former World Bank President James Wolfensohn referred to them in 2002 as ‘the hymnbook that we’re singing from now’ (cited in Bissio 2003, 157). Yet, as Saith (2006) argued, the MDGs were embedded in profoundly inegalitarian neoliberal relations and they sought not to change these, but only address the issue of absolute poverty. This is clear from the fact that the first MDG was to reduce the proportion of people living below the international poverty line of $1 a day, an accounting illusion that did not actually provide enough to allow people an average life expectancy (Hickel 2016).

The Aid Effectiveness Agenda emerged from the DAC, along with key statements made at High Level Forums in Rome (2003), Paris (2005), Accra (2008), and Busan (2011). The Agenda was a practical plan focussed on improving the quality and impact of aid policy and programmes and focussed on the practices of both donors and recipients. Ultimately a technocratic schedule devised by the Global North-led DAC (Booth 2008), the OECD (2011) itself acknowledged that donors did not progress the agenda as much as recipients. Nonetheless, all the larger MDBs and several smaller ones participated in Aid Effectiveness programmes, 13 out of the then 28 MDBs aligning behind institutional standards of behaviour. Notably, a few of the Arab-led MDBs were involved in these programmes but none of the smaller African SRDBs and only one of the Latin American SRDBs, the CDB.

4.2.1 Key developments at the World Bank

Clinton-appointed President James Wolfensohn oversaw the World Bank’s transition to the post-Washington Consensus and expanded the poverty-reduction mission (see Table 4.2). Under Wolfensohn, the phrase ‘Our dream is a world free of poverty’ was grandiosely carved into the entrance of the Bank’s refurbished headquarters in 1996 (Marshall 2008, 54). The Bank retained poverty reduction as its overarching mission since, even during the presidencies of conservative US Republican Party appointees Paul Wolfowitz and Robert Zoellick. Still, as Cammack (2004, 197) argued, Wolfensohn’s Bank promoted the ‘sustainable reproduction of capitalism’ by ensuring micro-level incentive structures were in line with neoliberal macroeconomic ones. Wolfensohn further attempted to maintain the Bank’s hegemony by shaping developmental thought through programmes like the Knowledge Bank initiative in 1996, designed to make the Bank the leading provider of development expertise, and the World Bank ‘Doing Business’ series starting in 2004, which reported on the ease of doing business in states across the globe and has been very influential (Banerjee et al. 2006). He also renamed structural adjustment loans as development policy loans in 2004 to distance the Bank from the most ideological aspects of the Washington Consensus (Bazbauers 2018). The Bank also helped launch the Heavily Indebted Poor Countries (HIPC) initiative for debt relief in 1996, although debts to the Bank were exempt until the 2005 Multilateral Debt Relief Initiative, to protect its preferred creditor status and credit rating. Despite progress, the conditions on debt relief advocated neoliberal prescriptions like limiting public expenditure and prioritising debt servicing over other needs.

World Bank lending spiked in 1998 and 1999 in response to the Asian Financial Crisis from an annual average of $22.03 billion in 1990–5 to $27.8 billion but rapidly declined to $15.3 billion in 2000. Yet, MDBs need to lend, so they steadily grew again to reach $24.7 billion in 2008, with the GFC then causing a further spike in loans. The relative stability of the 1999–2007 interregnum was not great for the IMF or Bank as their customers were reducing debt or able to borrow with few conditions and at competitive rates from other provides. Indeed, many countries were building foreign reserves explicitly to avoid having to turn to the IMF in the future. Still, the Bank remained vitally important to many smaller and poorer countries whose access to private finance was limited.

Co-financing expanded World Bank lending. This was mostly with official bilateral and multilateral partners. Between 1996 and 1999, co-financing ranged between 33.9% and 40.1% of the value of bank loans. As Bracking (2009) argued, these linkages highlight that there is not just an MDB system, but rather a system of interlinked development finance institutions. Still, an indication that MDF and the MDBs declined in influence over the 2000s was that by 2007 Bank co-financing was equal to just 25.5% of operations. Bank lending to the financial sector increased during this period through all three of its lending arms, particularly the IFC. Leading up to the GFC, the Bank was quite exposed to asset- and mortgage-backed securities, though the IADB was far more exposed (Kellerman 2019).

Table 4.2 World Bank Presidents 1995–2007

Name and term | Background | Legacy
James Wolfensohn 1995–2005 | Born in Australia, acquired US citizenship specifically to gain the World Bank presidency, attended University of Sydney and Harvard Business School, investment banker with interest in arts and music, known as the ‘Renaissance Banker.’ | Launched the HIPC in 1996 along with the IMF Managing Director. He focused on corruption before the Asian Financial Crisis and more so after with institutional mechanisms established in 1999. This crisis highlighted the Bank’s lack of inclusion, participation, and the shallow nature of its poverty reduction agenda, and they became key parts of the post-Washington Consensus along with influences from NIE. The 1997 Strategic Compact reform was designed to gain more resources for Bank in return for a streamlined institution. Launched the Comprehensive Development Framework and PRSPs in 1999 as frameworks for country lending and later as mechanisms for implementing the MDGs.
Paul Wolfowtiz 2005–7 | Born in US, attended Cornell University, obtained PhD from University of Chicago, held a number of government appointments for Republican administrations. | Wolfowitz was a political appointee from the Bush administration, which did not support the Bank. Had a tumultuous relationship with the Bank Board. Focused on anti-corruption but forced to resign after giving his partner a position with a high salary.

Source: Compiled by authors from a range of sources, basic details from World Bank website (2019).

4.2.2 Key developments in other MDBs

The AsDB took an active response to the Asian Financial Crisis, but some of its IMF-style policies led to backlash. It adopted poverty reduction as its mission in 1999, predating the World Bank. It was partly the result of pressure from the US Treasury, which forced the Asian MDB to put a much greater share of its funds into social and environmental projects than it had in the past (Babb 2009). The AsDB and most of the RDBs adopted and expanded safeguard mechanisms to protect project affected people from harm, which has helped ensure loans benefit local communities, though many problem projects are still funded. The RDBs increased inter-agency harmonisation too and engaged with new financial instruments following the World Bank’s lead.

The post-Washington Consensus era was a solid period for many of the sub-regional and specialised development banks. The smaller MDBs that would become influential during the 2010s began their expansion circa 2000, the CDB and CAF being two examples of this change in fortune, following organisational restructurings implemented during the 1990s. The focus on the private sector expanded in many smaller MDBs, for example, the AFESD’s Board of Governors approved a revision of the MDB’s Articles of Agreement in 1997 to better support the Arab private sector (AFESD 1997).

In Europe, the CEB broadened its mandate during the post-Washington Consensus era, through the 1997 Strasbourg Summit that advocated the CEB incorporate ‘strengthening European social cohesion’ into its mandate and the 2005 Warsaw Summit that called for building a free, democratic, and more inclusive European society; such changes reflected the greater focus on good governance in the post-Washington Consensus period. The EIB became the EIB Group during this period with the incorporation of sibling institutions addressing private sector financing and partnerships, reflecting the expansion of the World Bank into the World Bank Group with the IFC and MIGA.

In Africa, the misfortunes of the EADB continued into the 2000s, not as the result of the economic decline of its members but due to severe mismanagement of finances, leading to several high-ranking officials, including Director General Godfrey Tumusiime, being expelled; it posted losses of millions of dollars. In contrast, BOAD increased its private sector financing, along with a few other smaller MDBs. BOAD originally lent to regional member states but, from 2002, it provided loans to the private sector for development projects of regional significance plus lines of credit to small and medium private enterprises. This can be interpreted as the MDBs following the lead of the World Bank towards more private sector financing products in line with the post-Washington Consensus approach of market-led development.

4.2.3 New MDBs

Just two new MDBs were established between 1998 and 2009 and there was one unsuccessful proposal. The first new MDB, a trade and development bank, was established in 1996 by the Economic Cooperation Organisation (ECO) regional grouping comprised of mainly central Asian states. The ECO Trade and Development Bank (ETDB) was founded by three of the ECO states – Iran, Pakistan, and Turkey with Azerbaijan, Afghanistan, and the Kyrgyz Republic joining later. The ETDB aims simply to expand intra-regional trade and increase economic development. The second new MDB, the Eurasian Development Bank (EDB), was created in 2006 as another post-communist MDB mandated to develop and strengthen market economies, although its member states – the Russian Federation, Kazakhstan, Belarus, Armenia, Tajikistan, and Kyrgyzstan – remain far from model market economies.

The unsuccessful proposal was for a Banco del Sur (or Bank of the South), the idea for which was first raised in 2005 between Venezuela and Brazil. It was an expression of Neostructuralism and an indicator of new activism in the Global South. Its proposers were concerned that the South was still depositing large amounts of resources in Global North financial institutions and they wanted to create a new regional financial architecture (Pérez 2009–10, Rosales 2013). Discussions occurred in 2006–7 between Venezuela and Argentina, and they were joined by Brazil and Ecuador. In 2009, an agreement to establish the MDB was signed with eight initial members. In responding to the demands of the different founding member countries, the functions proposed for the MDB were:

to finance development projects in key sectors of the economy, aimed at improving competitiveness, scientific-technological development, infrastructure, creation and provision of services, intraregional productive complementarity, and the maximization of value added to raw materials produced in the countries of the region.

(cited in Rosales 2013, 31)

Its proposed structure seems rather like a standard MDB: a proposed initial capitalisation of $20 billion, capital raised on bond markets, and weighted voting for large projects and structures matters but one country, one vote for simple operational matters. Its constituent agreement entered into force in 2011 but adequate capital was not paid-in to make it operational. Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro attempted to revise it in April 2015, but it was not capitalised (Mares and Trinkunas 2016). The proposed Banco del Sur was a clear manifestation of Latin American Neostructuralism, and thus part of the broader post-Washington Consensus discourse. It also reopened discussion about the need for public development financing, which the NDB and AIIB continued in the 2010s.

4.3 Retroliberalism and the rise of debt: 2010–20

The progressive changes of the post-Washington Consensus era had come and largely gone by the early 2010s, with the focus turning to the retroliberal – or beyond aid – agenda. The quantity of resources delivered as opposed to the quality of aid effectiveness came to define MDB cooperation documents. The retroliberal agenda first emerged in the early 2000s and began as a slow political reconfiguration away from grant aid. As early as 2002, the International Conference on the Financing of Development in Monterrey made it clear that poor countries were responsible for their own development and that the private sector was expected to be the key course of finance going forward (Saith 2006). And, yet the retroliberal era did not fully emerge until around 2010, catalysed by the upheaval of the GFC.

Ideationally, it was hoped that the 2007–8 GFC would contribute to a broadening of development discourse. And, for a moment in the wake of the crisis, there was a brief flirtation with unorthodox policies, in particular Keynesian stimulus spending and financial controls in order to bail out capitalists but this was followed by a rapid return to austerity politics (Ortiz et al. 2020). The minor changes to regulations such as reforms to the Basel banking rules did not address the systemic risk that had been created by the liberalisation of financial flows, and financialisation revived after the crisis (Gabor 2020, Goldin et al. 2014). Mainstream donors and the MDBs maintained a broadly post-Washington Consensus mindset, but now with an increase emphasis on infrastructure, nationalism, and financialisation – promoting private investment and loans over grant aid. Thus, following Murray and Overton (2016), we label the period from 2010 to 2020 as the retroliberal era.

The term retroliberalism underscores that the policy response to the GFC benefited capital by socialising its losses and leaving labour income to pay for this through public debt. The practice of neoliberalism has always differed from the theory, with centre left and right governments adapting to serve business interests. In the current era, this means a return to a more state-centric and nationalist discourse focussing on the benefits that development aid and finance can provide to private and state firms rather than to poverty reduction. Retroliberalism has also marginalised the SDGs; they may get lip service, but they are no longer at the centre of development thinking. Significantly, the dramatic rise of China and its development strategy has put infrastructure again at the centre of development finance, a resurgence that broadly aligns with the modernisation mentality the World Bank pursued over its first two decades.

China’s approach to rapid industrialisation differs radically from the minimalist state agenda of the Washington Consensus and China’s influence on development has grown – by 2019, they were the third largest World Bank shareholder and were central to the formation of the NDB and AIIB. This has led scholars like Jakupec and Kelly (2019) and Lin and Wang (2017) to argue that China has created space for the Global South to adopt developmentalist approaches. However, like Yağcı (2016, 43), we argue that while China’s experience may be informative for debates about developmentalism, China itself is not concerned with ‘enlarging space for developing countries’ trade relations and industrialisation efforts.’ Rather, the contemporary inegalitarian capital order provides the foundations for China’s development, which they support along with the associated global economic governance system (Bond 2015, Robinson 2015).

The expansion of China’s mutual aid activities since 2008, notably the Belt and Road Initiative of 2013, was largely in response to domestic stagnation. Its aid promotes retroliberal policies – supporting open markets and broadly neoliberal fiscal and monetary policy, but with increased investment in infrastructure and less interference in state affairs including around human rights. Further, China’s policies support their investors, whether they are seeking to source raw materials, outsource elements of low-wage manufacturing, or gain construction contracts outside China using Chinese inputs and labour. Indeed, it is not unwarranted to say that they are often ‘kicking away the ladder for developing countries’ (Chang 2002). A key issue here is China’s extensive use of debt instruments, which previously had been very cautious about. During the 2010s, however, China’s approach became a retroliberal one – largely neoliberal policies with a good dash of infrastructure spending, all wrapped up in debt.

China’s expansion of debt relations has led the MDBs to expand their loan portfolios and the Global North to expand existing, and create new, bilateral development finance mechanisms, such as the US International Development Finance Corporation or Australia’s Infrastructure Financing Facility for the Pacific. Private sector debt has rapidly grown too over the past decade, and in 2018 global debt reached a record high of 230% of GDP. Since 2010, debt in EMDEs ‘has risen 54 percentage points of GDP to a historic peak of about 170% of GDP in 2018’ (Kose et al. 2020, xix). China itself has also rapidly expanded debt, but they have the advantage of most of their being owed to domestic sources.

Key contributors to the 2010s debt wave are the usual culprits of low interest rates and financialisation, as well as ‘a rise of regional banks, growing appetite for local currency bonds, and increased demand for EMDE debt from the expanding non-bank financial sector’ (Kose et al. 2020, xxi). The expansion in EMDE debt between 2010 and 2014 was predominantly private sector debt, but from 2014 to 2018 that reversed with publicly guaranteed debt making up the majority. In low-income countries, both public and private debt has grown and there has been a shift away from concessional finance and towards private creditors, although smaller sub-Saharan African states are still primarily reliant on official creditors (Bonizzi, Laskaridis, and Toporowski 2019). According to Kose et al. (2020, 10), this ‘wave of debt buildup has been unprecedented in its size, speed, and reach’ in EMDEs. It is also more global than previous debt build-up waves occurring since the 1970s, though debt in the Global North has been stable and there have been declines in debt in the Middle East, Eastern Europe, and Central Asia.

4.3.1 Key developments at the World Bank

World Bank President Jim Yong Kim, who led the MDB from 2012 to 2019, with his public health background, seemed to offer a progressive approach to development (see Table 4.3). By the time Kim left the Bank, however, the MDB had doubled down on financialisation. At the same time, networks between the MDBs and DFIs continued to grow. The International Development Finance Club was established by the IMF and Bank in 2011 to help DFIs set agendas on development finance and share know-how. It has six SRDBs and the IsDB as members of its private sector arm, along with Global North and South national development banks and one Exim bank.

Table 4.3 World Bank Presidents 2007–20

Name and term | Background | Legacy
Robert B. Zoellick 2007–12 | Born in US, attended Swarthmore College and Harvard, spent three decades between private sector firms (including Goldman Sachs) and government appointments in Republican administrations, including Deputy Secretary of State (2005–6). | World Bank President during the 2007–8 GFC, when lending increased to an all-time high. He oversaw the first general capital increase for IBRD in 20 years agreed to in 2010. Involved in an increase in shares for developing and transition countries and agreed to review their position every 5 years. Commissioned Zedillo Report released in 2009 on the World Bank Group’s governance structures. Zoellick’s presidency focused on good governance and anti-corruption and launched the World Bank’s ‘open data’ initiative.
Jim Yong Kim 2012–19 | Born in South Korea, migrated to the US with family at age 5, attended Brown University, obtained MD and PhD from Harvard University, co-founded public health NGO, served as a director in WHO, and worked as university lecturer and administrator. | Kim initiated another major and controversial reorganisation, some of it reversed in 2017. Originally focused on health and human development and approved Framework for Mainstreaming Citizen Engagement. Shifted to focus on financialisation through the Maximising Finance for Development initiative, which was linked to a large capital increase agreed to in 2018 and expanded the role of the IFC. This promoted privatised social services. Kim also set stronger targets for climate finance, ended financing for oil and gas exploration and extraction, and strengthened rules on lending to private banks with fossil fuel investments.
David R. Malpass 2019– | Born in US, attended Colorado College and University of Denver, Georgetown University economist, chief economist of Bear Stearns, held government appointments in Republican administrations. | Warned about the build-up of debt in EMDEs, including debt from IFIs. President during the COVID-19 pandemic, which to mid-2020 involved a $160 billion commitment, with strong emphasis on the IFC.

Source: Compiled by authors from a range of sources, basic details from World Bank website (2019).

World Bank commitments reached an all-time high in 2010 of $58.7 billion, and then dropped substantially to $29 billion in 2012. Yet, this lending interregnum was short. As the investment climate deteriorated mid-decade, states increased public spending, and President Kim announced his ‘billions to trillions’ agenda in 2013 that aimed to leverage Bank lending to shift from billions of dollars in investments to trillions. Between 2017 and 2019, average annual Bank commitments were $44.8 billion and IBRD gross disbursements were $18.5 billion and IDA gross disbursements totalled $14.9 billion (World Bank 2019).

The ‘billions to trillions’ agenda was followed by Maximising Finance for Development (MFD) in 2017, which sought to leverage official development finance to attract private investment but with a focus on ‘innovative’ financial instruments. The World Bank’s 2018 large shareholding increase (detailed in Chapter 5) was core to this, though it was also likely partly driven by competition with the new MDBs and Chinese development finance. The increase substantially expanded Bank Group lending capacity and is linked to the IDA raising funds on money markets for the first time in its history. With the Trump regime in power in the US, it seems that the shareholder increase came at the price of Kim’s resignation.

The MFD initiatives shows that, despite the havoc wreaked by financialisation in the GFC, the World Bank has become a proponent of it being extended to aid and development finance; the ‘overall strategy is to policy-engineer a shift towards securities-based financial systems and thus render DECs [developing and emerging countries] more amenable to the forces of financialised capitalism’ (Gabor 2018, 16). While the overall strategy is clear, the precise methods for implementation are less so. One method is issuing new kinds of bonds, such as green bonds, IDA bonds, the world’s first blockchain bond, and Indonesian women’s empowerment bonds (World Bank 2019). A second method is the ‘cascade approach’ that identifies imperfections that may be stopping private capital from investing in projects. If addressing the imperfection is not enough, subsidies and guarantees may be needed to leverage private investment and only when such reforms are still not attracting private investment can public investment be considered (Gabor 2018). It thus combines an ideological preference for private investment over public regardless of profitability or efficiency, with a preference for financialised capitalism over traditional banking. For example, the Bank issued catastrophe bonds in 2016 through the Pandemic Emergency Financing Facility (PEFF), a mechanism pioneered by insurance companies to pay high interest rates on the basis that investors may lose some of or all their money. The Bank’s PEFF bond had a complex set of triggers before they could be paid out, leading to an expectation that they would not be. But, the COVID-19 crisis met all the triggers and so investors lost their principal (Mackenzie 2020). The Bank created PEFF bonds to build a new market in securitised risk but given most investors are loss adverse, they will be less likely to purchase them again in the future (Mackenzie 2020). More to the point, such innovative financial instruments may have a strong structure, ‘but from almost any angle, they look fundamentally ill-suited to protecting vulnerable people from diseases, disaster, or climate change’ (Mackenzie 2020).

With Trump appointee David Malpass as the incumbent president (see Table 4.3), the Bank became more concerned with the growth of debt, which the IMF had been warning about for a few years. Yet, the COVID-19 pandemic has left no option but for a big increase in lending as bilateral donors are not increasing grant resources. The Bank has said they will provide $160 billion in frontloaded funds to help states respond to the crisis and other MDBs will private $80 billion. They are also frontloading grants through their COVID-19 Fast Track Facility, but more loans will follow.

In 2020, the Bank Group’s ambitious mission was to end extreme poverty by decreasing the percentage of people living on less than $1.90 a day to no more than 3% by 2030 and to promote shared prosperity by fostering the income growth of the bottom 40% of people in every country. But, just like the MDGs, this formulation is an accounting illusion that narrowly focusses on inequality by promoting income growth. This brings us back to the centrality of the Bank’s original purposes, which can be summarised as facilitating investment in productive purposes and promoting private investment and trade.

4.3.2 Key developments in other MDBs

The late 2000s and 2010s saw an across-the-board improvement in the organisational functioning and loan portfolios of the regional, sub-regional, and specialised development banks, particularly among a few smaller MDBs that had struggled during the 1980s and 1990s. Such improvements coincided with organisational restructurings, an expansion of capital availability, and new leadership. In the case of the RDBs, however, most of which had also lent counter-cyclically during the 2007–8 GFC, they had a larger decline in lending in the early 2010s than the World Bank, which has been attributed to downward pressure from credit rating agencies (Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli 2018).

In the case of the SRDBs, successful reform occurred across several continents. In Africa, the EADB went from severe financial mismanagement during the 2000s to significant organisational restructuring and the recovery of outstanding loans under Director General Vivienne Yeda, who was appointed in 2009. As a result, Yeda received several financial and banking awards, including the African Banker of the Year Award in 2014. At the TDB, President Adamassu Tadesse, who received the same African Banker Award in 2019, spearheaded a dramatic reformation of the African SRDB, including growing equity capital and annual profits four-fold between 2012 and 2019, attracting 15 new shareholders, and receiving the TDB’s first investment grade rating from Moody’s in 2017 (Africa Fintech Summit 2019). The TDB’s reform process began in 2000 and the overall result is that it is now substantially larger than the four African SRDBs that were created before it (Humphrey 2019). In Latin America, CAF came to rival the IADB and exceed World Bank Latin American and Caribbean commitments during the 2010s, which is indicative of the change in fortunes and expansion of operations of so many MDBs (Humphrey 2014, 2016).

In Europe, the NDF, after almost being dissolved in the 2000s, instituted a series of institutional reforms in 2009, shifting its mandate from soft loans for social and economic development to grants for climate change interventions in low-income countries (Amland 2018, Normann 2019). This was an attempt to not only satisfy the competing interests of its Nordic shareholders but also to better find its niche within MDF (Wihtol 2013). The CEB, its relevance revitalised in the 1990s with the collapse of the Soviet Union and reintegration of people from the former Soviet bloc into capitalist Europe, renewed its pertinence once again in response to the refugee crisis affecting Europe since the mid-2010s.

In Eastern Europe and Central Asia, the IIB underwent considerable restructuring in 2012. Following two decades of stagnation in the wake of the Soviet Union’s collapse, new management entered the former Soviet-led MDB to make it a modern-day development bank. A revised agreement in 2014 saw it shift to a much more capitalist agenda of ‘promoting economic growth, increasing the competitiveness of national economies, expanding trade and economic ties, and maximising investment interaction opportunities’ (IIB 2018, 1). The IIB also entered debt capital markets in 2014, the first time in its history, and began issuing bonds in Russia, Slovakia, and Romania.

In a range of ways, the 2010s saw a closer alignment between the MDBs as to what a development bank ‘should’ look like. In addition to broad harmonisation efforts, another example is the increasingly close alignment on climate finance following the 2015 Paris Agreement (see Chapter 10) and further many MDBs followed the World Bank’s lead in increasing their financial innovation engagement.

4.3.3 New MDBs

Two new MDBs emerged during the retroliberal era, the NDB and AIIB, and they were designed as traditional development banks. The NDB (2015, 1) adopts neutral language in its purposes, aiming to ‘mobilize resources for infrastructure and sustainable development projects in BRICS and other emerging economies and developing countries,’ and the AIIB (2015, 2), largely duplicating the AsDB’s Charter, has a strong profit focus prioritising ‘infrastructure and other productive sectors,’ despite being founded by an ostensibly socialist state. The absence of references to poverty reduction in the NDB and AIIB’s founding documents speaks to them being business-link banks, at odds with the SDGs; the new MDBs conform to the ‘GDP-centred, Northern-development-model approach’ (Dossani 2014).

Promoting private capital is remarkably prominent in the AIIB’s Articles of Agreement, giving the MDB responsibility for its promotion in the region. The Articles suggest that, as argued above, the practice of this China-led development financier is not much friendly to the state than the old traditional MDBs. The NDB is a little more conspicuous in its purposes, referring to ‘support’ for public and private projects. The similarities of purposes and inclusion of facilitating private investment demonstrates that the new MDBs aim to promote debt-based, capitalist expansion in the same way as the old ones have.

4.4 Conclusion

There are so many dimensions to the MDBs discussed in Chapters 3 and 4 that it is hard to offer simple conclusions. The chapters highlight the connections between MDB creation, geopolitics, economic theory, and debt. They demonstrate that there is a fair degree of coherence around the aims and objectives of the MDBs; almost all exhibit a Keynesian influence, which is not surprising given their logic is the Keynesian idea that markets will not always ensure adequate levels of investment. Some are more statist, others more pragmatic, and the EBRD brought in a neoliberal tone, but, in the end, they are all focussed on promoting market-based economic growth in line with banking principles. There is a remarkable consensus around the need for more and more debt to promote economic growth, despite there still being no orderly default and restructuring mechanism for states at the international level.

Many of the MDBs started out with strong regional missions but few have been able to live up to them in practice; not many governments want to be burdened by joint loans that they may not get an equal share of benefits from. This demonstrates the dominance of the state in development discourse and it permeates the analysis and lending strategies of the MDBs too. The MDBs have helped naturalise the idea that states are actual and effective units that can control development challenges at the same time as their banking and neoliberal logics lead them to want to constrain the state and promote the benefits of markets. This is the tension at the heart of the MDBs.

The durability of the MDB model and the MDBs themselves are further factors that leap out of the analysis – ‘once established MDBs do not disappear, but rather transform and evolve’ (Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli 2018, 21). The BDEGL is the only suspended MDB we have found and even it still exists on paper. Still, as the chapter demonstrates, many MDBs have faced challenges. Nonetheless, they are substantial financial actors. The 23 MDBs studied by Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli (2018, 49) had a total portfolio (loans, equity investments, and debt securities) of $1.13 trillion in 2016 or 1.6% of world GDP, which was a decline from earlier in the decade. In addition, states have turned to the idea of creating new MDBs time and again when faced with obstacles, which suggests they consider productive investment of the trillions of dollars that now float around the world is an ongoing challenge. States seem to like the influence that MDBs provide and, as Chapter 5 shows, once established MDBs are quite cheap for them. The next chapter focusses on the structure of the MDBs and it emphasises how their structure as banks has been a long-underestimated influence. Indeed, Kapur, Lewis, and Webb (1997, 1111) note that at times the World Bank’s ‘financial and development personas’ have been ‘more competitive than complementary.’

Bibliography

AFESD. 1997. Annual Report 1997. Safat, Kuwait: Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development.

Africa Fintech Summit. 2019. “5 Questions with Admassu Tadesse, President & Chief Executive of Trade and Development Bank (TDB).” https://africafintechsummit.com/2019/11/19/5-questions-with-admassu-tadesse-president-chief-executive-of-trade-and-development-bank-tdb/.

AIIB. 2015. Articles of Agreement. Beijing: Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank.

Amland, Bjørn H. 2018. “Nordic Donors to Discuss Strengthening Nordic Development Fund.” Development Today. http://www.development-today.com/magazine/Frontpage/nordic_donors_to_discuss_strengthening_nordic_development_fund.

Amsden, Alice. 1989. Asia’s Next Giant: South Korea and Late Industrialisation. New York: Oxford University Press.

Babb, Sarah. 2009. Behind the Development Banks: Washington Politics, World Poverty, and the Wealth of Nations. Chicago, IL and London: The University of Chicago Press.

Banerjee, Abhijit, Angus Deaton, Nora Lustig, Ken Rogoff, and Edward Hsu. 2006. An Evaluation of World Bank Research, 1998–2005. September 24. Washington, DC: World Bank.

Bazbauers, Adrian Robert. 2018. The World Bank and Transferring Development: Policy Movement through Technical Assistance. Cham: Palgrave Macmillan.

Bello, Walden. 1994. Dark Victory: The United States, Structural Adjustment, and Global Poverty. London: Pluto.

Bissio, Roberto. 2003. “Civil Society and the MDGs.” Development Policy Journal 3 (April):151–60.

Bond, Patrick. 2015. “BRICS and the Sub-imperial Location.” In BRICS: An Anti-Capitalist Critique, edited by Ana Garcia and Patrick Bond, 15–26. Chicago, IL: Haymarket Books.

Bonizzi, Bruno, Christina Laskaridis, and Jan Toporowski. 2019. “Global Liquidity, the Private Sector and Debt Sustainability in Sub-Saharan Africa.” Development and Change 50 (5):1430–54. doi: 10.1111/dech.12507.

Booth, David. 2008. Aid Effectiveness after Accra: How to Reform the ‘Paris agenda’. London: ODI.

Bracking, Sarah. 2009. Money and Power: Great Predators in the Political Economy of Development. London: Pluto Press.

Broad, Robin. 2004. “The Washington Consensus Meets the Global Backlash: Shifting Debates and Policies.” Globalizations 1 (2):129–54.

BSTDB. 2019. Medium-Term Strategy and Business Plan 2019–2022. Black Sea Trade and Development Bank. Accessed 1 June 2020. https://www.bstdb.org/MTSBP_2019-2022.pdf

Cahill, Damien. 2014. The End of Laissez-Faire? On the Durability of Embedded Neoliberalism. Cheltenham: Edward Elgar.

Cammack, Paul. 2004. “What the World Bank Means by Poverty Reduction and Why it Matters.” New Political Economy 9 (2):189–211.

Carroll, Toby. 2010. Delusions of Development: The World Bank and the Post-Washington Consensus in Southeast Asia. Houndmills, Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan.

Cevallos, Ricardo. 1996. “The Central American Bank for Economic Integration.” Tulane Journal of International and Comparative Law 4 (2):245–74.

Chang, Ha-Joon. 2002. Kicking Away the Ladder: Development Strategy in Historical Perspective. London: Anthem Press.

Chossudovsky, Michel. 1997. The Globalisation of Poverty: Impacts of IMF and World Bank Reforms. London: Zed Books.

Delikanli, Ihsan Ugur, Todor Dimitrov, and Roena Agolli. 2018. Multilateral Development Banks: Governance and Finance. Cham: Palgrave Macmillan.

Dossani, Sameer. 2014. BRICS Bank: New Bottle, How’s the Wine? Bretton Woods Bulletin (Februrary).

EBRD. 2013. Basic Documents of the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development. London: European Bank for Reconstruction and Development. Accessed 11 March 2020. https://www.ebrd.com/news/publications/institutional-documents/basic-documents-of-the-ebrd.html

Engel, Susan. 2010. The World Bank and the Post-Washington Consensus in Vietnam and Indonesia: Inheritance of Loss. London: Routledge.

Engel, Susan, and Adrian Robert Bazbauers. 2020. “Multilateral Development Banks: Washington Consensus, Beijing Consensus or Banking Consensus?” In Rethinking Multilateralism in Foreign Aid: Beyond the Neoliberal Hegemony, edited by Viktor Jakupc, Max Kelly and Jonathan Makuwira, 113–31. Abingdon, Oxon and New York: Routledge.

Fine, Ben. 2001. Social Capital versus Social Theory: Political Economy and Social Science at the Turn of the Millennium. London: Routledge.

Fine, Ben. 2005. “The New Development Economics.” In The New Development Economics: After the Washington Consensus, edited by K.S. Jomo and Ben Fine, 1–20. New Delhi: Tulika Books.

Gabor, Daniela. 2018. Understanding the Financialisation of International Development through 11 FAQs. Washington, DC: Heinrich Böll Stiftung North America.

Gabor, Daniela. 2020. The Wall Street Consensus. SocArXiv papers.

George, Susan, and Fabrizio Sabelli. 1994. Faith and Credit: The World Bank’s Secular Empire. London: Penguin Books.

Goldin, Ian, Mike Mariathasan, Co-Pierre Georg, and Tiffany Vogel. 2014. “The Financial Sectors.” In The Butterfly Defect: How Globalization Creates Systemic Risk, and What To Do about it, edited by Ian Goldin and Mike Mariathasan, 36–69. Princeton, NJ and Oxford: Princeton University Press.

Gowan, Peter. 1999. The Global Gamble: Washington’s Faustian Bid for World Dominance. London: Verso.

Greenwald, Bruce C., and Joesph Stiglitz. 1986. “Externalities in Economies with Imperfect Information and Incomplete Markets.” Quarterly Journal of Economics 90 (2):229–64.

Harvey, David. 2010. The Enigma of Capital: And the Crises of Capitalism. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

Hickel, Jason. 2016. “The True Extent of Global Poverty and Hunger: Questioning the Good News Narrative of the Millennium Development Goals.” Third World Quarterly 37 (5):749–67.

Hulme, David. 2009. The Millennium Development Goals (MDGs): A Short History of the World’s Biggest Promise. University of Manchester, Brooks World Poverty Institute. BWPI Working Paper 100, Manchester.

Humphrey, Chris. 2014. “The Politics of Loan Pricing in Multilateral Development Banks.” Review of International Political Economy 21 (3):611–39. doi: 10.1080/09692290.2013.858365.

Humphrey, Chris. 2016. “The Invisible Hand: Financial Pressures and Organisational Convergence in Multilateral Development Banks.” The Journal of Development Studies 52 (1):92–112. doi: 10.1080/00220388.2015.1075978.

Humphrey, Chris. 2019. “‘Minilateral’ Development Banks: What the Rise of Africa’s Trade and Development Bank Says about Multilateral Governance.” Development and Change 50 (1):164–90. doi: 10.1111/dech.12467.

IIB. 2018. Agreement Concerning the Establishment of an International Investment Bank. New York: United Nations – Treaty Series Volume 801, 1975. Accessed 11 March 2020. https://treaties.un.org/doc/Publication/UNTS/Volume%20801/v801.pdf.

Jakupec, Viktor, and Max Kelly. 2019. Foreign Aid in the Age of Populism: Political Economy Analysis from Washington to Beijing. London: Routledge.

Kapur, Devesh, John P. Lewis, and Richard Webb. 1997. The World Bank Its First Half Century, Volume 1: History. 2 vols. Vol. 1: History. Washington, DC: Brookings Institution Press.

Kellerman, Miles. 2019. “The Proliferation of Multilateral Development Banks.” Review of International Organization 14 (1):107–45. doi: 10.1007/s11558-018-9302-y.

Kose, M. Ayhan, Peter Nagle, Franziska Ohnsorge, and Naotaka Sugawara. 2020. Global Waves of Debt: Causes and Consequences. Washington, DC: World Bank.

Leiva, Fernando Ignacio. 2008. “Towards a Critique of Latin American Neostructuralism.” Latin American Politics and Society 50 (4):1–25.

Lin, Justin Yifu, and Yan Wang. 2017. Going Beyond Aid: Development Cooperation for Structural Transformation. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Mackenzie, Kate. 2020. Climate Change Is a Complex Problem, But Complex Financial Products Aren’t the Solution. New York: Bloomberg Wire Service.

Mak, James, and Seiji Finch Naya. 1994. “Is There a Need for a Pacific Islands Development Bank?” Pacific Economic Bulletin 9 (2):35–40.

Mares, David R., and Harold A. Trinkunas. 2016. Aspirational Power: Brazil on the Long Road to Global Influence. Washington, DC: Brookings Institution Press.

Marshall, Katherine. 2008. The World Bank: From Reconstruction to Development to Equity. Abingdon: Routledge.

Mawdsley, Emma, Warwick E. Murray, John Overton, Regina Scheyvens, and Glenn Banks. 2018. “Exporting Stimulus and “Shared Prosperity”: Reinventing Foreign Aid for a Retroliberal Era.” Development Policy Review 63 (S1):O25–43. doi: 10.1111/dpr.12282.

Mistry, Percy S., and Lolette Kritzinger-van Niekerk. 1998. Development Finance and the Need for a Sub-Regional Development Financing Institution in SADC. Southern African Development Community Finance & Investment Sector Coordinating Unit Research Project.

Murray, Warwick E., and John Overton. 2016. “Retroliberalism and the New Aid Regime of the 2010s.” Progress in Development Studies 16 (3):244–60. doi: 10.1177/1464993416641576.

NDB. 2015. Agreement on the New Development Bank. Shanghai: New Development Bank. Accessed 12 March 2020. https://www.ndb.int/data-and-documents/ndb-core-documents/

Normann, Henrik. 2019. Nordic Investment Bank – Henrik Normann – Answers to UNSW Survey 15.5.2019, edited by Adrian Robert Bazbauers: UNSW Canberra.

North, Douglass C. 1998. “The New Institutional Economics and Third World Development.” In The New Institutional Economics and Third World Development, edited by John Harriss, Janet Hunter and Colin M. Lewis, 17–26. London: Routledge. Original edition, 1995.

OECD. 2011. “Aid Effectiveness 2005–10: Progress in Implementing the Paris Declaration.” OECD Publishing. Accessed 15 January 2013. http://www.oecd.org/dac/aideffectiveness/48742718.pdf.

Ortiz, Isabel, Matthew Cummins, Jeronim Capaldo, and Kalaivani Karunanethy. 2020. The Decade of Adjustment: A Review of Austerity Trends 2010–2020 in 187 Countries. Geneva: International Labour Office.

Park, Susan. 2014. “Institutional Isomorphism and the Asian Development Bank’s Accountability Mechanism: Something Old, Something New, Something Borrowed, Something Blue?” The Pacific Review 27 (2):217–39.

Park, Susan. 2017. “Accountability as Justice for the Multilateral Development Banks? Borrower Opposition and Bank Avoidance to US Power and Influence.” Review of International Political Economy 24 (5):776–801. doi: 10.1080/09692290.2017.1363798.

Pérez, Pedro Páez. 2009–10. “The Ecuadorian Proposal for a New Regional Financial Architecture.” Journal of Post Keynesian Economic 32 (2):163–72.

Rich, Bruce. 1994. Mortgaging the Earth: The World Bank, Environmental Impoverishment, and the Crisis of Development. Boston, MA: Beacon Press.

Robinson, William. 2015. “The Transnational State and the BRICS: A Global Capitalism Perspective.” Third World Quarterly 36 (1):1–21.

Rosales, Antulio. 2013. “The Banco del Sur and the Return to Development.” Latin American Perspectives 40 (5):27–43.

Saith, Ashwani. 2006. “From Universal Values to Millennium Development Goals: Lost in Translation.” Development and Change 37 (6):1167–99.

Stiglitz, Joesph. 2000. “The Insider: What I Learned at the World Economic Crisis.” New Republic 222 (16/17):57–60.

Stiglitz, Joesph. 2002. Globalization and Its Discontents. London: Penguin Books.

Szasz, Paul C. 1999. “Establishment of the International Fund for Agricultural Development.” Studies in Transnational Legal Policy 31–32:32–43.

The New Times. 2009. CEPGL Mulls Reopening Bank. Accessed 1 June 2020. https://www.newtimes.co.rw/section/read/80411/

Thurbon, Elizabeth. 2016. Developmental Mindset: The Revival of Financial Activism in South Korea. Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press.

Toye, John. 1993. Dilemmas of Development, 2nd ed. Oxford: Blackwell Publishers.

Uhlin, Anders. 2016. “Civil Society and Policy Reforms in the Asian Development Bank.” In Global Economic Governance and the Practices of the Multilateral Development Banks, edited by Susan Park and Jonathan R. Strand, 60–79. London: Routledge.

Wade, Robert. 1996. “Japan, the World Bank, and the Art of Paradigm Maintenance: The East Asian Miracle in Political Perspective.” New Left Review 217:3–36.

Wade, Robert. 2001. “Showdown at the World Bank.” New Left Review 7:124–37.

Wade, Robert. 2018. “The Developmental State: Dead or Alive?” Development and Change 49 (2):518–46. doi: 10.1111/dech.12381.

Wihtol, Robert. 2013. “NDF and the Case for Niche Development Funds.” Development Today. http://www.development-today.com/magazine/2013/dt_14-15/opinion/ndf_and_the_case_for_niche_development_funds.

Williamson, John. 1990. “What Washington Means by Policy Reform.” In Latin American Readjustment: How Much Has Happened, edited by John Williamson, 7–20. Washington, DC: Peterson Institute for International Economics.

Willis, Katie. 2005. Theories and Practices of Development. New York: Routledge.

Woods, Ngaire. 2006. The Globalizers: The IMF, the World Bank, and Their Borrowers. Ithaca, NY and London: Cornell University Press.

World Bank. 1993. The East Asian Miracle: Economic Growth and Public Policy. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

World Bank. 2019. Annual Report 2019: Ending Poverty. Investing in Opportunity. Washington, DC: World Bank.

Yağcı, Mustafa. 2016. “A Beijing Consensus in the Making: The Rise of Chinese Initiatives in the International Political Economy and Implications for Developing Countries.” Perceptions XXI (2):29–56.

5 The structure of multilateral development banks

This chapter analyses the structure of the MDBs, positioning the World Bank as the archetype and exploring how the other MDBs are similar or different. The chapter starts with voting systems and capital subscriptions and how these have shaped Bank operations. Next, the Bank’s governance structure is outlined, analysing the relative influence of its Governors, Directors, and senior management. The chapter then turns to the Bank’s lending system – types of loans, conditionality, procurement, and interest rates. Table 5.2 systematically compares the Bank’s structures to those of other MDBs, highlighting organisational convergences and divergences.

5.1 The structure of the World Bank

The MDBs are all structured like private banks, following the model established by the IBRD. They have shareholders, predominantly states, contributing capital in return for shares and voting rights. An analysis of vote allocations, capitalisation, governance structures, and lending capacity may seem quite technical, but it is critical to understand the MDBs as organisations to comprehend their strengths and limitations and thus their role in development finance.

5.1.1 Voting rights

The negotiators at the 1944 Bretton Woods conference did not spend much time debating the IBRD’s organisational structure – Article V of the Bank’s establishing agreement is ‘nearly an exact copy of the [IMF’s] Articles XII and XIII’ (Mason and Asher 1973, 29). Article V outlines the Bank’s organisation and management, including its governance structure, system of voting rights, and location of offices. The voting rights were the ‘realist’ heart at the centre of post-war international economic organisation building at Bretton Woods. Closely following Harry Dexter White’s 1942 draft (Oliver 1971), IBRD voting rights were linked to the number of shares held – each member had 250 basic votes plus one additional vote for each share of stock held. The size of each country’s capital subscription was originally based on relative economy size and later subscriptions to IDA were added to encourage donations to the Bank’s concessional arm. Further, there is little incentive for developing countries to have large subscriptions because they are independent of borrowing rights; this is in contrast to the IMF, where subscriptions are linked to drawing rights (Mason and Asher 1973). This means that many borrowing members have little influence over the Bank, an issue identified as a severe democratic deficit in the MDB.

Basic votes are a compromise between equal representation and power-based voting, and some MDBs have more basic votes per member than others. In the IBRD’s case, capital increases were not matched by an expansion of basic votes, so their value has significantly declined (Leech and Leech 2006). Basic votes were later capped at a low 5.55% of total votes but generally have been below that. In some of the other MDBs, basic votes were set as a percentage of total votes from the outset. For example, basic votes are 20% of total votes in the AsDB, while they are 12% in the AIIB, with founding AIIB members getting an additional 600 votes giving them greater weight, though the value of these will decline as the capital stock increases. Several MDBs also have different formulas for regional and non-regional members, generally with the aim of increasing the power of developing regional member countries.

The largest shareholders in the IBRD – those countries that provide the main guarantee behind the Bank’s bond issues and loans on capital markets – were originally those from the Global North, namely the US and Western European countries. With the refusal of the Soviet Union to ratify the Bretton Woods agreement, the US had 35.07% of votes in 1946 and the US and European countries combined controlled 74% (Mason and Asher 1973, 800–02). Even with an influx of new members in the 1960s, the US and Europeans still held 61% in June 1971. Japan pushed to increase its shareholding in the early 1970s (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). After the creation of the IDA add-on in 1960, adjustments to Bank shareholding reflected not just the member’s economic weight but also contributions to the Bank’s concessional arm. In practice, however, political factors have always weighed in too.

China and other emerging economies began campaigns in the 1990s to gain more influence in the Bretton Woods institutions and other international organisations, to better reflect geopolitical changes. The Bank undertook what was described as major ‘voice’ reforms after a call from the UN International Conference on Financing for Development held in Monterrey in 2002. The revised quota framework was said to be 75% based on the size of state’s GDP, IDA contributions were given 20% weighting, and 5% weighting was given to country’s borrowings. The formulas were never formally published however, and countries did not have to agree to reductions, so the basis of decision-making remains unclear (Vestergaard 2010). Shareholding changes introduced in 2008 and 2010 produced only a 4.5% transfer from the Global North to developing and transition countries and much less for low-income countries (Vestergaard 2010)! By 2020, the top six shareholders in the IBRD were the US, whose 15.44% shareholding grants it veto power over certain key decisions, followed by Japan (7.75%), China (4.78%), Germany (4.08%), France (3.8%), and the UK (3.8%). Resolving over- and under-representation is difficult for the Bank and the rapid growth of emerging economies exacerbates this. Nevertheless, it can be said that: (i) high-income countries as a group remain over-represented; (ii) China is significantly under-represented, as is India; and (iii) low-income countries are over-represented relative to their GDP but still have just a tiny fraction of voting power (Vestergaard 2010).

The IBRD’s governing structure is made up of a Board of Governors, with representatives appointed from each member country, a Board of Directors, and a President nominally elected by the Executive Directors. Almost all MDBs follow this structure, or a close variant thereof, e.g., the EADB has a Director General in lieu of a President, although the role is analogous. Governors are generally appointed by ministries of finance, though sometimes by Treasury or state departments or central banks – they rarely come from national aid agencies. The World Bank’s Board of Governors is the supreme decision-making body, but its formal responsibilities are limited to admitting and suspending members, adjudicating appeals from the Directors on interpretations of the Bank’s Articles, and increasing and decreasing the capital stock. Most formal power including setting strategic directions and approving lending operations is vested in the Directors, but in practice the President and senior management have substantial control. Directors are elected for two-year terms and are paid by the Bank, not member governments. There were originally 12 Directors, but this grew to 24 in 1992 following an expansion of country membership, and in 2010 an additional Director for sub-Saharan Africa was added, bringing the total to 25. Larger boards can lead to better representation but can also complicate decision-making and coordination (Babb 2009).

The largest shareholders get to appoint Directors. For many decades, this meant the US, the UK, Germany, France, and Japan, but today also includes China. Other countries generally pool their votes in relatively stable constituencies, with directorships usually held by the largest constituency members. These elections do not precisely follow the IBRD’s Articles (Strand and Retzl 2016). Directors cast the number of votes that they control or have obtained at their election and voting for all IBRD decisions is 50% of votes cast, with a few key exceptions. The first is that capital increases require 75% of voting power, but the specification that members have the right to an equal subscription when there is a capital increase means that no country can have its shareholdings reduced without agreeing, so capital increases effectively require unanimous approval (Vestergaard 2010). Second, amending the Articles of Agreement requires three-fifths of members and 85% of voting power, increased from 80% in 1989, allowing the US to retain its veto. Finally, unanimous agreement is required to modify clauses on the right to withdraw from the IBRD, rights to subscribe to increases in the authorised capital stock, and limitations on liability.

Earlier Executive Director constituencies were sometimes based on historical or colonial relationships and there were often groups with a member from the Global North who dominated. Australia is an interesting example, as it formed a group in 1953 with the Union of South Africa, Vietnam joined in 1957, and New Zealand in 1965. By 1971, the group was without Vietnam. Then, in 2003, Australia was paired with New Zealand, Cambodia, the Republic of Korea, Mongolia, Palau, and seven Pacific Island nations. In 2020, the group was almost the same, except the seven Pacific states had expanded to ten and the group’s 3.45% voting power expanded to 3.99%. Contra the Australian example, most groups rarely change composition (Strand and Retzl 2016). The Russian Federation has a Director elected based on their shareholding, though Syria joined their constituency. Equally, Saudi Arabia is a single-member constituency. These two single-seat groups ‘mean that the remaining voting groups are larger than they otherwise would be, thus potentially reducing the formal voice of members represented by elected’ Directors (Strand and Retzl 2016, 420). Most other Directors are elected based on geographical groupings, though there are mixed constituencies, including the Philippines with several Latin American states and Switzerland with Eastern European and Central Asian states. Sub-Saharan Africa is represented by three groups, one with Angola, Nigeria, and South Africa and two others with over 20 states in each, which remain by far the largest groupings despite reforms enacted to address inequitable representation (Strand and Retzl 2016, 429). The Board is the same for the IBRD, IDA, and IFC though voting power differs, for example, the US holds only 10.06% shareholding in the IDA.

Almost all other MDBs operate along similar structures, with voting power linked to shareholding and allocated relative to their economic size. They can have higher or lower percentages of basic votes and some grant regional membership voting privileges over non-regional ones. The newly created NDB is the only MDB with equal voting power in 2020, but this may change when and if other countries are admitted. Further, some MDBs have financial institutions as shareholders in addition to countries. For example, the BOAD has eight regional member countries, the Central Bank of West African States, the AfDB and the EIB, three non-regional member states, and three financial institutions acting on behalf of Germany, India, and China. The admission of such eclectic members enabled BOAD to raise funds on bond markets, which it was previously unable to do due to capital and credit rating limitations of its regional member countries.

The shareholding system reflects a corporate governance model and is subject to similar vagaries with many MDBs having a dominant shareholder or group of shareholders, which creates problems around hegemonic power. Voting is usually pursued by consensus, but this often means appointed Directors set outcomes for their constituencies (Leech and Leech 2006). As Strand and Retzl (2016, 419) note, this is an expression of the power of major shareholders and weighted voting casts ‘long shadows over negotiations.’ There are no rules about whose interests elected Directors represent, which becomes particularly tricky in large constituencies (Leech and Leech 2006, Woods 2006), and quality control can be problematic in the absence of an independent evaluation office that reports to the Board (Ben-Artzi 2016).

5.1.2 Capital subscriptions

As shareholder banks, four factors shape MDB lending capacity: first, their size or total capitalisation; second, the amount of capital that is paid-in and the amount callable; third, the creditworthiness – or perceptions thereof – of the largest shareholders; and, fourth, their debt-to-lending ratios. When first established, the IBRD held $10 billion capital stock, which was not enough to meet Europe’s post-war reconstruction needs; hence, it was quickly superseded by the Marshall Plan. The cash-strapped British successfully argued to reduce the amount of paid-in capital from the 50% of total capital that White proposed to 20% (Gardner 1980, Mason and Asher 1973). Of the paid-in capital, only 2% had to be paid in US dollars or gold with the remainder in the member’s currency. This meant in the early years, when the US dollar was the only convertible currency, the Bank’s loanable funds were limited to contributions in dollars or gold (Mason and Asher 1973). As Engel (2010, 29) argued, the ‘small initial capital stock and even smaller paid-in component made the Bank reliant on financial markets for capital, which profoundly shaped its subsequent operations.’ Add to this a conservative debt-to-lending ratio adopted by IBRD management and clearly the Bank established a cautious business model that prioritised banking principles (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). This model was emulated in the regional, sub-regional, and specialised development banks, many of which function more as banks than development agencies (Ben-Artzi 2016), with their loan policies, financial management, and country risk assessment designed to ensure bond market approvals (Humphrey 2016).

For the IBRD in its early years, support from financial markets meant gaining allies on Wall Street (Caufield 1998). The preference for bankers as IBRD President (see Chapters 3 and 4) and in other key management roles was meant to gain investor trust. The corollary was that very few staff had development backgrounds (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). Still, in the post-war years, caution around international bonds persisted, thus raising capital was difficult for the Bank. When established in the mid-2010s, the NDB and AIIB followed the pattern of the early MDBs, with senior staff often coming across from finance sector firms like Goldman Sachs (Engel and Bazbauers 2018).

Credit rating agencies (CRAs) were a major influence on the MDBs from the outset because the ranking of MDB bonds were a major factor in their saleability. There are four key elements to CRA ratings of MDBs (Ben-Artzi 2016, Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli 2018, Humphrey 2014, Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). First, they examine if the MDB has preferred creditor status. Second, CRAs assess the soundness of the countries and projects that MDBs lend to and for. In terms of the countries lent to, this encourages the MDBs to have a substantial share of their loan portfolio with credit-worthy middle-income countries. The World Bank has come under criticism for its lending to high middle-income countries, particularly its lending to China (see Behar 2012). In terms of the soundness of individual loans, this led the IBRD to prioritise project lending in its early years, despite a mandate to finance programme lending (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). As early Bank staffer Victor Urquidi (1996, 48) said, the ‘Bank’s “bottom line” in judging a project was the “times earned column” on a spreadsheet.’ However, it has always been perceptions of project quality rather than reality that matters because of the substantial gap between when projects are approved and when they are completed and their outcomes are evaluated (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). The third way CRAs judge MDBs is the stability of their major shareholders. In other words: do they have rich industrialised member states? This is because they are the ones that would realistically be able to contribute callable capital should an MDB ever need it. The consequence is that MDBs with fewer wealthy member states have reduced access to financial markets. The AfDB, for example, admitted non-African shareholders to improve its capital base (English and Mule 1996). Fourth, CRAs use a range of financial ratios to determine MDB risk ratings, particularly equity-to-loan ratios to determine capital adequacy. Almost all MDBs have capital adequacy well above those of commercial banks and there are not many reasons for this, apart from protecting wealthy members from capital call-ins (Humphrey 2014). The IBRD gained its AAA credit rating from the major US CRAs in 1959 and kept it ever since. As Table 5.1 shows, other MDBs have not been able to achieve this, which often reflects who their major shareholders are as much as their soundness as banks.

Table 5.1 Multilateral Development Bank credit ratings 2019 and outlook

AAA | AA+ to AA − | A+ to A− | BBB+ to BBB− | BB+ to B− | No rating
AfDB (=) AIIB (=) AsDB (=) CEB (=) EBRD (=) EIB (=) IADB (=) IBRD/IDA (=) IsDB (=) NDB (=) NIB (=) | CABEI AA (=) CDB AA+ (=) | BSTDB A− (+) CAF A+ (−) FONPLATA A− (+) IBEC A− (=) IIB A− (=) | BOAD BBB+ (=) EADB BBB− (=) EDB BBB (=) | EBID B+ (=) TDB BBB (=) | AFESD BADEA BDEAC ETDB IFAD OFID PIDB

Source: Annual Reports and MDB Websites.
Note: Outlook positive (+), stable (=), negative (−).

After the 2007–8 GFC, CRAs enacted new evaluation methodologies equating the MDBs to commercial banks, even though they are effectively non-profit organisations. Consequently, Humphrey (2017, 283) argues, ‘to retain their AAA bond rating, major MDBs are (i) restricting their overall capacity to make use of their balance sheet for development projects and (ii) limiting lending to some borrowing countries facing economic difficulties.’ This impacts the poorest countries that already have difficulty accessing credit the most because the MDBs are powerful signallers to private finance. Such limits could prove problematic when the next financial crisis arrives, particularly as grant finance was hollowed out over the 2010s. Former MDB staffers note how the CRAs are ‘strategy makers and even regulators’ despite having ‘very little depth of comprehension’ about MDBs (Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli 2018, 58). CRAs regularly put demands on the MDBs, including reducing their portfolio risk and sector and country diversification. As a result of their inordinate impact, the BRICS started talks in 2015 about establishing alternatives to the US-based CRAs, but with little success. The reliance on international banking and money markets has thus created a system that priorities banking norms over development ideals.

The World Bank has increased its lending capacity in two ways over the years: first, by increasing its capital reserves and, second, by increasing its capital base. The first general capital increase (GCI) was 14 years after the Bank was established in 1959, which doubled its capitalisation; it was to ensure that increased lending did not result in too great a deterioration of its equity-to-loan ratio and was strongly supported by the US. Other shareholders have also bargained intensely to increase their capital share, as Japan did in the 1980s in the pursuit of becoming the second largest IBRD shareholder (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997).

Changes to relative IBRD shareholdings are done through Selective Capital Increases (SCIs). These generally follow IMF quota reviews and see countries offered additional shares to reflect their changed international positions, although political factors are always in the mix. This was the case in 1976 when OPEC members, whose economic influence increased after the 1973 oil shock, were offered larger shareholdings than their economies warranted as then President McNamara saw them as a potential source of new funds (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997). The second oil shock of 1979 reduced US resistance to a new GCI, which was agreed at $40 billion. Following US resistance to capital increases during the mid-1980s, there was a large $78.9 billion GCI in 1988 that shored up the Bank’s equity-to-loan ratio for quite some time. An influx of new members including Switzerland and former Soviet states led to further capital increases so that by 1995 the IBRD’s capital was $184 billion.

It took over two decades for the next GCI because, after the 1997 Asian Financial Crisis, there was a long period of relative global economic growth and stability with private financial flows on the rise. The GFC brought that to an end, and led to a $58 billion GCI under President Zoellick. This 2010 GCI was dependent on World Bank governance reforms, as were the large 2018 GCI and SCI President Kim oversaw shortly before stepping down. The 2018 capital increase was for both the IBRD’s paid-in ($7.5 billion) and callable ($52.6 billion) capital, with paid-in increases always harder to obtain. The Trump administration was critical of the Bank’s ongoing lending to China and, in return for supporting the capital increase, obtained commitments to operational reforms and loan pricing changes designed to reduce loans to China, but resulted in higher interest rate charges to all wealthier IBRD borrowers (Mayeda and Shankleman 2018).

Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli (2018, 38–9) examined 25 MDBs calculating their subscribed capital increased by an average of 5.7% per annum between 2007 and 2016 reaching $1.4 trillion, which in 2016 was equal to 1.8% of world GDP. Further, almost all MDBs retain earnings and this on average equalled 30.7% of total subscribed capital by 2016 (Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli 2018, 41). The very low costs of gaining influence by creating an MDB is likely, we think, a key reason that there are now 30 MDBs. With all the discussion about the recent establishment of the AIIB and NDB, this factor was overlooked.

5.1.3 Governance

The IBRD’s Articles of Agreement state that the Executive Directors select the Bank President. In practice, however, an informal agreement between the US and European countries means that the US proposes a presidential candidate for the Directors to approve and the Europeans propose the IMF Managing Director. A major campaign by several states, NGOs, and others started in the early 2000s pushed for a more merit-based selection process, this was epitomised by the 2012 Open Letter to all World Bank Governors signed by 59 leading development NGOs and published by the Bretton Woods Project, an NGO which critically monitors World Bank and IMF activities. But it remains the case that ‘at the end of the day he’ – and Bank Presidents have only even been men – ‘is only accountable to the President of the United States and the US Congress’ (Vestergaard 2010, 11).

All World Bank Presidents have been US citizens, though two were born overseas: James Wolfensohn in Australia and Jim Yong Kim in South Korea. The US has tended to select appointees without development backgrounds and, up to Wolfensohn, the majority were bankers, demonstrating again that it is a bank as much as, if not more so than, a development agency. Since Wolfensohn, Republican administrations have adopted a more partisan approach, with the three Republican appointees – Paul Wolfowitz, Robert Zoellick, and David Malpass – all having previously served as Republican political appointees. The last two Democratic appointees did not, however; Wolfensohn was a banker and Kim a public health specialist. This suggests that Republicans have taken a far more politicised approach to the Bank than Democrats. Still, it is not uncommon for MDB presidents to come from the political world and strong political ties may help in negotiating capital increases and replenishments (Ben-Artzi 2016).

The World Bank President guides day-to-day decisions, ‘under the direction of the Executive Directors’ (World Bank 2012). Bank Presidents are a key influence in shaping its strategic direction, as was shown in Chapters 3 and 4; they ‘were not only the source of power in the institution; they were also the ones the staff looked to for signals that would indicate the Bank’s primary mission and its operational priorities in a changing world’ (Kraske 1996, vii). Still, as with all MDBs, there are tensions between the Boards of Governors and Directors and senior management and staff, which can arise from different priorities around politics, development, and bank finances and who prioritises what can change over time (Ben-Artzi 2016).

The location of an MDB’s headquarters is political too. In the case of the IMF and World Bank, they were to ‘be located in the territory of the member holding the greatest number of shares’ (World Bank 2012). The US chose to headquarter the IBRD in Washington, DC, so it would be under close governmental influence. Subsequent MDBs mostly show a similar pattern of politicking, with head office locations being a decision by major shareholders or a backlash against them. As examples, the IADB is in Washington DC, while the AsDB is in Manila, the Philippines, to reduce member concerns about Japanese influence.

Debates about reform to World Bank governance have arisen at least once a decade both within and outside the MDB, leading to a never-ending cycle of restructuring. In terms of reform, many commentators have made the important point that MDB governance should be as sound as the MDBs expect the governance of their borrowers to be. Some outside the organisation call for reform (see inter alia Ahluwalia et al. 2016, Stiglitz 2006, Woods 2006), while others call for a more radical rethinking of international economic governance (Amin 2014, Bello, Kinley, and Elinson 1982, Cammack 2002, George and Sabelli 1994). And, yet, at the end of the day, despite regular restructuring, the Bank’s governance as delineated by its Articles of Agreement remains largely unchanged since the 1940s, a template emulated by almost all other MDBs and clearly evident in both the NDB and AIIB.

5.1.4 Loans

The World Bank offers three main loan types: investment project finance, development policy loans (DPLs), and programme-for-results lending. Investment project finance for physical and social infrastructure is the Bank’s staple lending instrument and can be approved as an IBRD loan, IDA credit, or as a guarantee. Investments can be in any sector and can only be financed by the Bank or co-financed with other development agencies either as loans or grants. DPLs provide budget support to governments based on commitment to a set of policy or institutional reforms. These originated from what was called non-project and programme lending, which comprised an average of 6% of Bank lending up until the late 1970s (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997, 487). In the 1980s, the Bank launched structural adjustment loans (SALs) and sectoral adjustment loans (SECALs), which were conditional on macroeconomic changes. Adjustment lending peaked at around 30% of loans in the 1980s then declined in the 1990s. DPLs replaced SALs and SECALs in 2004 and made up roughly one-quarter of financing between 2005 and 2015, largely due to a spike in overall lending and emergency responses to the GFC (World Bank 2020). This is the most controversial lending instrument as it involves the Bank interfering in a country’s macroeconomic policies. Compared to the coercive reputation of SALs and SECALs, DPLs are meant to be borrower-owned and -led, but the degree to which this is the case is questionable. Programme-for-results lending, previously known as programme lending, focusses investment on specific sectors. Funding is disbursed when pre-agreed results are achieved. This third instrument is focussed on lending to ‘high-performing’ countries. In addition, the Bank offers tailored loan programmes, but the three above loan types receive the bulk of annual approvals. The Bank also has several trust funds and grant facilities with different donors and these finances are often allocated along with a Bank loan. To develop loans, the Bank offers extensive technical assistance services (see Bazbauers 2018 for a detailed history).

Harry Dexter White’s first IBRD draft went into detail about lending operations (Oliver 1971), which likely reflected his concern to ensure the exploitative lending of the inter-war years was not repeated. Further, White judged that the below-market interest rates on offer would produce a good demand for loans, which has not in fact generally been the case for the IBRD. The IDA, however, tends to be oversubscribed because of its highly concessional terms. Many of White’s ideas are inscribed in the Bank’s Articles of Agreement and into those of subsequent MDBs. Loan conditions are specified in Article III, Section 4 and they start with the requirement that states guarantee loan repayments made in their territory regardless of who it is to. Next, to make sure Bank funds did not compete with private banks, the IBRD had to be satisfied that the loan could not be secured from the market. Section 4 continues in outlining that loans and guarantees, except in special circumstances, must ‘be for the purpose of specific projects of reconstruction and development’ (World Bank 2012). Further, interest rates must be ‘reasonable’ and, to ensure the productive use of loans, a ‘competent committee’ must study each proposal and complete a written report on it (Mason and Asher 1973). Debt was also a major concern of post-war planners, so the IBRD was tasked with making prudent assessments of the borrower’s capacity to repay. And, so, the aim was to create a cautious lending programme based on market ideals and framed by (Western) experts (Engel 2010).

Article 4, Point 10 of the IBRD’s establishing agreement on political non-interference gives ‘complete discretion’ for terms and conditions, meaning that an action is non-political if the Bank says it is (Mason and Asher 1973, 27). The artificial distinction between politics and economics in Point 10 has allowed the Bank to promote clearly political economic policies and prescriptions. Even loan conditions have been political, given that they grew with the rise of neoliberal SALs and SECALs in the 1980s and then declined in part because of their lack of efficacy.

Conditionality is the product of a three-way interaction between the Bank, shareholders, and borrowers, with more powerful borrowing countries being less subject to conditionality; influential shareholders only come into play if they have particular support for, or concerns about, loans to a borrower (Hernandez 2017). The availability of finance from other sources – the private sector and other donors – is also a factor shaping the level and impact of conditionality. Focussing on the availability from other states, Hernandez (2017) found that increased lending from China was associated with a decline in Bank conditionality on loans in 54 African states. While Hernandez (2017) regards conditions positively as a way of increasing aid effectiveness and protecting resources, progressive scholars and NGOs have argued that they often undermine the state and harm the well-being of the poor (Bello 1994, Cammack 2002, Carroll 2010, SAPRIN 2004).

The World Bank’s terminology for loan conditions has changed over the decades, thus if you are reading loan documents available from the Bank’s project database, you might see terms like ‘pre-requisites,’ ‘policy action,’ ‘triggers,’ and ‘challenges.’ Conditions can be targeted at the macro- and mid-levels and the project level. DPLs focus on macro- and mid-level conditionality. In investment loans, conditions relate to the sector the loan is in. For example, the West Bengal Major Irrigation and Flood Management Project approved in 2019 called some of its conditions its ‘theory of change’ and included a condition of outsourcing operations and maintenance ‘to irrigation contractors on a performance basis’ (World Bank 2019, 7). This demonstrates the Bank’s commitment to private sector provision of public services funded by its loans. Investment loan conditions can have even broader implications for a sector, for example, a loan for a power plant in Vietnam required not only a private provider to build and operate the plant, but also legislation to promote the expansion of private providers in the sector, despite decades of problems in privatised electricity (Engel 2010).

Projects are evaluated by their expected rates of return, though the country’s overall creditworthiness is also a factor (Kapur, Lewis, and Webb 1997, Urquidi 1996). As early as 1949, due in part to the low level and poor quality of loan applications, the Bank established a system of technical assistance to develop, assess, and supervise projects (Bazbauers 2018). It also assisted with broader state macroeconomic planning and management. Both were done with the assistance of ‘fly-in, fly-out’ Western experts. Within two decades, the Bank had built four technical assistance pillars, a structure emulated by several other MDBs. These pillars included technical assistance embedded within projects to support implementation, stand-alone technical assistance project that often guided capacity development, survey missions that reviewed a recipient’s development status to propose future lending schedules, and professional training institutes delivering courses and seminars to senior public servants (Bazbauers 2018).

The World Bank requires projects to be managed in accordance with Bank-set accounting, auditing, and other standards, though in some ‘high-performing’ countries the Bank allows the use of local project management systems. All Bank loans are subject to social and environmental safeguards, though the efficacy of these has long been a matter of debate, with NGOs and academics pointing to limitations. The Bank also has policies around anti-corruption in project management and procurement. And, under pressure from the US, the Bank established an Inspection Panel in 1993 to allow people negatively affected by its projects a means of redress. As Park (2017) outlines, institutional isomorphism saw most of the other RDBs follow suit over the next decade.

In terms of procurement, the Articles of Agreement were ahead of their time in specifying that loans must be untied; tied aid requires recipients to spend aid in the donor country. Bilateral Western donors have made commitments since at least the late 1980s to progress the untying of their aid particularly for the least developed countries and low-income countries but have not yet fully achieved this. Still, formal untying of procurement from donor states can be misleading, as Bracking (2009) notes there is an expectation that the largest shareholders will be the largest beneficiaries of contracts from MDBs and other development finance institutions (DFIs). In the 1990s, the US, UK, Germany, Japan, and France were the largest beneficiaries of procurement in the World Bank (51.5% of total), AsDB (98.6%), and IADB (86.3%), though they only accounted for 20% of AfDB procurement (Bracking 2009, 119). By the mid-2000s, China and India had risen dramatically up the World Bank list, dominating in civil works contracts, and they were followed by Brazil as the next largest beneficiary. In consultancy contracts, Indonesia and the Russian Federation have joined the US, the UK, and France in the top five. Of course, the beneficiaries of winning contractors are not always clear in today’s globalised marketplace; contracts won by the Indonesian office of a global consultancy firm likely flow through tax havens to top income earners in the Global North.

The World Bank provides the framework for how project procurement should be undertaken and requires all Bank-financed work to be done by contractors and not the state. In terms of contracting out, in a small number of cases the Bank allows direct selection, essentially where there is only one suitable firm to provide the work or where there is a strong reason for a preferred firm. Most of the work, however, is put through open, competitive procurement. For small contracts, this may be limited to contractors in the borrower state, but the preferred mechanism is international competition. This requirement dates to loan agreements approved in 1951 (Mason and Asher 1973, 26). Competition for these contracts is complex and requires high-level technical and legal skills, access to technology and finance, and there is often a preference for larger companies that have the scale to complete complex projects (Bracking 2009). Many Western governments have long had special programmes to help their firms bid for projects and they utilise their in-country networks with government officials to benefit their companies; in other words, they adopt crony practices and North firms are not adverse to paying bribes to win projects. In practice, the lowest cost bid is not necessarily the best quality and once a company has won a contract through a low-cost bid, they can often negotiate further funding to complete it. International procurement also means that Global South countries are largely buying goods and services from places that are more developed than they are, either from the Global North or from a handful of large emerging economies like China, Brazil, and India. Thus, their debt repayments embody the labour costs – either directly in technical assistance or indirectly through the price of goods – of people paid more, often much more, than most workers in the poorest countries. In other words, MDB loans promote what Marxists label unequal exchange (Amin 2014).

Loan rates and charges vary in the World Bank dependent on the recipient country’s gross national income (GNI) per capita. Low-income countries (set as GNI below $1,025 in 2020) are eligible for IDA loans, which are highly concessional. Lower-middle income countries (GNI between $1,026 and $3,995 in 2010) can receive a blend of IBRD and IDA loans. Upper-middle income countries (GNI between $3,996 and $12,375) are eligible for IBRD loans only, which are on harder terms. As of April 2020, regular IDA loans had a maturity of 38 years, a six-year grace period where no repayments are made, and an interest rate of 3.125%; terms for small economies are slightly more generous, while for somewhat wealthier states eligible for a blend of IBRD and IDA loans, they are harder. The commitment charge for loans was zero. IBRD rates are a lot more variable depending on the term of the loan (8–20 years), the currency borrowed in, whether the loan was fixed or variable, and GNI per capita of the country. Interest rates are set in relation to the London Inter-Bank Offered Rate (LIBOR), which is an interest rate average determined from estimates given by major London banks. In April 2020, they ranged between LIBOR +0.65% and +2.05% and the loans had a front-end fee and commitment fee each of 0.25%.

Earlier in the chapter, we outlined the key factors shaping assessments of MDB creditworthiness, which determine how cheaply they can borrow and, in turn, on-lend for. Examining the IBRD, IADB, and CAF, Humphrey (2014) demonstrated that the IBRD can borrow most cheaply, followed by the IADB, which has a large US shareholding, while the CAF faces higher costs because its shareholders are regional states. But the different institutions have also taken different positions on net income, decisions about how much is used to build up reserves and equity (in lieu of increases in paid-in capital), and allocation of net income to alternate financing streams, in particular to technical assistance, trust funds, and concessional arms. CAF has focussed on minimising costs to borrowers, so its loans are not as expensive as would be expected given their cost of borrowing, while the IADB is closer to the World Bank in terms of interest rates (Humphrey 2014). The IBRD could lend more cheaply if it were not for these decisions.

5.1.5 Comparing the IBRD and other MDBs

Each of the above sections – voting rights, capital subscriptions, governance, and loans – has made some comparisons to other MDBs, demonstrating that many key features are shared among them. Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli (2018, 112) regard the MDBs as ‘a family of peer cross-referenced institutions adhering to common norms and standards, with large MDBs often acting as role models.’ Table 5.2, however, provides a more systematic comparison of the IBRD to the regional, sub-regional, and specialised development banks.

Table 5.2 Key features of the structure of IBRD and variations in other MDBs

Issue | IBRD | Variations in other MDBs
Organisational Structure |

Structured like a company.

For-profit.

Largest shareholders are non-borrowers.

|

Structured like the IBRD.

Can be non-profit, e.g., the EIB; specific profits must be re-invested, e.g., the CABEI; or, have a special class of institutional shares that generate dividends, e.g., the TDB.

Can be led by borrowers, non-borrowers, or some balance between them.

Membership |

member states that must be IMF shareholders.

|

Can have non-IMF member states, other MDBs, and other financial institutions as members.

Smallest membership is five for the NDB.

Management |

Board of Governors representing all member states is supreme governing authority. They control decisions requiring more than a majority vote and elect appointees to the Board of Directors.

Board of Directors is responsible for strategic direction and lending operation approval but, in practice, Bank management has a lot of power. Originally 12 Executive Directors, now 25.

|

All MDBs have the same basic structure.

The AfDB, AsDB, CABEI, CDB, EBRD, and IADB have resident Executive Directors, most others have non-resident ones.

Only the EIB has a larger number of Executive Directors than the World Bank; the average is around 14 and the smallest five: the ETDB and NDB.

The AIIB, CAF, and TDB have greater delegations to management for loan approvals than the major MDBs. AIIB delegates decisions up to $300 million to management, meaning little Board oversight.

The EIB has a Management Committee that comprised the President and Vice Presidents.

Shareholding and Voting |

Originally, shareholdings were to reflect relative size of economy globally, later contributions to IDA became part of formula. There are still misalignments.

Shareholders get one vote for each share of stock held plus their basic votes; originally 250 basic votes but this was changed to 5.55% of all votes, though in practice it is less.

Executive Directors have the number of votes of the shareholders they represent and cannot split their votes.

Largest shareholder is the US with 15.76% of votes.

| The MDBs can have:

Higher or lower portions of basic votes, e.g., the AsDB has 20% basic votes.

Only votes per share, e.g. the NDB and EBRD.

Additional votes for founding members, e.g., the AIIB founding members get an additional 600 votes each.

Voting power linked to whether countries are regional or non-regional members; regional members generally must have the dominant shareholding, e.g., the AsDB regional membership must be 60% minimum; the AfDB has the lowest voting share of regional members at 59%.

Shareholders may be limited to borrowing states; split between borrowing and non-borrowing members (e.g., the BDEAC has 2% non-borrowing members, while the IADB’s Articles specify equal split between borrowing and non-borrowing shareholdings); fully owned by non-borrowers, e.g., the BADEA and OFID.

| |

Equal shareholdings and votes for each member, the NDB has this and the CABEI originally had this.

Groups of countries with equal votes, e.g., the IFAD has DAC, OPEC, and G77 groupings with equal votes.

Limits on all members maximum shareholding, e.g., the TDB has a 15% limit.

One vote per Executive Director regardless of shareholding, e.g., the NIB.

Executive Directors can split votes in the AsDB, EBRD, and IsDB.

Voting Majorities |

Majority of weighted votes is required for most decisions. In practice, most votes are by consensus but voting power shapes negotiations.

Double majority (majority of votes cast by member majority) for: suspension of members or operations and distributions.

Super majority (75% of total voting power) for: increases in capital stock; currencies of lending; approving securities that the Bank can purchase.

Super majority (60% of members with 85% of voting power) for: amendments to the Articles.

Unanimous agreement to modify clauses on the right to withdraw from Bank, rights to subscribe to increases in authorised capital stock, and limits on liability.

|

Most MDBs have simple majority votes for regular decisions, though there are quite a few exceptions where more than 51% is required (the AfDB, CAF, ETDB, and IIB), while the NIB requires unanimity. Like the IBRD, practice tends to be by consensus.

Special majority is required for similar decisions as per the IBRD Articles, with most just having one set of special majorities not the IBRD’s three. They generally require 66% of Governors having 75% of voting power but there are variations.

President and Staff |

Meant to be elected by the Executive Directors, but by informal agreement is selected by the US. Reforms to create a more merit-based selection process have had limited impact.

President is legal representative and chief executive officer with a five-year term and a maximum of two terms.

Largest MDB with over 11,000 staff with around 60% in Washington, DC, headquarters and 40% in resident missions.

|

Presidents are generally elected by Board of Governors and are often citizens of regional member states.

Senior appointments tend to be political in most MDBs.

Five-year terms are common; second terms often allowed.

Largest staffing after the IBRD is the AsDB with just over 3,000. It also has a relatively high percentage of its staff based at headquarters, whereas the AfDB have over 40% of staff decentralised.

Location of Headquarters |

In territory of largest member state. The US insisted on Washington, DC.

|

Headquarters is often linked to the distribution of regional institutions across member states.

At least six located in non-borrowing countries.

The OFID is the only MDB with headquarters in a non-member state.

Capitalisation |

The IBRD originally capitalised at $100 million, increased through GCIs and SCIs approved by Board of Governors.

In 2018, capitalised at $274.7 billion. 2018 Annual Meetings agreed to a further $60.1 billion increase, making it again the largest MDB.

Originally 20% of IBRD capital was paid-in with the rest callable, of the paid-in 2% had to be gold or hard currency like US dollars; now 6–7% of capital is paid-in.

The IFC has 100% paid-in capital and the IDA around 75%.

|

Three other MDBs have subscribed capital over $100 billion – the EIB, IADB, and AsDB. The AIIB is just below $100 billion.

Mid-tier MDBs have around $50 billion – the AsDB, IsDB, and NDB. The EBRD has $30 billion.

Smaller MDBs have less than $10 billion. The smallest – the PIDB – has just over $8 million.

MDBs often start with higher paid-in capital and it reduces over time as they gain creditworthiness, e.g., the AIIB has 20% paid-in capital, RDBs had an average of 10% in 2016, and SRDBs had an average of 44% in 2016; this high level increases their lending capacity – the CAF had 68% paid-in capital and a high level of reserves.

Concessional Arm |

The IDA was established in 1961, requires regular replenishments which are very political

The IBRD has transferred a share of profits to the IDA as did the IFC, but they stopped in 2018.

From 2018, the IDA will raise funds on private markets.

|

The AfDB has the AfDF and NTF.

The AsDB has the AsDF, which merged its balance sheet into Ordinary Capital Resources in 2015.

The IADB has the FSO, which also merged in 2016.

The IFAD is mostly funded by replenishments.

The IsDB has the IsDF.

Focus on Lending |

No political interference.

Finances projects that the private sector will not.

Instruments: investment and policy loans, credits, technical assistance, guarantees, and equity investments.

Social and economic conditions.

Social and environmental safeguards supported by an independent evaluation office and an Inspection Panel.

Outstanding loan portfolio in 2019: IBRD $192.8 billion; IDA $151.9 billion; Total $344.7 billion.

Loans average 2017–19:

IBRD: commitments $22.9 billion, gross disbursements $18.5 billion, and net disbursements $8.2 billion; IDA: commitments $21.8 billion, gross disbursements $14.9 billion, and net disbursements $9.9 billion.

|

The EBRD promotes democracy.

Many MDBs promote regional integration.

Instruments: many have only investment and no policy lending, most offer equity investments but only some offer lines of credit, grants, technical assistance, and guarantees.

Many MDBs have less or no conditionality, i.e., the IsDB has none.

Around half have some safeguards and, where they do, they tend to be similar and be supported by an independent evaluation office and inspection panel.

The EIB has the largest outstanding loan portfolio at over $500 billion 2019 and $54 billion in loan disbursements plus a further $11.5 billion for the EIF; the BSTDB as an example of small MDB had $1.4 billion portfolio and $555 million in loan disbursements in 2019.

Most MDBs have top five borrowers that account for half of their outstanding loans (see Engen & Prizzon, 2018 for comparison of loan portfolios).

Lending Terms |

IBRD loans: variable depending on loan term (8–20 years), currency borrowed in, fixed or variable, and GNI per capita of the country; interest rates between LIBOR +0.65 to +2.05%, front-end fee and commitment fee each 0.25%.

IDA loans: 38 years maturity, 6 years grace period, no commitment charge, interest rate 3.125%; terms vary a little depending on borrower GNI.

|

Shorter and longer repayment periods and different interest rate regimes, e.g., revisable interest rates.

Trade loans generally have shorter terms than investment loans.

SRDBs interest rates are 130–40 basis points higher than the World Bank and RDBs.

Procurement |

Non-members states are eligible unconditionally to compete for contracts

Bank specifies procurement standards as part of loans, though in some cases borrowers can utilise their own systems.

|

Most MDBs allows non-members to compete but a few allow it on worse terms or not for special funds.

The CDB, IADB, and IIB do not allow non-members to compete nor do the AsDB and NDB though they have exceptions.

Smaller MDBs tend not to specify procurement procedures.

Other Arms |

The IFC for private sector lending.

The MIGA for investment guarantees.

The ICSD for dispute settlement.

|

Most fund private sector (non-sovereign) operations from main entity but two have arms like the IFC – the IADB and IsDB.

The IsDB has an arm like the MIGA.

The EIB funds non-sovereign operations from its main entity but also has separate small and medium enterprise arm and another arm a bit like the MIGA.

Other Services and Funds |

Funds and services for technical advice, trust funds.

|

Most MDBs provide technical assistance and see this as an area of comparative advantage.

Some have trust funds, e.g., the EIB has technical assistance trust funds plus several facilities to support private sector investment, public-private partnerships, and pre-investment studies.

Research and Training |

The IBRD has a Research Division and the World Bank Institute (formerly the Economic Development Institute), which funds research, partners with academia, and runs seminars and conferences (Bazbauers, 2018).

Engen and Prizzon (2018) calculated that the Bank produced over 22,000 research papers since 2000.

|

Only the larger MDBs have research units and only a few have training units, e.g., the EIB Institute, IsDB’s Islamic Research and Training Institute, and the African and Asian Development Bank Institutes.

Sources: MDB Websites and Annual Reports and Engen and Prizzon (2018), Delikanli, Dimitrov, and Agolli (2018), Griffith-Jones (2001), Humphrey (2019)